[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Steel is mainly an alloy of",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron and Carbon",
            "b) Sulphur and Zinc",
            "c) Zinc and tin",
            "d) Phosphorous and Tin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steel is alloy of iron and carbon. Apart from carbon, a small percent of manganese, sulphur, phosphorous, chrome, nickel, and copper are added to give special properties to steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a  disadvantage of Steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High strength per unit mass",
            "b) High durability",
            "c) Fire and corrosion resistance",
            "d) Reusable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Steel has high strength per unit mass, highly durable, and is reusable. But steel is poor in fire and corrosion resistance, it needs to be protected."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Elastic Modulus of Steel is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 x 109 N/mm2",
            "b) 2.0 x 105 N/mm2",
            "c) 2.0 x 105 N/m2",
            "d) 1.5 x 109 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Elastic modulus = Stress/Strain. As per IS 800-2007, elastic modulus of steel is 2.0 x 10⁵ N/mm²."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Unit mass of Steel = ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 785 kg/m3",
            "b) 450 kg/m3",
            "c) 450 kg/cm3",
            "d) 7850 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per IS 800-2007, unit mass of steel is 7850 kg/m³. A steel member with small section which has little self-weight is able to resist heavy loads  because steel members have high strength per unit weight."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Poisson’s ratio of steel is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 1.0",
            "c) 0.3",
            "d) 2.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Poisson’s ratio = transverse strain/axial strain. As per IS 800-2007, Poisson’s ratio of steel is 0.3 in elastic range and it is 0.5  in plastic range."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Structural Steel normally has carbon content less than _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0%",
            "b) 0.6%",
            "c) 3.0%",
            "d) 5.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Structural Steel  normally have a carbon content less than 0.6%. Carbon content increases hardness, yield and tensile strength of steel but it decreases ductility and toughness."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "What is the permissible percentage of Sulphur and Phosphorous content in steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1%, 0.12%",
            "b) 1.0%, 3.0%",
            "c) 3.0%, 1.0%",
            "d) 1.0%, 1.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sulphur content is generally between 0.02 – 0.1%. If more than 0.1%, it decreases strength and ductility of steel. If Phosphorous is more than 0.12%, it reduces shock resistance, ductility and strength of steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "What happens when Manganese is added to steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) decreases strength and hardness of steel",
            "b) improves corrosion resistance",
            "c) decreases ductility",
            "d) improves strength and hardness of steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Manganese is added to improve strength and hardness of steel . Based on Manganese content, steel are classified as Carbon Manganese steel (Mn >1%) and Carbon Steel (Mn <1%). If its content exceeds 1.5%, it increases the formation of martensite and hence decreases ductility and toughness."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the effect of increased content of Sulphur and Phosphorous in Steel ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) yields high strength",
            "b) affects weldability",
            "c) increases resistance to corrosion",
            "d) improves resistance to high temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When sulphur and phosphorous is used beyond 0.06%, it imparts brittleness and affects weldability and fatigue strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Which of the following is added to steel to increase resistance to corrosion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon",
            "b) Manganese",
            "c) Sulphur",
            "d) Copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Addition of small quantity of copper increases resistance to corrosion. Even Chrome and Nickel are added to impart corrosion resistance property to steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Chrome and Nickel are added to Steel to improve _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) corrosion resistance and high temperature resistance",
            "b) strength",
            "c) ductility",
            "d) weldablity"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Increased quantity of carbon and manganese imparts higher tensile strength and yield properties but lowers ductility which is more difficult to weld."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the property of high carbon steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) high toughness",
            "b) reduced ductility",
            "c) high strength",
            "d) reduced strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High carbon steel contains high carbon content. Hence it has reduced ductility, toughness and weldability."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "High carbon steel is used in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transmission lines and microwave towers",
            "b) structural buildings",
            "c) fire resistant buildings",
            "d) for waterproofing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High carbon steel is used in transmission lines and microwave towers where relatively light members are joint by bolting."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "What is the permissible percentage of micro-alloys in medium and high strength micro-alloyed steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1%",
            "b) 0.5%",
            "c) 0.25%",
            "d) 1.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Medium and High strength micro-alloyed steel have low carbon content, but alloys such as niobium, vanadium, titanium or boron are added to achieve high strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Fire resistant steels are also called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stainless steel",
            "b) Weathering steel",
            "c) High strength steel",
            "d) Thermomechanically treated steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fire resistant steels are also called as thermomechanically treated steel. They perform better than ordinary steel under fire."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "What is the minimum percentage of chromium and nickel  added to stainless steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5%, 10.5%",
            "b) 2%, 20%",
            "c) 10.5%, 0.5%",
            "d) 30%, 50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stainless steel are low carbon steels to which a minimum of 10.5% chromium (maximum 20%) and 0.5% nickel is added."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "6. Match the pair of Type of steel with its ultimate tensile strength :<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\tTYPE OF STEEL\t\t\t\t\tULTIMATE TENSILE CAPACITY\n(A) Carbon Steel \t\t\t\t\t(i) 700-950 MPa\n(B) High Strength Carbon Steel\t\t\t\t(ii) 440-590 MPa\n(C) Weathering Steel\t\t\t\t\t(iii) 410-440 MPa\n(D) High Strength quenched &amp; tempered steel\t\t(iv) 480 MPa\n(E) Medium and High strength microalloyed steel\t        (v) 480-550 MPa</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii, D-iv, E-v",
            "b) A-v, B-iv, C-iii, D-ii, E-i",
            "c) A-iii, B-v, C-iv, D-i, E-ii",
            "d) A-ii, B-iii, C-v, D-i, E-iv"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ultimate tensile strength is the capacity of material to withstand loads tending to elongate. It is the maximum stress that a material can withstand while being stretched or pulled. The ultimate tensile strength for Carbon Steel is 410-440 MPa, 480-550 MPa for High Strength Carbon Steel,  480 MPa for Weathering Steel, 700-950 MPa for High Strength quenched & tempered steel, 440-590 MPa for Medium and High strength microalloyed steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is weathering steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) low-alloy atmospheric corrosion-resistant steel",
            "b) low-carbon steel",
            "c) high strength quenched and tempered steel",
            "d) fire resistant steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Weathering steel are low-alloy atmospheric corrosion-resistant steel. They are often left unpainted. They have an ultimate tensile strength of 480 MPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "8. Match the pair of Type of steel with its yield strength:<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\tTYPE OF STEEL\t\t\t\t\tYIELD STRENGTH\n(A) Carbon Steel \t\t\t\t\t(i) 300-450 MPa\n(B) High Strength Carbon Steel\t\t\t\t(ii) 350 MPa\n(C) Weathering Steel\t\t\t\t\t(iii) 350-400 MPa\n(D) High Strength quenched &amp; tempered steel\t\t(iv) 230-300MPa\n(E) Medium and High strength microalloyed steel\t        (v) 550-700 MPa</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii, D-iv, E-v",
            "b) A-i, B-iii, C-v, D-iv, E-ii",
            "c) A-v, B-iv, C-iii, D-ii, E-i",
            "d) A-iv, B-iii, C-ii, D-v, E-i"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Yield Strength is the stress that a material can withstand without any permanent deformation i.e. the point of stress at which any material starts to deform plastically. The yield strength of carbon steel is 230-300MPa, 350-400 MPa for High Strength Carbon Steel, 350 MPa for Weathering Steel, 550-700 MPa for High Strength quenched & tempered steel, 300-450 MPa for Medium and High strength microalloyed steel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct criteria to be considered while designing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structure should be aesthetically pleasing but structurally unsafe",
            "b) Structure should be cheap in cost even though it may be structurally unsafe",
            "c) Structure should be structurally safe but less durable",
            "d) Structure should be adequately safe, should have adequate serviceability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Structure should be designed such that it fulfils it intended purpose during its lifetime and be adequately safe in terms of strength, stability and structural integrity and have adequate serviceability. Structure should also be economically viable, aesthetically pleasing and environment friendly."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "What is serviceability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It refers to condition when structure is not usable",
            "b) It refers to services offered in the structure",
            "c) It means that the structure should perform satisfactorily under different loads, without discomfort to user",
            "d) It means that structure should be economically viable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Serviceability is related to utility of structure. The structure should perform satisfactorily under service loads, without discomfort to user due to excessive deflection, cracking, vibration, etc. Other considerations of serviceability are durability, impermeability, acoustic and thermal insulation etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Analysis is referred to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) determination of cost of structure",
            "b) determination of axial forces, bending moment, shear force etc.",
            "c) determination of factor of safety",
            "d) drafting architectural plans and drawings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Analysis refers to determination of axial forces, bending moment, shear force, torsional moments etc. acting on different members of structure due to applied loads and their combinations."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "The structure is statically indeterminate when________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) static equilibrium equations are insufficient for determining internal forces and reactions on that structure",
            "b) static equilibrium equations are sufficient for determining internal forces and reactions on that structure",
            "c) structure is economically viable",
            "d) structure is environment friendly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the static equilibrium equations are insufficient for determining internal forces and reactions on that structure, the structure is said to be statically indeterminate. Analysis of these structures is complex and cannot be analysed only by using laws of statics, various analytical methods like slope deflection method, moment distribution method, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which of the following is one of the methods of analysis prescribed in the code for steel structures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hinge Analysis",
            "b) Limit Analysis",
            "c) Roller Analysis",
            "d) Dynamic Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Code suggests the use of any of the following methods for steel structures : (i) elastic analysis, (ii) plastic analysis, (iii) advanced analysis, (iv) dynamic analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which method is mainly adopted for design of steel structures as per IS code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limit State Method",
            "b) Working Stress Method",
            "c) Ultimate Load Method",
            "d) Earthquake Load Method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steel structures and their elements are normally designed by limit state method. When limit state method cannot be conveniently adopted, working stress method may be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Which IS code is used for general construction of steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 456",
            "b) IS 256",
            "c) IS 800",
            "d) IS 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS 800:2007 is the code of practice for general construction in steel. It is issued by Bureau of Indian Standards."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Permissible Stress = Yield Stress x Factor of Safety",
            "b) Permissible Stress = Yield Stress / Factor of Safety",
            "c) Yield Stress = Permissible Stress /  Factor of Safety",
            "d) Permissible Stress = Yield Stress – Factor of Safety"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Permissible Stress = Yield Stress / Factor of Safety. Permissible Stress is the amount of stress that will not cause failure. It is a fraction of yield stress. It takes care of overload or other unknown factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "In Working Stress Method, which of the following relation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Working Stress ≤ Permissible Stress",
            "b) Working Stress ≥ Permissible Stress",
            "c) Working Stress = Permissible Stress",
            "d) Working Stress > Permissible Stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Working Stress Method, Working Stress ≤ Permissible Stress. Each member is checked for number of different combinations of loadings."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "What is Load Factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ratio of working load to ultimate load",
            "b) product of working load and ultimate load",
            "c) product of working load and factor of safety",
            "d) ratio of ultimate load to working load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In working stress method, the factor of safety for the above are as follows : (i) for tension members = 1.67, (ii) for long column = 1.92, (iii) for short columns = 1.67, (iv) for connections = 2.5-3."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a main element of framed structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beam",
            "b) Column",
            "c) Shear connector",
            "d) Lattice member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Load Factor = working load / ultimate load. In ultimate load design, different types of loads and load combinations have different load factors assigned."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following are subjected to both axial loads and bending moments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beam-Column",
            "b) Column",
            "c) Lattice member",
            "d) Beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For framed structure, the main elements are beam, column, beam-column, tie and lattice members."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "How much percentage increase of permissible stress is allowed when dead load, live load and wind load are considered together in working stress method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%",
            "b) 33%",
            "c) 40%",
            "d) 60%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Beams are those elements which are subjected to bending moments and shear force only. Columns are subjected to axial loads. Beam-Column is subjected to axial load and bending moment. In special cases, beams are subjected to torsional moments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Limit State Method is based on _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) calculations on service load conditions alone",
            "b) calculations on ultimate load conditions alone",
            "c) calculations at working loads and ultimate loads",
            "d) calculations on earthquake loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Working stress method is based on calculations on service load conditions alone. Ultimate Strength method is based on calculations on ultimate load conditions alone. In Limit State method, safety at ultimate loads and serviceability at working loads are considered."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "What is limit state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptable limits for safety and serviceability requirements before failure occurs",
            "b) Acceptable limits for safety and serviceability requirements after failure occurs",
            "c) Acceptable limits for safety after failure occurs",
            "d) Acceptable limits for serviceability after failure occurs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Acceptable limits for safety and serviceability requirements before failure occurs is called limit state. In Limit State design, structures are designed on the basis of safety against failure and are checked for serviceability requirements."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Which of the following format is used in limit state method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single safety factor",
            "b) Multiple safety factor",
            "c) Load factor",
            "d) Wind factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Limit state method uses multiple safety factor format that helps to provide adequate safety at ultimate loads and adequate serviceability at service loads, by considering all possible limit states. Multiple safety factor format is also called partial safety factor format."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors is included in the limit state of strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fire",
            "b) Failure by excessive deformation",
            "c) Corrosion",
            "d) Repairable damage or crack due to fatigue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Limit state of strength are prescribed to avoid collapse of structure which may endanger safety of life and property. It includes (i) loss of equilibrium of whole or part of structure, (ii) loss of stability of structure as a whole or part of structure, (iii) failure by excessive deformation, (iv) fracture due to fatigue , (v) brittle fracture."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors is included in the limit state of serviceability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brittle facture",
            "b) Fracture due to fatigue",
            "c) Failure by excessive deformation",
            "d) Deformation and deflection adversely affecting appearance or effective use of structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Limit state of serviceability includes (i) deformation and deflection adversely affecting appearance or effective use of structure, (ii) vibrations in structure or any part of its compound limiting its functional effectiveness, (iii) repairable repair or crack due to fatigue, (iv) corrosion, (v) fire."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "What is permanent action according to classification of actions by IS code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) due to self weight",
            "b) due to construction and service stage loads",
            "c) due to accidents",
            "d) due to earthquake loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Permanent actions are actions due to self weight of structural and non structural components, fittings, ancillaries, fixed equipments etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "What is variable action according to classification of actions by IS code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) due to self weight",
            "b) due to accidents",
            "c) due to construction and service stage loads",
            "d) due to earthquake loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Variable actions are actions due to construction and service stage loads such as imposed loads, wind loads, earthquake loads, etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design Load = Characteristic Load",
            "b) Design Load = Characteristic Load + Partial factor of safety",
            "c) Design Load = Characteristic Load / Partial factor of safety",
            "d) Design Load = Characteristic Load x Partial factor of safety"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Design Load = Partial factor of safety x Characteristic Load.\nThis partial safety factor accounts for possibility of unfavourable deviation of load from characteristic value, inaccurate assessment of load, uncertainty in assessment of effects of load and in assessment of limit state being considered."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": " Which of the following relation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design Strength = Ultimate strength + Partial factor of safety",
            "b) Design Strength = Ultimate strength – Partial factor of safety",
            "c) Design Strength = Ultimate strength /Partial factor of safety",
            "d) Design Strength = Ultimate strength x Partial factor of safety"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Design Strength = Ultimate strength /Partial factor of safety.\nThis partial safety factor accounts for possibility of unfavourable deviation of material strength from characteristic value, variation of member sizes, reduction in member strength due to fabrication and tolerances and uncertainty in calculation of strength of members."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following criteria is to be satisfied in selection of member in limit state method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Factored Load > Factored Strength",
            "b) Factored Load ≤ Factored Strength",
            "c) Factored Load ≥ Factored Strength",
            "d) Sometimes Factored Load < Factored Strength (or) Factored Load > Factored Strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Limit Sate method is also known as load and resistance factor design. Load factors are applied to service loads and then theoretical strength of member is reduced by application of resistance factor.  The criteria is to be satisfied in selection of member in limit state method is factored load ≤ factored strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "The partial factor of safety for resistance governed by yielding is :",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.10",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 2.0",
            "d) 1.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Partial factor of safety for resistance governed by yielding and resistance of member to buckling is 1.10. The loads are multiplied or resistances are divided by this factor to get design values."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The partial factor of safety for resistance governed by ultimate strength is :",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.10",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 2.0",
            "d) 1.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Partial factor of safety for resistance governed by ultimate strength is 1.25. Factors affecting ultimate strength are stability, fatigue and plastic collapse. The loads are multiplied or resistances are divided by this factor to get design values."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": " Which IS code is used for calculating different loads on different structures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 800",
            "b) IS 200",
            "c) IS 300",
            "d) IS 875"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IS 875 (all 5 parts) is recommended by Bureau of Indian Standards for calculating various types of loads on the structure. Part 1 is for dead loads, part 2 for imposed loads, part 3 for wind load, part 4 for snow loads and part 5 for special loads and combinations."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Which of the following load is to be considered on liquid retaining structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydrostatic load",
            "b) wave and current load",
            "c) earth pressure",
            "d) dynamic load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrostatic load is considered on liquid retaining structures or hydraulic structures. Wave and current load is considered in marine and offshore structure. Earth pressure is considered in basements, retaining walls, column footings, etc.  Dynamic load is due to earthquake and wind."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "What is P-Δ effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) earthquake load",
            "b) second order moments arising from joint displaced",
            "c) second order moments arising from member deflection",
            "d) load due to shrinkage effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Second order moments arising from joint displaced is called P-Δ effect and second order moments arising from member deflection is called P-δ effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "4. Match the pair :<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\t(A) Mass and gravitational effect\t\t(i) wind load\n\t(B) Mass and acceleration effect \t\t(ii) load due to settlement\n\t(C) Environmental effects\t\t\t(iii) imposed load</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii",
            "b) A-iii, B-ii, C-i",
            "c) A-iii, B-i, C-ii",
            "d) A-ii, B-iii, C-i"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Load on structure may be due to following :\n1) Mass and gravitational effect : examples of such loads are dead loads, imposed loads, snow and ice loads, earth loads, etc.\n2) Mass and acceleration effect : examples of such loads are those caused by earthquake, wind, impact, blasts, etc.\n3) Environmental effects : examples of such loads are due to temperature difference, settlement, shrinkage, etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "The probability that a specific load will be exceeded during life of structure depends on _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) wind",
            "b) factor of safety",
            "c) partial factor of safety",
            "d) period of exposure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The probability that a specific load will be exceeded during life of structure depends on period of exposure. It also depends on magnitude of design load."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "What is characteristic load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) seismic load",
            "b) load which will be exceeded by certain probability during life of structure",
            "c) load which will not be exceeded by certain probability during life of structure",
            "d) pressure load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Characteristic load is the load which will not be exceeded by certain assumed or pre-assumed probability during life of structure. These loads are anticipated loads due to self weight, imposed load, snow, wind load, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Which of the following  is not included in imposed load classification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Residential load",
            "b) Earthquake load",
            "c) Industrial load",
            "d) Educational load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Imposed loads are gravity loads other than dead load and cover factors such as occupancy by people, stored material etc. It is classified into following groups : (i)residential, (ii)educational, (iii)institutional, (iv)assembly halls, (v)office and business buildings, (vi)mercantile buildings, (vii)industrial, (viii)storage buildings."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "What is the minimum imposed load on roof trusses as per IS code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 kN/m2",
            "b) 0.4 kN/m2",
            "c) 0.9 kN/m2",
            "d) 0.75 kN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per IS 875, the minimum imposed load on roof truss should be 0.4 kN/m2. For sloping roof upto 10˚, the imposed load is taken as 0.5 kN/m2 if access is not provided and 0.75 kN/m2 if access is provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "For roofs of slope greater than 10˚, the imposed load is reduced by ____ for every degree rise in slope.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.02 kN/m2",
            "b) 0.05 kN/m2",
            "c) 0.75 kN/m2",
            "d) 0.5 kN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per IS 875, for roofs of slope greater than 10o, the imposed load is taken as 0.75 kN/m2 and reduced by 0.02 kN/m2  for every degree rise in slope."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Calculate imposed load on roof truss of span 20m with slope of 20o.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.75 kN/m2",
            "b) 0.95 kN/m2",
            "c) 0.45 kN/m2",
            "d) 0.55 kN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per IS 875, for roofs of slope greater than 10o, the imposed load is reduced by 0.02 kN/m2  for every degree rise in slope.\nTherefore, Imposed load = 0.75 – 0.02*(20o-10o) = 0.55 kN/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Which IS Code is used for designing a structure considering earthquake loads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 800",
            "b) IS 875",
            "c) IS 1893",
            "d) IS 456"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS 1893(Part 1) is used for designing a structure considering earthquake loads. For all other loads like dead load, wind load, IS 875 is used for design."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "What is the load factor considered for steel structures when combination of dead load and earthquake load is considered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 1.3",
            "c) 1.2",
            "d) 1.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In plastic design of steel structures, load factor is 1.7 when combination of dead load and earthquake load is considered i.e.  1.7(DL + EL) or 1.7(DL – EL)."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "What is the load factor considered for steel structures when combination of dead load, imposed load and earthquake load is considered?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 1.3",
            "c) 1.2",
            "d) 1.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In plastic design of steel structures, load factor is 1.3 when combination of dead load, imposed load and earthquake load is considered i.e.  1.3(DL +/- IL +/- EL )."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "For earthquake loads, axially loaded members have to resist ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tension only",
            "b) compression only",
            "c) both tension and compression",
            "d) bending moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Earthquake are cyclic and induce reversal of stresses. Hence as per seismic philosophy, axially loaded members have to resist both tension and compression."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": " For earthquake loads, beams are designed to resist ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tension only",
            "b) positive and negative bending moments",
            "c) compression only",
            "d) torsion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Beams are designed  to resist positive and negative bending moments at the same section for earthquake loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Structures are designed for seismic forces which is ____ than expected seismic force.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lesser",
            "b) greater",
            "c) equal to",
            "d) seismic forces are not considered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Structures are designed for seismic forces which is less than expected seismic force under strong earthquakes, if the structures were to remain linearly elastic."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors does not influence earthquake resistance design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) geographical location of structure",
            "b) wind of location",
            "c) site soil",
            "d) strength of structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The factors which influence earthquake resistance design are : (i) geographical location of structure, (ii) site soil and foundation condition, (iii) importance of structure, (iv) dynamic characteristics of structure such as strength, stiffness, ductility and energy dissipation factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Structures should be designed such that ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minor and frequent earthquakes can collapse the structure",
            "b) Moderate earthquakes can cause damage to the structure",
            "c) Major earthquakes should not cause any damage to the structure and the structure should be functional",
            "d) Minor earthquake should not cause any damage to the structure and the structure should be functional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per IS 1893, the following seismic philosophy is adopted\n(i) Minor and frequent earthquakes should not cause any damage to the structure\n(ii) Moderate earthquake should not cause significant structural damage but could have some non structural damage(the structure should become operational once the damage is repaired)\n(iii) Major and infrequent earthquake should not cause collapse( structure will be dysfunctional for further use, but will stand so that people can be evacuated and property can be recovered)."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": " Which of the following assumption is correct for earthquake design resistant structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earthquake will not occur simultaneously with wind",
            "b) Earthquake will occur simultaneously with maximum flood",
            "c) Earthquake will occur simultaneously with maximum sea waves",
            "d) Earthquake will occur simultaneously with wind"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per IS 1893, it is assumed that earthquake is not likely to occur simultaneously with wind or maximum flood or maximum sea waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Which analysis is used to obtain design seismic force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic Analysis",
            "b) Plastic Analysis",
            "c) Dynamic Analysis",
            "d) Both elastic and plastic analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dynamic analysis is used to obtain design seismic force, and its distribution to different level along the height of the building and to various lateral load resisting members."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct for design horizontal seismic coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A = ZISa*2Rg",
            "b) A = ZISa/2Rg",
            "c) A = ZISa-2Rg",
            "d) A = ZISa+2Rg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Design horizontal seismic coefficient is given by A = ZISa/2Rg, where Z is zone factor, R is response reduction factor, I is importance factor, Sa/g is average response acceleration coefficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "What is structural response factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) factor denoting the acceleration response spectrum of the structure subjected to earthquake ground vibrations",
            "b) factor by which the actual base shear force is reduced",
            "c) factor to obtain the design spectrum",
            "d) factor used to obtain the design seismic force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Structural response factor (Sa/g) is the factor denoting the acceleration response spectrum of the structure subjected to earthquake ground vibrations. It depends on natural period of vibration and damping of the structure. Response Reduction Factor(R)  is the factor by which the actual base shear force is reduced. Zone Factor(Z) is factor to obtain the design spectrum. Importance Factor (I) is the factor used to obtain the design seismic force."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Wind pressure acting normal to individual is element or claddity unit is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) F = [ (Cpe – Cpi)A/pd].",
            "b) F = [ (Cpe + Cpi)A/pd].",
            "c) F = [ (Cpe – Cpi)Apd].",
            "d) F = [ (Cpe – Cpi)/Apd]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: F = (Cpe – Cpi)A pd , where F=net wind force on element, Cpi= internal pressure coefficient, Cpe=external pressure coefficient,  A=surface area of element, pd=design wind pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Internal pressure coefficient in a building is positive if acting from ________ and external pressure coefficient in a building is positive if acting from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) outside to inside, inside to outside",
            "b) inside to outside, outside to inside",
            "c) outside to inside, outside to inside",
            "d) inside to outside, inside to outside"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Internal pressure coefficient in a building is positive if acting from inside to outside and external pressure coefficient in a building is positive if acting from outside to inside. The pressure depends on degree of permeability of cladding and direction of wind."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Which IS Code is used for design loads for buildings and structures for wind load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS 456",
            "b) IS 875 Part 3",
            "c) IS 500",
            "d) IS 1280"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For design loads for buildings and structures for wind load, IS 875-Part 3 given by Bureau of Indian Standards is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "IS Code gives basic wind speed averaged over a short interval of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 seconds",
            "b) 20 seconds",
            "c) 5 seconds",
            "d) 3 seconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Basic wind speed is based on peak wind gust velocity averaged over a short interval of 3s and having return period of 50 years and corresponds to mean above ground level in open terrain."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": " Positive sign of pressure coefficient indicates ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pressure acting towards the surface",
            "b) pressure acting away the surface",
            "c) pressure acting above the surface",
            "d) pressure acting below the surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Positive sign of pressure coefficient indicates pressure acting towards the surface and negative sign of pressure coefficient indicates pressure acting away the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": " What is return period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) number of years, the reciprocal of which gives the probability of extreme wind exceeding given wind speed in any one year",
            "b) number of years, the reciprocal of which gives the probability of extreme wind less than given wind speed in any one year",
            "c) number of years, the reciprocal of which gives the probability of mild wind exceeding given wind speed in any one year",
            "d) number of years, the reciprocal of which gives the probability of mild wind less than given wind speed in any one year"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pressure Coefficient is the ratio of difference between pressure acting at point on surface and static pressure of incident wind to the design wind pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Wind Pressure at any height of structure does not depend on _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) velocity and density of air",
            "b) angle of wind attack",
            "c) topography of ground surface",
            "d) material of structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Wind load acting on structure varies from year to year based on wind speed and maximum that can be expected to occur at a given location only once in so many years. This period is called return period."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": " Which of the following relation is correct for design wind speed (Vz) and basic wind speed (Vb) ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vz ∝ Vb2",
            "b) Vz ∝ 1/Vb2",
            "c) Vz ∝ Vb",
            "d) Vz ∝ 1/Vb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Wind Pressure at any height of structure depend on (i)velocity and density of air, (ii)height above ground level, (iii)shape and aspect ratio of building, (iv) topography of surrounding ground surface, (v)angle of wind attack, (vi)solidity ratio or openings in the structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Calculate design wind speed for a site in a city with basic wind speed of 50 m/s, risk coefficient =1, topography factor = 1, terrain is with closely spaced buildings and height of building (class A) = 15m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 m/s",
            "b) 48.5 m/s",
            "c) 50 m/s",
            "d) 52.5 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Vz = k1k2k3Vb , where k1=probability factor(risk coefficient), k2=terrain, height and structure size factor, k3=topography factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation between design pressure, pz and design wind speed, Vz  is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pz ∝ Vz2",
            "b) pz ∝ 1/Vz2",
            "c) pz ∝ Vz",
            "d) pz ∝ 1/Vz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:   Vb = 50m/s, k1 = 1, k3 = 1,\nfor terrain with closely spaced buildings, height of building=15m, class A : k2=0.97 (from IS 875 Part 3)\nVz = k1k2k3Vb  = 1×0.97x1x50 = 48.5 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Calculate the design wind pressure if the basic wind speed is 44 m/s, risk coefficient is 1, topography factor is 1, terrain is with closely spaced buildings and height of building(class A) = 20m .",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1285 N/m2",
            "b) 1580 N/m2",
            "c) 1085 N/m2",
            "d) 1185 N/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: pz = 0.6Vz2, where pz is in N/m2 and Vz  is in m/s. 0.6 factor depends on number of factors and mainly on atmospheric pressure and air temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What is the partial safety factor for combination of DL+LL for limit state of strength, where DL=Dead load, LL=imposed load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2",
            "b) 1.0",
            "c) 0.8",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vb = 44m/s, k1 = 1, k3 = 1,\nfor terrain with closely spaced buildings, height of building=20m, class A: k2=1.01 (from IS 875 Part 3)\n Vz = k1k2k3Vb = 1×1.01x1x44 = 44.44 m/s\npz = 0.6Vz2 = 0.6x(44.44)2 = 1184.95 N/m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which of the following load combination is not possible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dead load + imposed load + wind load",
            "b) Dead load + imposed load + earthquake load",
            "c) Dead load + wind load + earthquake load",
            "d) Dead load + imposed load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For limit state of strength, the load combination is 1.5(DL+LL), for limit state of serviceability, the load combination is 1.0(DL+LL), where DL=Dead load, LL=imposed load."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "What is the partial safety factor for dead load in combination of DL+LL+WL/EL for limit state of serviceability, where DL=Dead load,  LL=imposed load , WL=wind load, EL=earthquake load ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0",
            "b) 0.8",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 1.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to IS code, it is assumed that  maximum wind load and earthquake load will not occur simultaneously on a structure. The following combination of loads with appropriate partial safety factors may be considered : (i)Dead load + imposed load, (ii) Dead load + imposed load + earthquake load or wind load, (iii) Dead load + wind load or earthquake load, (iv) Dead load + erection load."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "What is the partial safety factor for dead load in combination of DL+ WL/EL for limit state of serviceability, where DL=Dead load,  WL=wind load, EL=earthquake load ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 1.2",
            "d) 0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For limit state of strength, the load combination is 1.2(DL+LL+WL/EL), for limit state of serviceability, the load combination is 1.0DL+0.8LL+0.8WL/EL, where DL=Dead load,  LL=imposed load, WL=wind load, EL=earthquake load."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "What is the partial safety factor for imposed load in combination of DL+LL+AL , where DL=Dead load,  WL=wind load, AL=Accidental  load ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 0.4",
            "d) 0.35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For limit state of serviceability, the load combination is 1.0(DL +WL/EL), for limit state of strength, the load combination is 1.5(DL +WL/EL), where DL=Dead load,  WL=wind load, EL=earthquake load."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "The design action effects for design basis earthquake loads is obtained by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic Analysis",
            "b) Plastic Analysis",
            "c) Advanced Analysis",
            "d) Dynamic Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design action effects for design basis earthquake loads is obtained by elastic analysis. The maximum credible earthquake load can be assumed to correspond to load at which significant plastic hinges are formed and shall be obtained by plastic analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "What is non-sway frame?",
        "Options": [
            "a) transverse displacement of one end of member relative to other end is not effectively prevented",
            "b) longitudinal displacement of one end of member relative to other end is not effectively prevented",
            "c) transverse displacement of one end of member relative to other end is effectively prevented",
            "d) longitudinal displacement of one end of member relative to other end is effectively prevented"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In non-sway frame, transverse displacement of one end of member relative to other end is effectively prevented. Example : in triangulated frames and trusses, in plane stiffeners is provided by bracings or by shear walls, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "What is sway frame?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal displacement of one end of member relative to other end is not effectively prevented",
            "b) transverse displacement of one end of member relative to other end is effectively prevented",
            "c) longitudinal displacement of one end of member relative to other end is effectively prevented",
            "d) transverse displacement of one end of member relative to other end is not effectively prevented"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In sway frame, transverse displacement of one end of member relative to other end is not effectively prevented. Such members and frames occur in structure which depend on flexural action of members to resist lateral loads and sway."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about rigid construction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) connections between members at their junction does not have sufficient rigidity",
            "b) connections between members at their junction have sufficient rigidity",
            "c) members are not connected",
            "d) connection between members at junction will not resist any moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In rigid construction, connections between members at their junction have sufficient rigidity to hold angles between members connected at joint, unchanged under load."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "In simple construction, connection between members at their junction will __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) resist moment",
            "b) resist force",
            "c) not resist force",
            "d) not resist moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In simple construction, connection between members at their junction will not resist any appreciable moment and shall be assumed to be hinged."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "What percent of factored load is notional horizontal force?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5%",
            "b) 1%",
            "c) 10%",
            "d) 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Notional horizontal force = 0.5% of factored dead load + vertical imposed load at that level. Notional horizontal force are applied to analyse a frame subjected to gravity loads, considering sway stability of frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "In first order elastic analysis, equilibrium is expressed in terms of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) geometry of deformed structure",
            "b) geometry of undeformed structure",
            "c) geometry of both deformed and undeformed structure",
            "d) geometry of any structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In first order elastic analysis, equilibrium is expressed in terms of geometry of undeformed structure. This assumption is valid when elastic displacement are small compared to dimensions of structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an assumption of first order elastic analysis of rigid jointed frame?",
        "Options": [
            "a) materials behave linearly",
            "b) yielding effects can be ignored",
            "c) member instability effects cannot be ignored",
            "d) frame instability effects can be ignored"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following are the assumptions of first order elastic analysis of rigid jointed frame : (i) materials behave linearly, (ii) yielding effects can be ignored, (iii) member instability effects such as those caused by axial compression can ignored, (iv) frame behaves linearly frame instability effects such as those caused by moments due to horizontal frame deflection, etc can be ignored."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Basic objective of second order elastic analysis is :",
        "Options": [
            "a) to calculate external force equilibrium in deformed geometry of structure",
            "b) to calculate internal force equilibrium in deformed geometry of structure",
            "c) to calculate external force equilibrium in undeformed geometry of structure",
            "d) to calculate internal force equilibrium in undeformed geometry of structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Basic objective of second order elastic analysis is to calculate internal force equilibrium in deformed geometry of structure. In this P-Δ effect is also considered."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "First order analysis yields bending moment equal to those for a _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) cantilever beam",
            "b) continuous beam",
            "c) fixed beam",
            "d) simply supported beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: First order analysis yields bending moment equal to those for a simply supported beam since material and frame are assumed to behave linearly and member instability effects and frame instability effects can be ignored."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "When plastic analysis is used, the yield stress of grade of steel used shall not exceed _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 MPa",
            "b) 500 MPa",
            "c) 450 MPa",
            "d) 800 MPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When plastic analysis is used, the yield stress of grade of steel used shall not exceed 450 MPa and the stress strain distribution of steel shall not be significantly different from those obtained for steels complying with IS 2062."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "What is riveting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the process of making holes in the structure",
            "b) process of making mould for structure",
            "c) method of joining together pieces of metal by inserting ductile metal pins called rivets",
            "d) method of joining together pieces of metal by inserting non ductile metal pins called rivets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Riveting is the method of joining together pieces of metal by inserting ductile metal pins called rivets into holes of pieces to be connected and forming a head at end of rivet to prevent each metal piece from coming out."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Size of rivet hole is _________ size of rivet",
        "Options": [
            "a) more than",
            "b) less than",
            "c) equal to",
            "d) not compared with"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Size of rivet hole is kept slightly more than size of rivet.\nSize of rivet hole is 1.5mm more for rivet diameter < 25mm\nSize of rivet hole is 2mm more for rivet diameter ≥ 25mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Hammering is done in rivet to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) give proper shape to rivet",
            "b) completely fill up the rivet hole",
            "c) partially fill up the rivet hole",
            "d) make a rivet hole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Holding red hot rivet at shop head end, hammering is made. It results into expansion of rivet to completely fill up the rivet hole and also into formation at driven head."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of the following about rivet is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) causes low level of noise pollution",
            "b) it does not require skilled work",
            "c) labour cost is low",
            "d) removing poorly installed rivet is costly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: (i)Rivet connection is associated with high level of noise pollution, (ii)needs heating rivet to red hot, (iii)inspection of connection is skilled work, (iv) removing poorly installed rivet is costly, (v)labour cost is high."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) effective diameter of rivets = rivet hole diameter",
            "b) effective diameter of rivets = nominal diameter of rivet",
            "c) effective diameter of rivets = 1.5 x rivet hole diameter",
            "d) effective diameter of rivets = 1.5 x nominal diameter of rivet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Effective diameter of rivet is taken as rivet hole diameter  instead of nominal diameter of rivet. Rivet hole diameter is diameter of rivet + clearance."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Diameter of head for button head rivet is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.60d, where d=nominal rivet diameter",
            "b) 2.5d, where d=nominal rivet diameter",
            "c) 3d, where d=nominal rivet diameter",
            "d) 5d, where d=nominal rivet diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diameter of head for\n\t(i) button head rivet = 1.6d,\n\t(ii) flat countersunk head = 1.5d,\n\t(iii) flat head = 2d, where d=nominal rivet diameter.\t"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Height of head for flat countersunk head rivet is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.7d, where d=nominal rivet diameter",
            "b) 0.5d, where d=nominal rivet diameter",
            "c) 0.43d, where d=nominal rivet diameter",
            "d) 0.25d, where d=nominal rivet diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diameter of head for\n\t(i) button head rivet = 0.7d,\n\t(ii) flat countersunk head rivet = 0.43d,\n\t(iii) flat head rivet = 0.25d, where d=nominal rivet diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Tolerance on length for rivet diameter > 16mm is_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5mm",
            "b) 2mm",
            "c) 5mm",
            "d) 3mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Preferred nominal length of shank are 28,30,32,…..,225mm. Range of length depends on rivet diameter. Tolerance on length = 1.5mm, for rivet diameter ≤ 16mm and tolerance on length = 3mm, for rivet diameter > 16mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which of the following assumption is true for rivet connection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) friction between plates is considered",
            "b) distribution of direct stress on portions of plates between rivet holes is uniform",
            "c) bending stresses are considered",
            "d) shear stress is not uniform on cross section of rivet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The assumptions for rivet connection are : (i) friction between plates is neglected, (ii) distribution of direct stress on portions of plates between rivet holes is uniform, (iii) shear stress is uniform on cross section of rivet, (iv) bending stresses are neglected."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Rivets in group subjected to direct loads share load ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) equally",
            "b) unequally",
            "c) according to rivet diameter",
            "d) rivets are not used in groups"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rivets in group subjected to direct loads share load equally.\nStrength of group of rivets = Strength of single rivet x number of rivets in group."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "What is the yield strength of bolt of class 4.6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 N/mm2",
            "b) 240 N/mm2",
            "c) 250 N/mm2",
            "d) 500 N/mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For class 4.6, ultimate strength = 4×100 = 400 N/mm2\nyield strength / ultimate strength = 0.6\nyield strength = 0.6×400 = 240 N/mm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) size of hole = nominal diameter of fastener – clearances",
            "b) size of hole = nominal diameter of fastener x clearances",
            "c) size of hole = nominal diameter of fastener / clearances",
            "d) size of hole = nominal diameter of fastener + clearances"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Size of hole = nominal diameter of fastener + clearances\nClearance may be standard size, oversize, short slotted or long slotted."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "High strength bolt is used for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear connection",
            "b) slip resistant connection only",
            "c) bearing type connection only",
            "d) both slip resistant and bearing type connection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High strength bolt may be used for slip resistant and bearing type connection. At serviceability, HSFG bolts do not slip and the joints are called slip resistant connections. At ultimate load, HSFG bolts do not slip and the joints behave like bearing type connections."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which of the following is advantage of HSFG bolts over bearing type bolts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) joints are not rigid",
            "b) bolts are subjected to shearing and bearing stresses",
            "c) high strength fatigue",
            "d) low static strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The advantages of HSFG bolts over bearing type bolts are : (i) joints are rigid, (ii) bolts are not subjected to shearing and bearing stresses as load transfer is mainly due to friction, (iii) high static strength due to high frictional resistance, (iv) high strength fatigue since nuts are prevented from loosening, (v)smaller number of bolts results into smaller number of gusset plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct for pitch of the bolts and gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pitch is measured along direction of load, gauge is measured perpendicular to direction of load",
            "b) pitch is measured perpendicular direction of load, gauge is measured along to direction of load",
            "c) pitch is measured along direction of load, gauge is measured along to direction of load",
            "d) pitch is measured perpendicular direction of load, gauge is measured perpendicular to direction of load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pitch is centre to centre spacing of bolts in a row, measured along direction of load. Gauge is the distance between two consecutive bolts of adjacent row measured at right angles to the direction of load."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "What is the minimum pitch distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.0 x nominal diameter of fastener",
            "b) 3.0 x nominal diameter of fastener",
            "c) 1.5 x nominal diameter of fastener",
            "d) 2.5 x nominal diameter of fastener"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pitch is centre to centre spacing of bolts in a row, measured along direction of load. Distance between centre to centre of fasteners shall not be more than 2.5 times nominal diameter of fasteners."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Maximum pitch distance = ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16 x thickness of thinner plate",
            "b) 32 x thickness of thinner plate",
            "c) 40 x thickness of thinner plate",
            "d) 20 x thickness of thinner plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Distance between centre of any two adjacent fasteners shall not exceed 32t or 300mm, whichever is less where t is thickness of thinner plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Pitch shall not be more than ___ in tension member and _______ in compression member.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12t, 16t, where t = thickness of thinner plate",
            "b) 20t, 16t, where t = thickness of thinner plate",
            "c) 16t, 12t, where t = thickness of thinner plate",
            "d) 16t, 20t, where t = thickness of thinner plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pitch shall not be more than 16t or 200mm, whichever is less in tension member  where t is thickness of thinner plate.  Pitch shall not be more than 12t or 200mm, whichever is less in compression member, where t is thickness of thinner plate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "In case of staggered pitch, pitch may be increased by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 100%",
            "d) 30%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spacing between centres of fasteners may be increased by 50% when fasteners are staggered at equal interval and gauge does not exceed at 75mm, subjected to maximum spacing condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "What is the difference between end and edge distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Edge distance is measured parallel to direction of stress, while end distance is measured perpendicular to direction of stress",
            "b) Edge distance is measured parallel to direction of stress, while end distance is measured parallel to direction of stress",
            "c) Edge distance is measured perpendicular to direction of stress, while end distance is measured perpendicular to direction of stress",
            "d) Edge distance is measured perpendicular to direction of stress, while end distance is measured parallel to direction of stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Edge distance is distance at right angles to the direction of stress from centre of hole to adjacent edge. End distance is distance in the direction of stress from centre of hole to end of element."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Maximum gauge length is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100+4t, where t is thickness of thinner plate",
            "b) 100-4t, where t is thickness of thinner plate",
            "c) 4t, where t is thickness of thinner plate",
            "d) 100mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Distance between centres of any two consecutive fasteners in line adjacent and parallel to edge of outside plate shall not exceed (100+4t) or 200mm, whichever is less in compression and tension members."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Minimum edge distance and end distance for rolled, machine flame cut is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7 x hole diameter",
            "b) 1.2 x hole diameter",
            "c) 1.5 x hole diameter",
            "d) 2.0 x hole diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Minimum edge distance and end distance from centre of any hole to nearest edge of plate shall not be (i) less than 1.7 x hole diameter, in case of sheared or hand flame cut edge, (ii) less than 1.5 x hole diameter, in case of rolled, machine flame cut."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Maximum edge distance should not exceed ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10tε, where ε = √(250/fy), t = thickness of thinner outer plate",
            "b) 20tε, where ε = √(250/fy), t = thickness of thinner outer plate",
            "c) 16tε, where ε = √(250/fy), t = thickness of thinner outer plate",
            "d) 12tε, where ε = √(250/fy), t = thickness of thinner outer plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Maximum edge distance should not exceed 12tε, where ε = √(250/fy), t = thickness of thinner outer plate. If members are exposed to corrosive influence, it shall not exceed (40+4t), where t = thickness of thinner connected plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Tacking fasteners are used when _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimum distance between centre of two adjacent fasteners is exceeded",
            "b) maximum distance between centre of two adjacent fasteners is exceeded",
            "c) maximum distance between centre of two adjacent fasteners is  not exceeded",
            "d) for aesthetic appearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tacking fasteners are used when maximum distance between centre of two adjacent fasteners is exceeded. These are not subjected to calculated stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Spacing of tacking fasteners when exposed to weather should not exceed ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32t, where t= thickness of outside plate",
            "b) 25t, where t= thickness of outside plate",
            "c) 20t, where t= thickness of outside plate",
            "d) 16t, where t= thickness of outside plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Spacing of tacking fasteners in a line should not exceed (i)32t or 300mm, whichever is less when not exposed to weather, where t= thickness of outside plate, (ii)16t or 200mm, whichever is less when not exposed to weather, where t= thickness of outside plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "In case of compression members where forces are transferred through butting faces, pitch shall not exceed ___ for a distance of 1.5 times width of member from butting faces.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.5d, where d= diameter of fasteners",
            "b) 5d, where d= diameter of fasteners",
            "c) 2.5d, where d= diameter of fasteners",
            "d) 5.5d, where d= diameter of fasteners"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In case of compression members where forces are transferred through butting faces, pitch shall not exceed 4.5d, where d= diameter of fasteners for a distance of 1.5 times width of member from butting faces."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Shear strength of bolt is given by ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) fu(nnAnb+ nsAsb)/(√3 x 1.1)",
            "b) fy(nnAnb+ nsAsb)/(√3 x 1.1)",
            "c) fu(nnAnb+ nsAsb)/(√3 x 1.25)",
            "d) fy(nnAnb+ nsAsb)/(√3 x 1.25)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shear strength of bolt = fu(nnAnb+ nsAsb)/(√3 x 1.25), where fu=ultimate strength of bolt, nn=number of shear planes with thread intercepting shear plane, ns=number of shear planes without thread intercepting shear plane, Anb=nominal plain shank area of bolt, Asb=net shear area of bolt at threads."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Tensile strength of bolt is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.9fubAn/1.1",
            "b) 0.9fybAn/1.1",
            "c) 0.9fubAn/1.25",
            "d) 0.9fybAn/1.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nominal bearing strength of bolt is 2.5kbdtfu, where kb  is smaller of e/3d0, p/3d0 -0.25, fub/fu, 1 ; where e, d = end and pitch distances, d0= diameter of hole, fub and fu = ultimate tensile stress of bolts and plate, d = nominal diameter of bolt."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Proof stress for minimum bolt tension is :",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.7fub",
            "b) 0.5fub",
            "c) 0.7fyb",
            "d) 0.5fyb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tensile strength of bolt is given by 0.9fubAn/1.25, where fub=ultimate tensile stress of bolt, An= net tensile area."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation is correct for bolt subjected to combined shear and tension?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Vsb/Vdb)2 + (Tsb/Tdb)2 ≤ 1",
            "b) (Vsb/Vdb)2 + (Tsb/Tdb)2 ≥ 1",
            "c) (Vsb/Vdb) + (Tsb/Tdb) ≤ 1",
            "d) (Vsb/Vdb) + (Tsb/Tdb) ≥ 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bolt required to satisfy both shear and tension at the same time should satisfy (Vsb/Vdb)2 + (Tsb/Tdb)2 ≤ 1 , where Vsb= factored shear force, Vdb = design shear capacity, Tsb = factored tensile force, Tdb= design tensile capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Shear Capacity of HSFG bolts is",
        "Options": [
            "a) μfnekhFo",
            "b) μfnekhFoγmf",
            "c) μfnekhoγmf",
            "d) μfnekhFo/γmf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Shear Capacity of HSFG bolts is μfnekhFo/γmf, where μf = coefficient of friction(0.55), ne = number of frictional interfaces offering frictional resistance to slip, kh = 1 for fasteners in clearance holes, 0.85 for fasteners in over sized and short slotted holes, γmf = 1.1 (slip resistance designed at service load), 1.25 (slip resistance designed at ultimate load), Fo = minimum bolt tension = Anbf0 , where Anb = net area of bolt, f0 = 0.7fub , fub = ultimate tensile stress of bolt."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "The maximum number of bolts of diameter 25mm that can be accomodated in one row in 200mm wide flat are:",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Minimum end distance = 2.5×25 = 62.5mm\nNumber of bolts that can be accommodated = (200-2×62.5)/25 = 3 bolts."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": " Calculate strength in shear of 16mm diameter of bolt of grade 4.6 for lap joint",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 kN",
            "b) 40 kN",
            "c) 29 kN",
            "d) 59 kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bolts will be in single shear. Diameter of bolt = 16mm. Net area = 0.78x(π/4)x162=156.83mm2.\nStrength of bolt in shear = Anbfub/(√3 x 1.25) = 156.83x400x10-3/1.25x√3 = 28.97kN."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "What is the value of kb in nominal bearing strength for a bolt of 20mm diameter of grade 4.6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0.97",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: diameter of bolt = 20mm, diameter of hole = 20+2 =22mm\ne=1.5×22=33mm, p=2.5×20=50mm\ne/3d0 = 33/(3×22) = 0.5, p/3d0  -0.25 = 50/(3×22) -0.25=0.5, fub /fb  = 400/410=0.975\nkb  = minimum of (e/3d0 , p/3d0  -0.25, fub /fb, 1) = 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Calculate bearing strength of 20mm diameter bolt of grade 4.6 for joining main plates of 10mm thick using cover plate of 8mm thick using single cover butt joint.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70.26 kN",
            "b) 109.82 kN",
            "c) 50.18 kN",
            "d) 29.56 kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: diameter of bolt = 16mm, diameter of hole =16+2 =18mm\ne=1.5×18=27mm, p=2.5×16=40mm\ne/3d0 = 27/(3×18) = 0.5, p/3d0 -0.25 = 40/(3×18) -0.25=0.49, fub /fb = 400/410=0.975\nkb = minimum of (e/3d0, p/3d0 -0.25, fub /fb,1) = 0.49\nbearing strength = 2.5kbdtfu/1.25 = 2.5×0.49x16x8x400x10-3/1.25 = 50.18 kN."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Find the number of HSFG bolts of diameter 20mm, grade 88 for connection of member carrying factored tensile load of 200kN when no slip is permitted.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fo=0.7fubAnb=0.7x800x0.78x(π/4)x202x10-3=137.22 kN\nAssume μf=0.5, ne=1, kh=1\nSlip resistance of bolt = μf ne kh Fo/1.25 = 0.5x1x1x137.22/1.25 =54.88 kN\nNumber of bolts required = 200/54.88 = 3.64 = 4(approximately)."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "What is the efficiency of joint when strength of bolt per pitch length is 60kN and strength of plate per pitch length is 150kN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25%",
            "b) 30%",
            "c) 35%",
            "d) 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Efficiency = (strength of bolt per pitch length/ strength of plate per pitch length)x100 = 60×100/150 = 40%."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Strength of bolt is",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimum of shear strength and bearing capacity of bolt",
            "b) maximum of shear strength and bearing capacity of bolt",
            "c) shear strength of bolt",
            "d) bearing capacity of bolt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Strength of bolt is minimum of shear strength and bearing capacity of bolt. Design shear strength = nominal shear capacity/1.25, Design bearing strength = nominal bearing capacity/1.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Prying forces are",
        "Options": [
            "a) friction forces",
            "b) shear forced",
            "c) tensile forces",
            "d) bending forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In connections subjected to tensile stresses, the flexibility of connected parts can lead to deformations that increases tension applied to bolts. This additional tension is called prying force."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "What are pin connections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) structural members connected by bolts",
            "b) structural members connected by cylindrical pins",
            "c) structural members connected by bolts and pins",
            "d) structural members connected by welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When two structural members are connected by means of cylindrical-shaped pins, the connection is known as pinned connection. It resists horizontal and vertical movement, but not moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Pin connections are provided when _______ required.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hinge joint",
            "b) fixed joint",
            "c) irrotational joint",
            "d) rigid joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pin connections are provided when hinged joints are required , where zero moments or free rotation is desired and horizontal and vertical movement are not desired."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Pins used for the connection _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not affect secondary stresses",
            "b) increase secondary stresses",
            "c) reduce secondary stresses",
            "d) doubles secondary stresses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pins used for the connection reduce secondary stresses. It serves the same purpose as shank of bolt."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Forces acting on pin are ______ those on bolt",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than",
            "b) equal to",
            "c) half the force",
            "d) greater than"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since only one pin is present in the connection, forces acting on pin are greater than those on bolt."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": " In which of the following cases pin connections are not used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) truss bridge girders",
            "b) hinged arches",
            "c) tall buildings",
            "d) diagonal bracing connection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pin connections are used in following cases : (i) truss bridge girders, (ii) hinged arches, (iii)tie rod connection in water tanks, (iv)as diagonal bracing connections in beams and columns, (v)chain-link cables suspension bridges."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Shear capacity of pin when rotation is allowed is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5fypA",
            "b) 0.6fypA",
            "c) 0.7fypA",
            "d) 0.8fypA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shear capacity of pin is given by (i) 0.5fypA, when rotation is required, (ii) 0.6fypA, when rotation is not required, where fyp=design strength of pin, A = cross sectional area of pin."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Bearing capacity of pin when rotation is not allowed is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8fypdt",
            "b) 0.6fypdt",
            "c) 0.7fypdt",
            "d) 1.5fypdt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bearing capacity of pin given by (i) 1.5fypA, when rotation is not required, (ii) 0.8fypdt, when rotation is not required, where fyp=design strength of pin."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": " Moment capcity of pin when rotation is not allowed is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8fypZ",
            "b) 0.6fypZ",
            "c) 1.5fypZ",
            "d) 2.0fypZ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Moment capacity of pin given by (i) 1.5fypZ, when rotation is not required, (ii) 1.0fypdt, when rotation is not required, where fyp=design strength of pin, Z=section modulus of the pin."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": " Members joined by pin connections are separated some distance _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) to allow friction",
            "b) to allow for bolt heads",
            "c) to allow bending",
            "d) to allow to be removed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Members joined by pin connections are separated some distance (i) to prevent friction, (ii) to allow for bolt heads, if the members are built up, (iii) to facilitate painting."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Design of pin connections is primarily governed by",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear",
            "b) bending",
            "c) flexure",
            "d) friction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Large bending moments are generated since members joined by pin connections are separated some distance. So the pin diameter is generally governed by flexure."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": " Simple connections are used to transmit ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) forces",
            "b) moments",
            "c) stresses",
            "d) both force and moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Simple Connection is required to transmit force only and there may not be any moment acting on the group of connectors. This connection may be capable of transmitting some amount of moment. Simple connections are also called flexible connections."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": " Which of the following statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lap joint eliminates eccentricity of applied load, butt joint results in eccentricity at connection",
            "b) lap joint and butt joint eliminates eccentricity at connection",
            "c) lap joint results in eccentricity of applied load, butt joint eliminates eccentricity at connection",
            "d) lap joint and butt joint results in eccentricity of applied load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lap joints and butt joints are used to connect plates or members composed of plate elements. Lap joint results in eccentricity of applied load, butt joint eliminates eccentricity at connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "In a lap joint, at least  __________  bolts should be provided in a line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In lap joint, members to be connected are simply overlapped and connected together by means of bolts and welds. To minimize the effect of bending due to eccentricity in a lap joint, at least two bolts in a line should be provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Use of lap joints is not recommended because",
        "Options": [
            "a) stresses are distributed unevenly",
            "b) eccentricity is eliminated",
            "c) bolts are in double shear",
            "d) no bending is produced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In lap joint the centre of gravity of load in one member does not coincide with centre of gravity of load in other member. It results in eccentricity of applied loads and bending. Due to eccentricity, stresses are also not evenly distributed, Hence lap joint is not recommended."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Why is double cover butt joint preferred over single cover butt joint or lap joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bolts are in single shear",
            "b) eliminates eccentricity",
            "c) bending in bolts",
            "d) shear force is not transmitted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Double cover butt joint preferred over single cover butt joint or lap joint because (i) eccentricity of load is eliminated, hence no bending in bolts, (ii) total shear force to be transmitted is split into two parts, hence bolts are in double shear. Shear capacity of double cover butt joint is double the shear capacity of single cover butt joint or lap joint."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": " Clip and seating angle connection is provided for",
        "Options": [
            "a) lateral support",
            "b) bending support",
            "c) frictional support",
            "d) hinged support"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Clip and seating angle connection transfer reaction from beam to column through angle seat.  The cleat angle is provided for lateral or torsional support to the top flange of the  beam and bolted to the top flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "In flexible end plate design, beam is designed for the",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum bending moment",
            "b) shear force",
            "c) torsional moment",
            "d) zero end moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In flexible end plate design. beam is designed for the zero end moment and the end plates augment the web shear and bending capacity of beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "which of the following condition is true for web side plate connection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HSFG bolts should be used",
            "b) Bolts should be designed to fail by shear of bolt",
            "c) Bolts should be designed to fail by bearing of connected plies",
            "d) Edge distances must be less than two times the bolt diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following condition must be considered for web side plate connection (i) only ordinary bolts should be used, (ii) bolts should be designed to fail by bearing of connected plies ad not by shear of bolt, (iii) edge distances must be greater than two times the bolt diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The effect of twisting moment and shear force on the bolt group cause ____ whereas bending moment and shear force cause ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear force on the bolts, tension and shear in the bolt",
            "b) tension and shear in the bolt, shear force on the bolts",
            "c) shear force on the bolts, shear force on the bolts",
            "d) tension and shear in the bolt, tension and shear in the bolt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Moment resistant connections are used to transfer moments, axial force and shear force from one member to another. These connections are used in framed structures where joints are considered rigid."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "If bolt group is subjected to applied moment and torque, the number of bolts is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) √(6Mn’pVsd)",
            "b) √(6Mn’/pVsd)",
            "c) √(6M/n’pVsd)",
            "d) √(6Mn’p/Vsd)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effect of twisting moment and shear force on the bolt group cause shear force along two directions of the bolts whereas bending moment and shear force cause tension and shear in the bolts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Clip angle connection are designed to",
        "Options": [
            "a) transfer small end moments in addition to large end shear",
            "b) transfer large end shear only",
            "c) transfer small end moments only",
            "d) transfer bending moments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If bolt group is subjected to applied moment and torque, the number of bolts is given by n = √(6M/n’pVsd), where p=pitch, M=applied moment, Vsd = design shear strength of single bolt, n’ = number of rows of bolt."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about bracket connections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More rigid than any other connection",
            "b) Fabrication cost is low",
            "c) These connections are used to accommodate less number of bolts",
            "d) They are used to give aesthetic appearance to the structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When additional pair of angles in angle seat connection is used to connect the web of beam to flange of column, the connection can be designed to transfer small end moments in addition to large end shear. Such connections are called clip angle connections or light moment connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "In bolted moment end plate connection, bending moment , axial force and shear force are transferred by",
        "Options": [
            "a) tension only",
            "b) compression only",
            "c) tension and compression",
            "d) friction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the lever arm is to be extended to accommodate more number of bolts, bracket connection is used. The bracket type connection are more rigid than any other type of connection. But the fabrication cost is very high, so they are not adopted in general practice."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "What is eccentric shear”",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear effects caused by concentric load on a bolt group",
            "b) shear effects caused by eccentric load on a bolt group",
            "c) shear effects caused by moment on a bolt group",
            "d) shear effects caused by torsion load on a bolt group"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: In bolted moment end plate connection, bending moment, axial force and shear force are transferred by tension and compression or shear through flange welds and by shear through the web welds to the end plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which of the following connections can be used for beam-beam connection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pin Connection",
            "b) Moment Resistant Connection",
            "c) Simple Connection",
            "d) Complex Connection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When bolt groups are subjected to shear and moment in shear plane, the load that is eccentric is eccentric with respect to centroid of bolt group can be replaced with a force acting through the centroid of bolt group and a moment (Magnitude = Pe). Both the moment and the force result in shear effects in the bolts of the group and is called as eccentric shear.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "In practice, secondary beams are connected to main beams by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) web cleats",
            "b) bolts",
            "c) seating angle",
            "d) web cleats and bolts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Simple connections such as clip and seating angle connection, web angle connection and flexible end plate connections, etc. used for connecting beam-to-columns, can be adopted for beam-beam connections."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "For which of the following conditions rigid construction is required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fixed beam supported by girder",
            "b) cantilever beam supported by girder",
            "c) overhanging beam",
            "d) overhanging beam supported by girder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In practice, secondary beams are connected to main beams by web cleats and bolts since web of the main beam may not be strong enough to support seating angles."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "When cantilever beam is supported by girder, the end of cantilever will transfer",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear force",
            "b) torsion",
            "c) bending moment",
            "d) shear force and bending moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rigid connections are necessary if a cantilever beam is supported by girder. Rigid connections may be provided for moment continuity between secondary beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "In a beam-beam connection, which type of connection is used when top flanges are required to be at same level ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bracket connection",
            "b) combined splice plate/end plate connection",
            "c) combined splice plate/bracket connection",
            "d) moment resistant connection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When cantilever beam is supported by girder, the end of cantilever will transfer shear force and bending moment and this bending moment will be transferred to primary beam as torsion."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the reason for beams, plate girders and columns being spliced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) full length is available from the mill",
            "b) for easy transportation",
            "c) for aesthetic appearance",
            "d) for frictional resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rolled beams, plate girders and columns are spliced due to following reasons : (i)full length of the member may not be available from the mill, (ii)size of section which can be transported depends on size of truck, so for easy transportation, (iii)splice points may be used to camber the beam, (iv)when a change in section is required to fit variation in strength required along span of beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct regarding splice plates used for beam splices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plates on the flange should be designed to do the work of the web and plates on the web should be designed to do the work of the flange",
            "b) plates on the flange should be designed to do the work of the web and plates on the web should be designed to do the work of the web",
            "c) plates on the flange should be designed to do the work of the flange and plates on the web should be designed to do the work of the flange",
            "d) plates on the flange should be designed to do the work of the flange and plates on the web should be designed to do the work of the web"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For beam splices, each element of the splice is designed to do the work the sections underlying the splice plates could do, if uncut. Plates on the flange should be designed to do the work of the flange and plates on the web should be designed to do the work of the web."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "According to IS code, strength of spliced portion ________  of the effective strength of material spliced.",
        "Options": [
            "a)  should not be less than 50%",
            "b) should be less than 50%",
            "c) should not be less than 80%",
            "d) should be less than 80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per  IS code, strength of spliced portion should not be less than 50% of the effective strength of material spliced."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Choose the correct option from the following regarding basic forms of beam splices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flush end plates are used when bending moments to be resisted are high",
            "b) Extended end plates are used when bending moments to be resisted are not high",
            "c) Flush end plates are used when bending moments to be resisted are modest",
            "d) Extended end plates are used when torsional moments to be resisted are not high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flush end plates are used when bending moments to be resisted are modest. Singly or doubly extended plates are used when resisting high moments of one sign or full reversal respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "When are longitudinal stiffeners introduced to beam splices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) when change in size between two sections of beam occurs",
            "b) when change in size between two sections of beam does not occur",
            "c) when change in moment between two sections of beam occurs",
            "d) when change in moment between two sections of beam does not occur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When change in size between two sections of beam occurs at an end plate splice, it can be easily accommodated by introducing longitudinal stiffeners to the larger beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "In direct end bearing arrangement for column splices,",
        "Options": [
            "a) load is transferred through splices",
            "b) splices are designed only to resist accidental tension",
            "c) bending moment is transferred through splices",
            "d) splices are designed only to resist bending moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: End bearing arrangement may be used when the columns carry predominantly axial forces. In this load is transferred through contact area and splices are designed only to resist accidental tension due to some uplift loading or internal explosion in the building."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding arrangement of leaving a gap between the ends for column splices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) load is transferred through splices",
            "b) splices are designed only to resist accidental tension",
            "c) load is transferred through contact area",
            "d) splices are designed only to resist bending moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the columns carry predominantly axial forces, leaving a gap between the ends may be used. In this case, the whole load is transmitted through means of splice plates. HSFG bolts may be used in the connections and changes in size of column may be accommodated using packing plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true when end plate splices is used for columns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short end plates are used for heavy moments",
            "b) Extended end plates are used for moderate moments",
            "c) Short end plates are used for moderate moments",
            "d) Short end plates and extended end plates are used for moderate moments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: End plate splices can be used in column to provide load reversals in columns. Short end plates are used for moderate moments and extended end plates are used for heavy moments."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Position of splices should be _____ in normal practice.",
        "Options": [
            "a) at mid height of columns",
            "b) at three fourth height of column from bottom of column",
            "c) at three fourth height of column from top of column",
            "d) just above the floor level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In normal practice, splices are positioned just above the floor level to neglect the effects of flexing of the column. In regions of seismic activity, splices should be placed near mid-height of columns, where bending moments will be minimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Which of the following parameters control the quality of weld?",
        "Options": [
            "a) composition of electrode",
            "b) size of electrode",
            "c) size of metal plate",
            "d) composition of metal plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The parameters control the quality of weld are size of electrode and the current that produces sufficient heat to melt the base metal and minimizes electrode splatter."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Why is electrode coated with a flux in shielded metal arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) for shiny appearance of electrode",
            "b) to make welding faster",
            "c) to increase the melting of electrode",
            "d) to protect the electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electrode is coated with a flux in shielded metal arc welding. Heat from electric current causes the combustion and decomposition of electrode. This creates a gaseous shield to protect the electrode, metal and molten pool from atmospheric contamination due to oxidation."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be non-low hydrogen process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shielded metal arc welding",
            "b) Submerged arc welding",
            "c) Gas-shielded metal arc welding",
            "d) Flux core arc welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shielded metal arc welding can be a low hydrogen process or non-low hydrogen process, while submerged arc welding, gas-shielded metal arc welding, flux core arc welding are low hydrogen process."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Why hydrogen not used excessively for welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases welding rate",
            "b) decreases welding rate",
            "c) destroys the metal plate",
            "d) affects the weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydrogen causes weld to crack. Hence most of the welding processes are low hydrogen welding process."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about shielded metal arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) equipment cost is high",
            "b) cannot weld different types of  metals",
            "c) cannot be used for metal sheets under 1.5mm thickness",
            "d) entire electrode can be used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following are some advantages of shielded metal arc welding : (i)low equipment cost, (ii)welds many different metals, (iii)welds can be performed in any position, (iv)process less affected by wind, (v)can be performed under most weather conditions. SomeThe disadvantages are : (i)not suitable for metal sheets under 1.5mm thickness,(ii) entire electrode cannot be used, about 25-50mm electrode is wasted."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about submerged arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) high deposition rate",
            "b) short set-up time",
            "c) high quality welds",
            "d) slag removal needed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The following are some advantages of submerged arc welding: (i) high deposition rate, (ii)high quality welds with good ductility, high impact strength, good corrosion resistance, (iii)good for welding long joints(in excess of 1m), (iv)no eye protection required. Some disadvantages are : (i) long set-up time, (ii)slag removal needed, (iii)used for flat or horizontal fillets only."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Choose the correct option regarding metal-active gas welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) not suitable for thin metal sheets",
            "b) need to stop welding to change the consumed electrode",
            "c) equipment is not expensive",
            "d) high deposition rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gas-shielded metal arc welding is also called metal-active gas welding. The following are some advantages of gas-shielded metal arc welding : (i) suitable for metals as thin as 0.58mm, (ii)all welding positions can be used, (iii) no need to stop welding to change the consumed electrode, (iv)high deposition rates. Some disadvantages are : (i)welding equipment is expensive and complicated, (ii)cannot be performed outdoors in greater than 8km/hr breeze."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "What is the differentiating factor between flux core arc welding and gas-shielded metal arc welding processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) structure and chemical composition of electrode",
            "b) structure and chemical composition of metal plate",
            "c) time of welding",
            "d) process of welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The structure and chemical composition of electrode wire is the differentiating factor between flux core arc welding and gas-shielded metal arc welding processes. Unlike gas-shielded metal arc welding, flux core arc welding electrode wire is not solid and consists of thin-walled metal tube filled with flux."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about flux core arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) low deposition rate",
            "b) cannot weld narrow angles",
            "c) slag removal required",
            "d) generates less volume of fumes and smoke."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following are some advantages of flux core arc welding: (i)high deposition rates, (ii)can be used to groove angles as narrow as 30˚, (iii)welds in all positions can be made, (iv)has excellent weld pool control. Some disadvantages are: (i) slag removal required, (ii) generates large volume of fumes and smoke."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Which of the following welding process is preferred for field application?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shielded metal arc welding",
            "b) Submerged arc welding",
            "c) Gas-shielded metal arc welding",
            "d) Flux core arc welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Submerged arc welding, gas-shielded metal arc welding, flux core arc welding, electro slag welding can be used when welding is done in fabrication shop. For field applications, shielded metal arc welding is preferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct about electro slag welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) high deposition rates",
            "b) welds flat or vertical joints only",
            "c) multiple electrodes may not be used",
            "d) complicated set-up"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following are some advantages of electro slag welding: (i) high deposition rates, (ii) multiple electrodes may be used, (iii)low distortion. Some disadvantages are: (i) welds flat or vertical joints only, (ii) complicated set-up, (iii)cooling water is needed."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Which of the following process does not have high deposition rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shielded metal arc welding",
            "b) Electro Slag welding",
            "c) Gas-shielded metal arc welding",
            "d) Flux core arc welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flux core arc welding, gas-shielded metal arc welding, electro slag welding have high deposition rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "13. Match the pairs<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\"> \tWelding Process \t\t\t\tSuitable Position of welding\nA) Submerged arc welding\t\t\t(i)  suitable for overhead works at site\nB) Gas-shielded metal arc welding\t\t(ii) not suitable for overhead positions\nC) Shielded metal arc welding\t\t\t(iii) can be used in all positions</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii",
            "b) A-iii, B-ii, C-i",
            "c) A-ii, B-iii, C-i",
            "d) A-ii, B-i, C-iii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Submerged arc welding and electro slag welding are not suitable for overhead positions. Flux core arc welding and gas-shielded metal arc welding can be used in all positions. Shielded metal arc welding is probably the best for overhead works, especially at site."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": " Arrange the following welds in ascending order as per their usage in structural engineering applications.",
        "Options": [
            "a) fillet weld, groove weld, slot and plug weld",
            "b) slot and plug weld, groove weld, fillet weld",
            "c) groove weld, fillet weld, slot and plug weld",
            "d) fillet weld, slot and plug weld, groove weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fillet welds are used extensively (about 80%) followed by groove welds (15%). Slot and plug welds are rarely used (less than 5%) in structural engineering applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of weld is most suitable for lap and T-joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fillet weld",
            "b) Groove weld",
            "c) Slot weld",
            "d) Plug weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fillet welds are suitable for lap and T-joints and groove welds are suitable for butt, corner, and edge joints."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about back-up strip provided at bottom of single-V grooves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Back-up strips are commonly used when welding is done from both the sides",
            "b) Back-up strips are commonly used when  root opening is sufficient",
            "c) It creates a problem of burn-through",
            "d) It introduces a crevice into the weld geometry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Back-up strip is provided at the bottom of single-V/bevel/J or U grooves. It is commonly provided when welding is done from one side or when the root opening is excessive. It introduces a crevice into the weld geometry and prevents the problem of burn-through."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "The size of root gap and root face for groove weld does not depend on :",
        "Options": [
            "a) type of welding process",
            "b) welding position",
            "c) type of metal plate",
            "d) volume of deposited material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For groove weld, the root opening or gap is provided for the electrode to access the base of the joint. The size of root gap and root face depends on the following : (i) type of welding process, (ii) welding position, (iii) volume of deposited material, (iv)cost of preparing edges, (v)access for arc and electrode, (vi)shrinkage and distortion."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Which of the following groove weld is used for plates of thickness more than 40mm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double-bevel",
            "b) Single-J",
            "c) Single-U",
            "d) Double-U"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The groove is made of double-bevel or double-V for plates of thickness more than 12mm, and made of double-U or double-J for plates of thickness more than 40mm. For plates of thickness between 12-40mm, single-J and single-U grooves may be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Groove welds should have ________ strength as member they join.",
        "Options": [
            "a) same",
            "b) less",
            "c) greater",
            "d) half"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Groove welds will transmit full load of the members they join, so they should have the same strength as the members they join."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not true regarding fillet welds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They require less precision in fitting up two sections",
            "b) They are adopted in field as well as shop welding",
            "c) They are assumed to fail in tension",
            "d) They are cheaper than groove welds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fillet welds require less precision in fitting up two sections. They are adopted in field as well as shop welding. They are assumed to fail in shear and are cheaper than groove welds."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about slot and plug welds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are extensively used in steel construction",
            "b) They are assumed to fail in shear",
            "c) The inspection of these welds is easy",
            "d) They are normally used to connect members carrying tensile loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Slot and plug welds are not extensively used in steel construction. They are used to fill up holes in connections. They are assumed to fail in shear. The inspection of these welds is difficult. They are useful in preventing overlapping parts from buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Choose the correct option regarding weld metal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weld metal is same as parent metal",
            "b) Weld metal is same as steel",
            "c) It has higher yield to ultimate ratio",
            "d) It has higher ductility compared to structural steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Weld metal is a mixture of parent metal and steel melted from electrode. The solidified weld metal has properties characteristic of cast steel. It has higher yield to ultimate ratio but lower ductility compared to structural steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding pre-heating of heat affected zone ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pre-heating does not help to reduce heat affected zone cracks",
            "b) Pre-heating increases the cost of welding",
            "c) It is done to remove surface moisture in highly humid conditions",
            "d) It is done to disperse hydrogen away from weld pool and heat affected zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pre-heating of joints help to reduce heat affected zone cracks but increases the cost of welding. It is done to remove surface moisture in highly humid conditions, to disperse hydrogen away from weld pool and heat affected zone, to bring steel to ambient temperature in cold climates."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The production of sound welds is not governed by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) type of joint",
            "b) choice of electrode",
            "c) type of metal plate",
            "d) arc length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The production of sound welds is governed by type of joint, its preparation, root opening, etc. The choice of electrode, welding position, welding current and voltage, arc length, rate of travel also affect the quality of weld."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a reason for incomplete fusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) surfaces to be jointed are coated with oxides",
            "b) insufficient current supplied by welding equipment",
            "c) high rate of welding",
            "d) use of large electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Incomplete fusion may result if surfaces to be jointed have not been cleaned properly and are coated with oxides and other foreign materials. Insufficient current supplied by welding equipment and high rate of welding will result in incomplete fusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) incomplete penetration is found in fillet welds",
            "b) it is due to use of large size of electrodes",
            "c) it is due to excessive welding current",
            "d) it is due to insufficient welding rates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Incomplete penetration is due to failure of weld metal to penetrate the complete depth of joint where full penetration has been specified. This defect is found in groove welds sue to unsuitable groove design for selected welding process, use of large size of electrodes, insufficient welding current, excessive welding rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Porosity is caused due to insufficient current",
            "b) It is caused due to longer arc length",
            "c) It may be due to poor welding procedure",
            "d) It results in stress concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Porosity is formed when gas pockets or voids are draped during cooling process. It may be due to excessively high current or longer arc length or due to poor welding procedure. Porosity results in stress concentration and reduced ductility of metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding undercutting defect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undercutting is due to local increase of thickness of parent metal at weld toe",
            "b) It is due to insufficient current",
            "c) It can be corrected by depositing additional weld material",
            "d) It is not easy to detect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Undercutting is due to local decrease of thickness of parent metal at weld toe. This results in groove in base metal adjacent to toe of weld and left unfilled by weld metal during welding process. Undercutting may result in loss of gross section and will act as stress riser. This defect may be due to excessive current or longer arc length. It can be easily detected visually and can be corrected by depositing additional weld material."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Hot cracks can be prevented by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) faster cooling",
            "b) non uniform heating",
            "c) pre-heating",
            "d) slower cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hot cracks form as weld begin to solidify and are caused by brittle constituents (presence of sulphur, carbon, silicon and hydrogen). They can be prevented by more uniform heating and slower cooling."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Cold cracks can be prevented by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) uniform heating",
            "b) by use of low hydrogen electrode",
            "c) faster cooling",
            "d) slower cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cold cracks occur under room temperature run parallel to but under the weld in base metal. Use of low hydrogen electrodes along with proper pre-heating and post-heating may reduce possibility of cold cracks."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "The types of welded joints does not depend on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) size of members connected at joint",
            "b) type of loading",
            "c) area available for welding",
            "d) size of weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The types of welded joints depends on (i) size and shape of members connected at joint, (ii) type of loading, (iii) area available for welding at the joint, (iv) relative cost of various types of weld."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of the following are correct regarding butt joints over lap joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Lap joints eliminates eccentricity whereas butt joints develops eccentricity",
            "b) Butt joints minimizes the size of connection",
            "c) Lap joints are aesthetically pleasing over butt joints",
            "d) Butt joint obtained from full penetration groove weld has 50% efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Butt joints eliminates eccentricity developed using lap joints. Butt joints minimizes the size of connection and are aesthetically pleasing over lap joints. Butt joint obtained from full penetration groove weld has 100% efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "What is face reinforcement used in butt joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is extra weld metal that makes throat dimensions greater than the thickness of the welded material",
            "b) It is extra weld metal that makes the throat dimensions smaller than the thickness of the welded material",
            "c) It is extra weld metal that makes the throat dimensions equal to the thickness of the welded material",
            "d) It is parent metal makes that the throat dimensions smaller than the thickness of the welded material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Face reinforcement is extra weld metal that makes the throat dimensions greater than the thickness of the welded material. The provision of reinforcement increases the efficiency of joint and ensures that depth of weld is at least equal to thickness of the plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "When plates of two different thicknesses and/or widths are joined, the wider or thicker part should be reduced at the butt joint to make __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) thickness less than smaller part, the slope being steeper than one in five",
            "b) thickness greater than smaller part, the slope being steeper than one in five",
            "c) thickness equal to smaller part, the slope not being steeper than one in five",
            "d) thickness equal to smaller part, the slope being steeper than one in five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When plates of two different thicknesses and/or widths are joined, the wider or thicker part should be reduced at the butt joint to make thickness equal to smaller part, the slope not being steeper than one in five. When reduction is not possible, the weld metal shall be built up at the junction with thicker part to dimensions at least 25% greater than those of thinner part, or alternatively to the dimensions of thicker member."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding lap joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Connection using lap joint requires large number of erection bolts",
            "b) It can accommodate minor errors in fabrication",
            "c) Lap joints are well suited for shop as well as field welding",
            "d) It introduces some eccentricity of loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lap joints offer ease of fitting and ease of jointing. It can accommodate minor errors in fabrication or minor adjustment in length. They are well suited for shop as well as field welding. Connection using lap joint requires a small number of erection bolts. The main drawback of lap joint is that it introduces some eccentricity of loads, unless a double lap joint is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "T-joints are not used to fabricate _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) I-shapes",
            "b) T-shapes",
            "c) Brackets",
            "d) Plates joined at straight angles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: T-joints are used to fabricate built up sections such as T-shapes, I-shapes, plate girders, brackets and stiffeners where two plates are joined at right angles."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "14. Match the pair<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\tTypes of joints\t\t\t\t\tUse / Application\n\tA) Butt joint\t\t\ti) used to keep two or more plats in given plane\n\tB) Lap joint\t\t\tii) used to join ends of flat plates of nearly equal thickness\n\tC) Tee joint\t\t\tiii) used to form built-up rectangular box sections\n\tD) Corner joint\t\t        iv) used to fabricate built-up sections  \n\tE) Edge joint\t\t        v) plates with different thickness can be joined without any difficulty</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii, D-iv, E-v",
            "b) A-ii, B-v, C-iv, D-iii, E-i",
            "c) A-ii, B-iii, C-iv, D-v, E-i",
            "d) A-v, B-iv, C-iii, D-ii, E-i"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Butt joint is used to join of flat plates of nearly equal thickness. Plates with different thickness can be joined without any difficulty using lap joints. Tee joint is used to fabricate built-up sections,  where two plates are joined at right angles. Corner joint is used to form built-up rectangular box sections, which may be used as columns or beams to resist high torsional forces. Edge joints are not used in structural engineering applications, they are used to keep two or more plats in given plane."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not the assumptions made in the analysis of welded joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) welds connecting various joints are homogenous, isotropic",
            "b) parts connected by weld are rigid",
            "c) only stresses due to internal forces are considered",
            "d) effects of residual stresses are neglected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following are the assumptions made in analysis of welded joints: (i) welds connecting various joints are homogenous, isotropic and elastic elements, (ii) parts connected by weld are rigid and their deformations are neglected, (iii) only stresses due to external forces are considered. Effects of residual stresses, stress concentration and shape of welds are neglected."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "The minimum size of fillet weld should _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) not be less than 3mm",
            "b) be less than 3mm",
            "c) be less than 2mm",
            "d) greater than thickness of thinner part joined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum size of fillet weld should not be less than 3mm and not more than thickness of thinner part joined."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "The maximum size of fillet weld is obtained by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) adding 1.5mm to thickness of thinner member to be jointed",
            "b) adding 3mm to thickness of thinner member to be jointed",
            "c) subtracting 3mm from thickness of thinner member to be jointed",
            "d) subtracting 1.5mm from thickness of thinner member to be jointed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum size of fillet weld is obtained by subtracting 1.5mm from thickness of thinner member to be jointed. The maximum size of weld should not be more than 3/4 of the thickness of section at toe when welds are applied to round toe of steel sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What is the minimum specified length of fillet weld?",
        "Options": [
            "a) two times the size of weld",
            "b) four times the size of weld",
            "c) six times the size of weld",
            "d) half the size of weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per IS code, the actual length of fillet weld should not be less than four times the size of weld. If this requirement is not met, the size of weld should be one fourth of the effective length."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Effective length of fillet weld is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) equal to overall length plus twice the weld size",
            "b) twice the overall length plus twice the weld size",
            "c) equal to overall length minus twice the weld size",
            "d) twice the overall length minus twice the weld size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Effective length of fillet weld is taken equal to overall length minus twice the weld size. The deduction is made to allow for craters to be formed at the ends of welded length."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "End returns are made ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) equal to twice the size of weld",
            "b) equal to half the size of weld",
            "c) equal to the size of weld",
            "d) equal to thrice the size of weld"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: End returns are made equal to twice the size of weld to relieve the weld lengths from high stress concentrations at the ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding effective throat thickness of weld?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective throat thickness should not be less than 3mm",
            "b) It should not exceed 0.7t or 1t, where t is thickness of thinner plate of elements being welded",
            "c) Effective throat thickness = K x size of weld, where K is a constant",
            "d) Effective throat thickness = K x (size of weld)2 , where K is a constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Effective throat thickness is the shortest distance from the root of fillet weld to face of diagrammatic weld(line joining the toes). The effective throat thickness should not be less than 3mm and it should not exceed 0.7t or 1t, where t is thickness of thinner plate of elements being welded. Effective throat thickness = K x size of weld, where K is a constant which depends on angle between fusion faces."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "The effective throat thickness is K times the size of weld. What is the value of K when angle between fusion faces is 80˚?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.65",
            "c) 0.7",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of K varies with angle between fusion faces. Values of K for different angles between fusion faces are :\n\n\nAngle between fusion faces\n60˚-90˚\n91˚-100˚\n101˚-106˚\n107˚-113˚\n114˚-120˚\n\n\nK\n0.7\n0.65\n0.6\n0.55\n0.5\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "The length of overlap of plates to be fillet welded in lap joint ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) should not be less than 4 times the thickness of thinner part",
            "b) should be less than 4 times the thickness of thinner part",
            "c) should  be less than 2 times the thickness of thinner part",
            "d) should not be less than 2 times the thickness of thinner part"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The length of overlap of plates to be fillet welded in lap joint should not be less than 4 times the thickness of thinner part."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Which of the following option is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective length of groove weld should not be less than 4 times the weld size",
            "b) Effective length of groove weld should be less than 4 times the weld size",
            "c) Effective length of intermittent weld should not be less than 4 times the weld size",
            "d) Effective length of intermittent weld should have a minimum length 80mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Effective length of groove weld should not be less than 4 times the weld size. Effective length of intermittent weld should not be less than 4 times the weld size, with a minimum of 40mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "The design nominal strength of fillet weld is given by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fu",
            "b) √3 fu",
            "c) fu/√3",
            "d) fu/(1.25 x √3)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Design nominal strength of fillet weld = fu/√3, where fu is smaller of ultimate stress of weld or parent metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "When welds are subjected to compressive or tensile or shear force alone, the stress in weld is given by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) P/ttlw",
            "b) Ptt/lw",
            "c) Pttlw",
            "d) Plw/tt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When welds are subjected to compressive or tensile or shear force alone, the stress in weld is given by q = P/ttlw , where q=shear stress in N/mm2, P = force transmitted, tt = effective throat thickness of weld in mm, lw = effective length of weld in mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "When fillet welds are subjected to combination of normal and shear stress, the equivalent stress is given by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) √(fa2+q2)",
            "b) √(fa2+2q2)",
            "c) √(3fa2+q2)",
            "d) √(fa2+3q2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When fillet welds are subjected to combination of normal and shear stress, the equivalent stress is given by fe = √(fa2+3q2), where fa = normal stresses, compression or tension, due to axial force or bending moment, q = shear stress due to shear force or tension."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Two plates of 12mm and 16mm thickness are to be joined by groove weld. The joint is subjected to factored tensile load of 400kN. Due to some reasons the effective length of weld that could be provided was 150mm only. What is the safety of joint if single-V groove weld is provided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Safe",
            "b) Unsafe",
            "c) Unsafe, but adequate",
            "d) Safe, but adequate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lw = 150mm, Throat thickness, te = 5×12/8 = 7.5 mm\nStrength of weld = Lwtefy/1.25 = 150×7.5x250x10-3/1.25 = 225kN < 400kN. Therefore joint is unsafe and inadequate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "What is the effective throat thickness dimension of 10mm fillet weld made by shielded metal arc welding and submerged arc welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.6mm, 5mm",
            "b) 5mm, 4.6mm",
            "c) 8.6mm, 7mm",
            "d) 7mm, 8.6mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: a) Using shielded metal arc welding process,\neffective throat thickness = 0.7a = 0.7×10 = 7mm\nb) Using submerged arc welding (we get better penetration than shielded metal arc welding):\na = 10+2.4 = 12.4mm\neffective throat thickness = 0.7a = 0.7×12.4 = 8.6mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "What is the strength of weld  per mm length used to connect two plates of 10mm thickness using a lap joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 795.36 N/mm",
            "b) 295.5N/mm",
            "c) 552.6 N/mm",
            "d) 487.93 N/mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Minimum size of weld = 3mm\nMaximum size of weld = 10-1.5 = 8.5mm\nAssume weld size = 6mm\nEffective throat thickness, te = 0.7 x 6 = 4.2mm\nStrength of weld = te [fu/(√3 x 1.25)] = 410 x 4.2 /(√3 x 1.25) = 795.36 N/mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "What is the overall length of fillet weld to be provided for lap joint to transmit a factored load of 100kN? Assume site welds and width and thickness of plate as 75mm and 8mm respectively, Fe410 steel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500mm",
            "b) 382mm",
            "c) 201mm",
            "d) 468mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Minimum size of weld = 3mm\nMaximum size of weld = 8-1.5 = 6.5mm\nAssume size of weld = 5mm\nEffective throat thickness = 0.7 x 5 = 3.5mm\nStrength of weld = 3.5×410/(√3 x1.5) = 552.33 N/mm\nRequired length of weld = 100 x 103/552.33 = 181.05 mm\nlength to be provided on each side = 181/2 = 90.5mm\nEnd return = 2×5 = 10mm\nOverall length = 2 x (90.5 + 2 x 5) = 201mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "The clear spacing between effective lengths of intermittent welds should not be ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than 16t in case of tension joint, where t is thickness of thinner plate",
            "b) less than 12t in case of compression joint, where t is thickness of thinner plate",
            "c) less than 20t in case of tension joint, where t is thickness of thinner plate",
            "d) less than 20t in case of compression joint, where t is thickness of thinner plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The clear spacing between effective lengths of intermittent welds should not be less than 16 times and 12 times the thickness of thinner plate jointed in case of tension joint and compression joint respectively, and should never be more than 200mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "What are steel tension members?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural elements that are subjected to direct compressive loads",
            "b) Structural elements that are subjected to direct tensile loads",
            "c) Structural elements that are subjected to indirect compressive loads",
            "d) Structural elements that are subjected to indirect tensile loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Steel tension members are those structural elements that are subjected to direct axial tensile loads, which tend to elongate the members. A member in pure tension can be stressed up to and beyond the yield limit and does not buckle locally or overall."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "The strength of tensile members is not influenced by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) length of connection",
            "b) net area of cross section",
            "c) type of fabrication",
            "d) length of plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The strength of tensile members is influenced by factors such as length of connection, size and spacing of fasteners, size and spacing of fasteners, net area of cross section, type of fabrication, connection eccentricity, and shear lag at the end connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) single angle section with bolted connection produce eccentricity about both planes",
            "b) single angle section with bolted connection produce eccentricity about one plane only",
            "c) single angle section with welded connection produce eccentricity about both planes",
            "d) single angle section with welded connection does not produce eccentricity about one plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Single angle section with bolted connection produce eccentricity about both planes, whereas single angle section with welded connection may produce eccentricity about one plane only."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single angle members are used where members are subjected to reversal of stresses",
            "b) Double angle members are used in towers",
            "c) Single angle members are used as web members in trusses",
            "d) Double angle members are used as web members in trusses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Single angle members are used in towers and as web members in trusses. Double angle sections are used as chord members in light roof trusses or in situations where some rigidity is required and where members are subjected to reversal of stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "What is the difference between strand and wire rope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strand consists of individual wires wound helically around a central core, wire rope is made of several strand laid helically around a core",
            "b) Wire rope consists of individual wires wound helically around a central core, strand is made of several wire ropes laid helically around a core",
            "c) Strand consists of individual wires wound straight around a central core, wire rope is made of several strand laid helically around a core",
            "d) Wire rope consists of individual wires wound straight around a central core, strand is made of several wire ropes laid helically around a core"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Strand consists of individual wires wound helically around a central core, wire rope is made of several strand laid helically around a core. Wire ropes are exclusively used for hoisting purposes and as guy wires in steel stacks and towers."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cables in form of wires ropes and strands are used in application where high strength is required",
            "b) Cables are generally long and their flexural rigidity is negligible",
            "c) They are flexible",
            "d) They are recommended in bracing systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cables used as floor suspenders in suspension bridges are made from individual strands wound together in rope like fashion. Cables in form of wires ropes and strands are used in application where high strength is required and flexural rigidity is unimportant. Cables are generally long and their flexural rigidity is negligible. They are flexible. They are not recommended in bracing systems as they cannot resist compression."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Bars and rods are not used as :",
        "Options": [
            "a) tension members in bracing systems",
            "b) friction resistant members",
            "c) sag rods to support purlin",
            "d) to support girts in industrial buildings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bars and rods are used as tension members in bracing systems, sag rods to support purlin between trusses, to support girts in industrial buildings, where light structure is desirable. Rods are also used in arches to resist thrust of arch."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Sagging of members by built up bars and rods may be minimised by",
        "Options": [
            "a) increasing length diameter",
            "b) increasing thickness ratio",
            "c) fabricating rod/bar short of its required theoretical length",
            "d) fabricating rod/bar more than its required theoretical length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sagging of members by built up bars and rods may be minimised by limiting length diameter or thickness ratio or by fabricating the rod/bar short of its required theoretical length by some arbitrary amount and drawing into place to provide an initial tension. The same effect may be produced by providing turnbuckle in the rod."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of tension member is not mainly used in modern practice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) open section such as angles",
            "b) flat bars",
            "c) double angles",
            "d) circular section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tension members were generally made of flat bars earlier. But modern practice is to use mainly the following sections for tension members: (i)open sections such as angles, channels and I-sections, (ii)compound and built up sections such as double angle and double channels with or without additional plates, (iii)closed sections such as circular, square, rectangular or hollow sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Which among the following comparison between angle and flat bars is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) for light loads, angles are preferred over flat bars",
            "b) flat bar tension members tend to vibrate during passage of load in light bridges",
            "c) flat bars are used instead of angles in case of stress reversal",
            "d) angles are used instead of flat bars in case of stress reversal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For light loads, angles are preferred over flat bars. In many light bridges, flat bar tension members tend to vibrate during passage of load. In case of stress reversal angles are more suitable whereas flat bars are unfit to carry compressive load on reversal due to their small radius of gyration in one direction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) angles placed on same side of gusset plate produce eccentricity about one plane only",
            "b) angles placed on same side of gusset plate produce eccentricity about two planes",
            "c) angles placed on opposite side of gusset plate produce eccentricity about one plane only",
            "d) angles placed on opposite side of gusset plate produce eccentricity about two planes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two angle sections can either be placed back-to-back on the same side of gusset plate, or back-to-back on the opposite side of gusset plate. When angles are connected on the same side of gusset plate, the eccentricity is about one plane only, which can be almost eliminated when the same angles are connected on opposite side of gusset plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about built up section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Built up members are less rigid than single rolled section",
            "b) Single rolled section are formed to meet required area which cannot be provided by built up members",
            "c) Built up members can be made sufficiently stiff",
            "d) Built up sections are not desirable when stress reversal occurs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Built-up members, made up of two or more plates or shapes and connected to act as single member, are formed primarily to meet required area which cannot be provided by single rolled section. Built up members are more rigid because for same area much greater moment of inertia can be obtained than single rolled section. Built up members can be made sufficiently stiff to carry compression and tension thus desirable when stress reversal occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "What is slenderness ratio of a tension member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ratio of its least radius of gyration to its unsupported length",
            "b) ratio of its unsupported length to its least radius of gyration",
            "c) ratio of its maximum radius of gyration to its unsupported length",
            "d) ratio of its unsupported length to its maximum radius of gyration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Slenderness ratio of tension member is ratio of its unsupported length to its least radius of gyration. This limiting slenderness ratio is required in order to prevent undesirable lateral movement or excessive vibration."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "What is the maximum effective slenderness ratio for a tension member in which stress reversal occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 180",
            "b) 200",
            "c) 280",
            "d) 300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum effective slenderness ratio for a tension member in which stress reversal occurs due to loads other than wind or seismic forces is 180."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "What is the maximum effective slenderness ratio for a member subjected to compressive forces resulting only from combination of wind/earthquake actions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 180",
            "b) 200",
            "c) 340",
            "d) 250"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum effective slenderness ratio for a member subjected to compressive forces resulting only from combination of wind or earthquake actions, such that the deformation of such member does not adversely affect stresses in any part of structure is 250."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "What is the maximum effective slenderness ratio for a member normally acting as a tie in roof truss or a bracing member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 180",
            "b) 200",
            "c) 350",
            "d) 400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum effective slenderness ratio for a member normally acting as a tie in roof truss or a bracing member, which is not considered when subject to stress reversal resulting from action of wind or earthquake forces is 350."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "What is the maximum effective slenderness ratio for members always in tension?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400",
            "b) 200",
            "c) 350",
            "d) 150"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum effective slenderness ratio for members always in tension other than pre-tensioned members is 400."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "The limits specified for slenderness ratio are not",
        "Options": [
            "a) applicable to cables",
            "b) applicable to angle sections",
            "c) applicable to built-up sections",
            "d) applicable to circular sections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The limits specified for slenderness ratio in the IS code are not applicable to cables. They are applicable to angle sections, built-up sections, circular sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "The displacement of tension member under service load is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) PLEAg",
            "b) PLE/Ag",
            "c) PL/EAg",
            "d) P/LEAg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The displacement, that is increase in length of tension member, under service load is given by Δ = PL/EAg, where Δ = Elongation of member in mm, P= unfactored axial load in N, L = length of member in mm, E = elastic modulus = 2×105MPa, Ag = gross cross sectional area of member in mm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "What is gross section yielding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) considerable deformation of the member in longitudinal direction may take place before it fractures, making the structure unserviceable",
            "b) considerable deformation of the member in longitudinal direction may take place before it fractures, making the structure serviceable",
            "c) considerable deformation of the member in lateral direction may take place before it fractures, making the structure unserviceable",
            "d) considerable deformation of the member in lateral direction may take place before it fractures, making the structure serviceable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tension member without bolt holes can resist loads up to ultimate load without failure. But such a member will deform in longitudinal direction considerably(10-15% of its original length)before fracture and the structure becomes unserviceable."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "What is net section rupture failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rupture of member when the cross section reaches yield stress",
            "b) rupture of member when the cross section reaches ultimate stress",
            "c) rupture of member when the cross section reaches less value than yield stress",
            "d) rupture of member when the cross section is reaches  very less value than ultimate stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The point adjacent to hole reaches yield stress first when tension member with hole is loaded statically. The stress at that point remains constant and each fibre away from hole progressively reaches yield stress on further loading. With increasing load, deformations continue until finally rupture of member occurs when entire net cross section of member reaches ultimate stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "The tensile stress adjacent to hole will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) about five times the average stress on the net area",
            "b) about half the average stress on the net area",
            "c) equal to average stress on the net area",
            "d) about two to three times the average stress on the net area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From the theory of elasticity, the tensile stress adjacent to hole will be about two to three times the average stress on the net area, depending upon the ratio of diameter of hole to the width of plate normal to direction of stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "What is stress concentration factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ratio of average stress to maximum elastic stress",
            "b) product of average stress and maximum elastic stress",
            "c) ratio of maximum elastic stress to average stress",
            "d) twice the average stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ratio of maximum elastic stress to average stress (fmax/favg)is called as stress concentration factor. It becomes very significant when repeated applications of load may lead to fatigue failure or where there is possibility of brittle fracture of tension member under dynamic load. It may minimised by providing suitable joint and member details."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "What is block shear failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) failure of fasteners occurs along path involving tension on one plane and shear on perpendicular plane along fasteners",
            "b) failure of member occurs along path involving tension on one plane and shear on perpendicular plane along fasteners",
            "c) failure of member occurs along path involving tension on one plane and shear on parallel plane along fasteners",
            "d) failure of fasteners occurs along path involving tension on one plane and shear on parallel plane along fasteners"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Failure of member occurs along path that involves (i) tension on one plane and (ii) shear on perpendicular plane along fasteners in block shear failure mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "The possibility of block shear failure increases by",
        "Options": [
            "a) larger connection length",
            "b) increasing the number of bolts per connection",
            "c) with use of low strength bolts",
            "d) with use of high bearing strength material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The block shear failure becomes a possible mode of failure when material bearing strength and bolt shear strength are higher. When high bearing strength of material and high strength bolts are used, only few bolts are required in connection. Decreasing number of bolts per connection results in smaller connection length, but the possibility of block shear failure increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) stress and strain calculated using initial cross section area and initial gauge length are referred to as true stress and true strain",
            "b) stress and strain calculated using current cross section area and initial gauge length are referred to as true stress and engineering strain",
            "c) stress and strain calculated using initial cross section area and initial gauge length are referred to as engineering stress and engineering strain",
            "d) stress and strain calculated using current cross section area and gauge length are referred to as engineering stress and engineering strain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stress and strain calculated using initial cross section area and initial gauge length are referred to as engineering stress and engineering strain. Stress and strain calculated using current cross section area and gauge length are referred to as true stress and true strain."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Arrange the regions of engineering stress-strain curve in order from right to left as in graph",
        "Options": [
            "a) strain softening region, strain hardening region, yield plateau, linear elastic region",
            "b) strain hardening region, strain softening region, linear elastic region, yield plateau",
            "c) strain softening region, yield plateau, linear elastic region, strain hardening region",
            "d) strain hardening region, linear elastic region, yield plateau, strain softening region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The engineering stress-strain curve is typically represented by four regions : linear elastic region, yield plateau, strain hardening region, strain softening (unloading)region."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding engineering stress-strain curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it gives true indication of deformation characteristics of metal because it is entirely based on true dimensions of specimen",
            "b) it does not gives true indication of deformation characteristics of metal because it is entirely based on true dimensions of specimen",
            "c) it gives true indication of deformation characteristics of metal because it is not entirely based on true dimensions of specimen",
            "d) it does not gives true indication of deformation characteristics of metal because it is not entirely based on true dimensions of specimen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The engineering stress-strain curve does not provide true indication of deformation characteristics of metal. It is entirely based on true dimensions of specimen and these dimensions change continuously as the load increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Choose the correct option",
        "Options": [
            "a) post ultimate strain softening in engineering stress strain curve is present in true stress strain curve",
            "b) post ultimate strain softening in true stress strain curve is absent in engineering  stress strain curve",
            "c) post ultimate strain softening in true stress strain curve is present",
            "d) post ultimate strain softening in engineering stress strain curve is absent in true stress strain curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The post ultimate strain softening in engineering stress strain curve caused by necking of cross section is absent in true stress strain curve as engineering stress strain curve are based on true dimensions of specimen and true stress strain curve are based on actual cross sectional area of specimen."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "What is the yield point for high strength steel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5% of offset load",
            "b) 0.2% of offset load",
            "c) 0.1% of offset load",
            "d) 1.5% of offset load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High-strength steel tension members do not exhibit well defined yield point and yield plateau. Hence, 0.2% of offset load is usually taken as yield point for such high strength steel."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "True stress strain curve is also known as",
        "Options": [
            "a) flow curve",
            "b) un-flow curve",
            "c) elastic curve",
            "d) parabolic curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True stress strain curve is also known as flow curve since it represents basic plastic flow characteristics if the material. Any point on the flow curve can be considered as local stress for metal strained in tension by magnitude shown on the curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The design strength of tension member corresponding to gross section yielding is given by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) γm0 fyAg",
            "b) γm0fy/Ag",
            "c) fy/Ag γm0",
            "d) fyAg/ γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design strength of tension member corresponding to gross section yielding is given by Tdg = fyAg/ γm0, where fy = yield strength of material in MPa, Ag = gross cross-sectional area in mm2, γm0 = partial safety factor for failure in tension by yielding = 1.10."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Net area = Gross area x deductions",
            "b) Net area = Gross area + deductions",
            "c) Net area = Gross area – deductions",
            "d) Net area = Gross area / deductions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Net area = Gross area – deductions, that is net area of tensile members is calculated by deducting areal of holes from the gross area."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "The design strength of tension member corresponding to net section rupture is given by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anfyγm1",
            "b) 0.9Anfyγm1",
            "c) 0.9An/fyγm1",
            "d) 0.9Anfy/γm1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design strength of tension member corresponding to net section rupture is given by Tdn = 0.9Anfy/γm1,  where An = net effective area of cross section in mm2, fy = ultimate strength of material in MPa, γm1 = partial safety factor for failure due to rupture of cross section = 1.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "The block shear strength at an end connection for shear yield and tension fracture is given by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Avgfy/√3 γm0)+(0.9Atnfu/γm1)",
            "b) (Atgfy/√3 γm0)+(0.9Avnfu/γm1)",
            "c) (0.9Atgfy/√3 γm0)+( Avnfu/γm1)",
            "d) (0.9Avgfy/√3 γm0)+(Atnfu/γm1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The block shear strength at an end connection for shear yield and tension fracture is given by Tdb1 = (Avgfy/√3 γm0)+(0.9Atnfu/γm1), where Avg = minimum gross area in shear along line of action of force, Atn = minimum net area of cross section in tension from hole to toe of angle or last row of bolts in plates perpendicular to line of force, fy and fu are yield and ultimate stress of material respectively, γm1 = 1.25, γm0 = 1.10."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The block shear strength at an end connection for shear fracture and tension yield is given by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Avgfy/√3 γm0)+(0.9Atnfu/γm1)",
            "b) (Atgfy/ γm0)+(0.9Avnfu/√3 γm1)",
            "c) (0.9Avgfy/√3 γm0)+(Atnfu/γm1)",
            "d) (0.9Atgfy/√3 γm0)+( Avnfu/γm1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The block shear strength at an end connection for shear fracture and tension yield is given by Tdb2 = (Atgfy/ γm0)+(0.9Avnfu/√3 γm1), where Avn = minimum net area in shear along line of action of force, Atg = minimum gross area in tension from hole to toe of angle or last row of bolts in plates perpendicular to line of force, fy and fu are yield and ultimate stress of material respectively, γm1 = 1.25, γm0 = 1.10."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "The block shear strength of connection is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) block shear strength at an end connection for shear fracture and tension yield",
            "b) block shear strength at an end connection for shear yield and tension fracture",
            "c) larger of block shear strength at an end connection for (shear fracture, tension yield) and (shear yield, tension fracture)",
            "d) smaller of block shear strength at an end connection for (shear fracture, tension yield) and (shear yield, tension fracture)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The block shear strength of connection is smaller of block shear strength at an end connection for shear yield, tension fracture Tdb1 = (Avgfy/√3 γm0)+(0.9Atnfu/γm1) and block shear strength at an end connection for shear fracture, tension yield Tdb2 = (Atgfy/ γm0)+(0.9Avnfu/√3 γvm1)."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "The design tensile strength of tensile member is",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimum of strength due to gross yielding, net section rupture, block shear",
            "b) maximum of strength due to gross yielding, net section rupture, block shear",
            "c) strength due to gross yielding",
            "d) strength due to block shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design tensile strength of tensile member is taken as the minimum of strength due to gross yielding (Tdg=fyAg/1.1), net section rupture(Tdn=0.9Anfy/γm1), block shear (Tdb1=(Avgfy/√3 γm0)+(0.9Atnfu/γm1),  Tdb2=(Atgfy/ γm0)+(0.9Avnfu/√3 γm1)). "
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for angles as tension members?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angles if axially loaded through centroid can be designed as plates",
            "b) Angles connected to gusset plates by welding or bolting only through one of the two legs results in eccentric loading",
            "c) When load is applied by connecting only one leg of member, there is shear lag at the end connection",
            "d) When angles are connected to gusset plates by welding or bolting only through one of the two legs resulting in eccentric loading, there is a uniform stress distribution over cross section."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Angles if axially loaded through centroid can be designed as plates. Angles connected to gusset plates by welding or bolting only through one of the two legs results in eccentric loading, causing non-uniform stress distribution over cross section. When load is applied by connecting only one leg of member, there is shear lag at the end connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true statement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) thickness of angle has no significant influence on member strength",
            "b) net section efficiency is lower when long leg of angle is connected rather than short leg",
            "c) when length of connection decreases, the tensile strength increases",
            "d) effect of gusset plate thickness on ultimate tensile strength is significant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: (i) The effect of gusset plate thickness on ultimate tensile strength is not significant, (ii) the thickness of angle has no significant influence on member strength, (iii) the net section efficiency is higher(7-10%) when long leg of angle is connected rather than short leg, (iv) when length of connection increases, the tensile strength increases upto four bolts and effect of any further increase in number of bolts on tensile strength of member is not significant."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "The additional factor to be added for angles for design strength of tension member corresponding to net section rupture is given by :",
        "Options": [
            "a) βAg0fyγm0",
            "b) βAg0fy/γm0",
            "c) βAg0γm0",
            "d) βAg0/fyγm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design strength of angle section governed by tearing at net section is given by     Tdn = (0.9Ancfu/γm1) + βAg0fy/γm0 , where Anc = net area of connected leg, Ag0 = gross area of outstanding leg, fu = ultimate strength of material, γm1 = partial safety factor for failure due to rupture of cross section = 1.25, γm0 = partial safety factor for failure in tension by yielding = 1.10."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "The constant β in βAg0fy/γm0 for tensile strength of angle section does not depend on :",
        "Options": [
            "a) area of unconnected leg",
            "b) size of outstanding leg",
            "c) ultimate stress of material",
            "d) thickness of outstanding leg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: β = 1.4 – 0.076[(bs/Lc)(w/t)(fy/fu)] , where fu and fy are ultimate and yield stress of material, w and t are size and thickness of outstanding leg respectively, bs is the shear distance from edge of outstanding leg to nearest line of fasteners, Lc is the length of end connection measured from centre of first bolt hole to centre of last bolt hole in the end connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) β ≥ fuγm0/fyγm1",
            "b) β ≥ fuγm1/fy γm0",
            "c) β ≤ fuγm0/fyγm1",
            "d) β ≤ fuγm1/fy γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tdn = (0.9Ancfu/γm1) + βAg0fy/γm0, where β = 1.4 – 0.076[(bs/Lc)(w/t)(fy/fu)] and β ≤ fuγm0/fyγm1, β ≥ 0.7."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "What is the maximum value of β in βAg0fy/γm0 for tensile strength of angle section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2",
            "b) 0.9",
            "c) 1.4",
            "d) 0.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tdn = (0.9Ancfu/γm1) + βAg0fy/γm0, where β = 1.4 – 0.076[(bs/Lc)(w/t)(fy/fu)] and β ≥ 0.7."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "What is the value of partial factor of safety for material α for preliminary design for angle section as per IS code for three bolts in connection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.6",
            "b) 0.7",
            "c) 0.8",
            "d) 1.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per IS code, the equation for preliminary design of angle tension member  with partial factor of safety for material is given by Tdn = αAnfy/γm1, where α = 0.6 for one or two bolts, 0.7 for two bolts, 0.8 for four or more bolts in the end connection or equivalent weld length."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) strength of members with punched holes is less than members with drilled holes",
            "b) strength of members with drilled holes is less than members with punched holes",
            "c) strength of members with punched holes is greater than members with drilled holes",
            "d) strength of members with punched holes is equal to members with drilled holes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Strength of members with punched holes may be 10-15% less than the members with drilled holes. This is due to strain hardening effect of material around punched holes and consequent loss of ductility."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "The presence of holes _____ the strength of tension member",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not affect",
            "b) improves",
            "c) reduces",
            "d) doubles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bolt holes reduce the area of cross section available to carry tension and hence reduce the strength of tension member."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Staggering of holes __________ the load carrying capacity of tension member",
        "Options": [
            "a) reduces",
            "b) improves",
            "c) does not affect",
            "d) halves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Staggering of holes improves the load carrying capacity of tension member for given number of bolts. The failure paths may occur along sections normal to axis of member, or they may include zigzag sections when more than one bolt hole is present  and staggering of holes may help to make the net area minimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The actual failure mode in bearing depends on",
        "Options": [
            "a) length of metal plate",
            "b) length of bolt",
            "c) hole diameter",
            "d) bolt diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The actual failure mode in bearing depends on end distance, bolt diameter and thickness of the connected material."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "The shear lag effect _____ with increase in connection length",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) reduces",
            "c) does not change",
            "d) doubles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shear lag effect increases with increase in connection length. The shear lag reduces the effectiveness of component plates of tension member that are not connected directly to gusset plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase in ductility reduces strength of member",
            "b) reduction in ductility increases strength of member",
            "c) increase in ductility does not affect strength of member",
            "d) reduction in ductility reduces strength of member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reduction in ductility tends to reduce strength of member. An increase in ductility tends to increase net section strength by allowing better plastic redistribution of stress concentration over cross section."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": " Which of the following statement is true regarding residual stresses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) residual stress result in local early strain hardening",
            "b) it increase plastic range of member",
            "c) it is not important when fatigue is involved",
            "d) it improves strength of member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Residual stress result in local early strain hardening and reduce plastic range of member. Residual stresses have no consequences with respect to static strength of member, they can be important if fatigue is involved."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Lug angles are ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) additional angles used to reduce joint length",
            "b) additional angles used to increase joint length",
            "c) additional angles used for aesthetic appearance",
            "d) additional angles used for seismic resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When tension member is subjected to heavy load, the number of bolts or length of welds required for making connection becomes large, it results in uneconomical size of gusset plates. In such situations, additional short angles called lug angles may be used to reduce joint length and shear lag."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Lug angles are found to be more effective at _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) end of the connection",
            "b) middle of connection",
            "c) beginning of connection",
            "d) they are equally effective at all connections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lug angles are found to be more effective at beginning of connection rather than the end due to non-uniform distribution of load among connecting bolts."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": " Which of the following solution can be used to eliminate lug angles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) by providing equal angle sections with wider leg as connected leg",
            "b) by providing unequal angle sections with wider leg as connected leg",
            "c) by providing equal angle sections with shorter leg as connected leg",
            "d) by providing unequal angle sections with shorter leg as connected leg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lug angles can be eliminated by providing unequal angle sections with wider leg as connected leg and using two rows of staggered bolts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct in case of angle members?",
        "Options": [
            "a) connection of lug angle to angle member should be capable of developing a strength of 10% of excess of force of outstanding leg of angle",
            "b) connection of lug angle to angle member should be capable of developing a strength of 20% of excess of force of outstanding leg of angle",
            "c) lug angles and their connection to gusset should be capable of developing a strength of less than 20% of excess of force of outstanding leg of angle",
            "d) lug angles and their connection to gusset should be capable of developing a strength of not less than 20% of excess of force of outstanding leg of angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of angle members, lug angles and their connection to gusset should be capable of developing a strength of not less than 20% of excess of force of outstanding leg of angle, and the connection of lug angle to angle member should be capable of developing a strength of 40% of excess of force."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct in case of channel members?",
        "Options": [
            "a) connection of lug angle to angle member should have a strength not less than 20% of excess of force in flange of channel",
            "b) connection of lug angle to angle member should have a strength less than 20% of excess of force in flange of channel",
            "c) lug angles and their connection to gusset should be capable of developing a strength of less than 10% of excess of force in flange of channel",
            "d) lug angles and their connection to gusset should be capable of developing a strength of less than 5% of excess of force in flange of channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of channel members, lug angles and their connection to gusset should be capable of developing a strength of not less than 10% of excess of force in flange of channel, and the attachment of lug angle to angle member should have a strength not less than 20% of excess of that force."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Splices are provided when_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) available length is more than required length of a tension member",
            "b) available length is less than required length of a tension member",
            "c) available length is equal to required length of a tension member",
            "d) for aesthetic appearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Splices are provided when the available length is less than required length of a tension member.  Splices in tension members are used to join sections when a joint is to be provided that is these replace the members at the joint where it is cut. If the sections to spliced are not of same thickness, then packing plates are introduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "As per IS specification, splice connection should be designed for a force of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) at least 0.3 times the member design capacity in tension",
            "b) at least 0.1 times the member design capacity in tension",
            "c) less than 0.3 times the member design capacity in tension",
            "d) less than 0.15 times the member design capacity in tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per IS specification, splice connection should be designed for a force of at least 0.3 times the member design capacity in tension or the design action, whichever is more."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": " Which of the following is  not correct about gusset plates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gusset plate is provided to make connections at place where more than one member is to be joined",
            "b) plate outlines are fixed to meet minimum edge distances for bolts used for connection",
            "c) lines of action of truss members meeting at a joint should  not coincide",
            "d) size and shape of gusset plates are usually decided from direction of members meeting at joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A gusset plate is plate provided at ends of tension members through which forces are transferred to main member. Gusset plates are used to join more than one member at a joint. The lines of action of truss members meeting at a joint should coincide. The size and shape of gusset plates are usually decided from direction of members meeting at joint. The plate outlines are fixed to meet minimum edge distances for bolts used for connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "What is the minimum thickness of gusset plate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5mm",
            "b) 8mm",
            "c) 10mm",
            "d) 12mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The thickness of gusset plate in any case should not be less than 12mm. Structurally a gusset plate is subjected to shear stresses, direct stresses and bending stresses and therefore it should be of ample thickness to resist all these at the critical section."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "For the calculation of net area of flat with staggered bolts, the area to be deducted from gross area is :",
        "Options": [
            "a) nd",
            "b) n’p2t/8g",
            "c) ndt – n’p2t/4g",
            "d) nd + n’p2t/4g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The net area of flat with staggered hole is given by : A = (b – ndh + n’p2/4g)t, where b = width of plate, n = number of holes in zig-zag line, n’ = number of staggered pitches, p = pitch distance, g= gauge distance, t = thickness of flat."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "What is the net section area of steel plate 40cm wide and 10mm thick with one bolt if diameter of bolt hole is 18mm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 38.2 cm2",
            "b) 20 cm2",
            "c) 240 mm2",
            "d) 480 mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: b = 40cm = 400mm, t = 10mm, dh = 18mm\nNet section area = 400×10 – 16×10 = 3820mm2 = 38.2 cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "What is the net area for the plate 100 x 8 mm bolted  with a single bolt of 20mm diameter in case of drilled hole ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 624 mm2",
            "b) 756 mm2",
            "c) 800 mm2",
            "d) 640 mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The section giving minimum area of plate is considered for design. So, section 1-5-7-6-3 is used for net area of flat."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Determine the effective net area for angle section ISA 100 x 75 x 12 mm, when 100mm leg is connected to a gusset plate using weld of length 140mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1795 mm2",
            "b) 1812 mm2",
            "c) 1956 mm2",
            "d) 2100 mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: B = 300mm, t = 10mm, dh = 18+2 =20mm, n = 3, n’ = 1, p = 75mm, g = 50mm\nEffective net area = (B-ndh+n’p2/4g)t = (300 – 3×20 + 1×752/4×50)x10 = 2681.25 mm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Calculate the value of β for the given angle section ISA 150x115x8mm of Fe410 grade of steel connected with gusset plate : Length of weld = 150mm",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.89",
            "b) 0.75",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of drilled hole, dh = 20mm\nNet Area An = Ag – dht = 100 x 8 – 20 x 8 = 640mm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Calculate the tensile strength due to gross section yielding of an angle section 125 x 75 x 10mm of Fe410 grade of steel connected with a gusset plate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 780 kN",
            "b) 586.95 kN",
            "c) 432.27 kN",
            "d) 225.36 kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Net area of connected leg, Anc = (100 – 12/2) x 12 = 1128 mm2\nNet area of outstanding leg, Ago = (75 – 12/2) x 12 = 828 mm2\nTotal net area = 1128 + 828 = 1956 mm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "A single unequal angle 100 x 75 x 10 of Fe410 grade of steel is connected to a 10mm thick gusset plate at the ends with six 16mm diameter bolts with pitch of 40mm to transfer tension. Find the tensile strength due to net section rupture if gusset is connected to 100mm leg.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 526.83 kN",
            "b) 385.74 kN",
            "c) 450.98 kN",
            "d) 416.62 kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: w=115mm, t=8mm, b=115mm, Lc=150mm, fy=250MPa, fu=410MPa\nβ = 1.4 – [0.076 (w/t)(fy/fu)(bs/Lc)]\n   = 1.4 – [ 0.076 x (115/8) x (250/410) x (115/150)] = 0.89 (>0.7) . "
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Structures designed using elastic analysis may be ______ than those designed using plastic analysis",
        "Options": [
            "a) lighter",
            "b) heavier",
            "c) of same weight",
            "d) almost half times the weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In elastic design structures are designed for allowable stress level well below the elastic limit, whereas in plastic design structures are designed using ultimate load rather than yield stress, Hence, structures designed using elastic analysis may be heavier than those designed using plastic analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Both elastic and plastic methods neglect ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) live load acting on structure",
            "b) dead load acting on structure",
            "c) deformations due to load",
            "d) influence of stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Both elastic and plastic methods neglect the influence of stability, which may significantly affect the load carrying capacity of structures or elements which are slender and subjected to compressive stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "What is buckling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural behaviour in which a deformation develops in direction of plane perpendicular to that of load which produced it",
            "b) Structural behaviour in which a deformation does not develop in direction of plane perpendicular to that of load which produced it",
            "c) Structural behaviour in which a deformation develop in direction of plane parallel to that of load which produced it",
            "d) Structural behaviour in which a deformation develops in direction of plane along that of load which produced it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Buckling may be defined as structural behaviour in which a deformation develops in direction of plane perpendicular to that of load which produced it. This deformation changes rapidly with variations in the applied load."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation about plastic moment is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mp = Zp /fy",
            "b) Mp = Zp + fy",
            "c) Mp = Zpfy",
            "d) Mp = Zp – fy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When every fibre of the section has a strain equal to or greater than εy=fy/Es , nominal moment strength is referred as plastic moment and is given by Mp = Zpfy , where Zp = ∫ydA is plastic section modulus and fy = yield stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "What is plastic moment of resistance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum moment in stress strain curve, the point where the curvature can increase indefinitely",
            "b) maximum moment in stress strain curve, the point where the curvature can decrease indefinitely",
            "c) minimum moment in stress strain curve, the point where the curvature can increase indefinitely",
            "d) minimum moment in stress strain curve, the point where the curvature can decrease indefinitely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In stress strain curve, the maximum moment is reached at a point where the curvature can increase indefinitely, neglecting the strain hardening benefits. This maximum moment is called plastic moment of resistance and the portion where this moment occurs is called as plastic hinge. "
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "In elastic stage, equilibrium condition is achieved when neutral axis ___________ and in fully plastic stage, it is achieved when neutral axis ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) is above centroid of the section, divides the section into two parts of one-third area and two-third area",
            "b) is below centroid of the section, divides the section into two parts of one-third area and two-third area",
            "c) is above centroid of the section, divides the section into two equal areas",
            "d) passes through centroid of the section, divides the section into two equal areas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In elastic stage, when bending stress varies from zero at neutral axis  to maximum at extreme fibres, equilibrium condition is achieved when neutral axis passes through centroid of the section. In fully plastic stage, because the stress is uniformly equal to yield stress, equilibrium condition is achieved when neutral axis divides the section into two equal areas. "
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct for plastic section modulus, Zo ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zp = 2A(y1+y2)",
            "b) Zp = A(y1+y2)/2",
            "c) Zp = A(y1+y2)/4",
            "d) Zp = 4A(y1+y2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Zp = A(y1+y2)/2, where A= area of cross section, y1 and y2 are centroids of portion above and below neutral axis respectively. Plastic modulus is defined as combined statical moment of cross sectional area above and below the equal-area axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct about shape factor, v?",
        "Options": [
            "a) v = Zp+Ze",
            "b) v = ZpZe",
            "c) v = Zp/Ze",
            "d) v = Ze/Zp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shape factor, v = Zp/Ze = Mp/My , where Zp and Ze are plastic and elastic section modulus respectively, Mp and My are plastic and elastic moments respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "The shape factor does not depend on ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) material properties",
            "b) cross sectional shape",
            "c) moment of resistance",
            "d) section modulus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shape factor, v = Zp/Ze = Mp/My, where Zp and Ze are plastic and elastic section modulus respectively, Mp and My are plastic and elastic moments respectively. This ratio is the property of cross-sectional shape and is independent of material properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "10. Match the pairs with correct shape factor<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\t\tCross section\t\t\t\tShape factor (average or maximum)\n\tA) Circular\t\t\t\t\t(i) 1.8\n\tB) Rectangular\t\t\t\t\t(ii) 1.14\n\tC) wide flange I-section (about major axis)\t(iii) 1.7\n\tD) Channels (about minor axis) \t\t\t(iv) 1.5</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii, D-iv",
            "b) A-iv, B-iii, C-ii, D-i",
            "c) A-iii, B-iv, C-ii, D-i",
            "d) A-iii, B-ii, C-iv, D-i"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shape factor, v = Zp/Ze = Mp/My. The shape factor for various cross section are (i) for circular = 1.7, (ii) for rectangular = 1.5, (iii) wide flange I-section (about major axis) = 1.09-1.18, average is 1.14, (iv) wide flange I-section (about minor axis) = 1.67, (v) channels (about major axis) = 1.16-1.22, average is 1.18, (vi) channels (about minor axis) = 1.8 ."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following assumptions is correct for plastic design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) material obeys Hooke’s law before the stress reaches fy",
            "b) yield stress and modulus of elasticity does not have same value in compression and tension",
            "c) material is homogenous and isotropic in both elastic and plastic states.",
            "d) material is not sufficiently ductile to permit large rotations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The material obeys Hooke’s law till the stress reaches fy. The yield stress and modulus of elasticity have the same value in compression and tension. The material is homogeneous and isotropic in both elastic and plastic states. The material is assumed to be sufficiently ductile to permit large rotations of section to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which of the following assumptions is not correct for plastic design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plastic hinge rotations are small compared with elastic deformations so all the rotations are concentrated at plastic hinges",
            "b) segments between plastic hinges are rigid",
            "c) influence of normal and shear forces on plastic moments is not considered",
            "d) plane section remains plane after bending and the effect of shear is neglected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The plastic hinge rotations are large compared with elastic deformations so all the rotations are concentrated at plastic hinges. The segments between plastic hinges are rigid. The influence of normal and shear forces on plastic moments is not considered. The plane section remains plane even after bending and the effect of shear is neglected."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the conditions that stress strain characteristics of steel should obey to ensure plastic moment redistribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) yield plateau should be less than 6 times the yield strain",
            "b) ratio of ultimate tensile stress to yield stress should be less than 1.2",
            "c) steel should not exhibit strain-hardening capacity",
            "d) elongation on standard gauge length should be more than 15%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The conditions that stress strain characteristics of steel should obey to ensure plastic moment redistribution are: (i) yield plateau(horizontal portion of stress strain curve) should be greater than 6 times the yield strain, (ii) ratio of ultimate tensile stress to yield stress should be more than 1.2, (iii) elongation on standard gauge length should be more than 15%, (iv) steel should exhibit strain-hardening capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditions are true for using plastic method of analysis as per IS 800?",
        "Options": [
            "a) members shall not be hot-rolled or fabricated using hot-plates",
            "b) yield stress of steel should not be greater than 450MPa",
            "c) cross section should be unsymmetrical about its axis perpendicular to axis of plastic hinge rotation",
            "d) cross section of members not containing plastic hinges should be ‘plastic’ and those members containing plastic hinges should be ‘compact’"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The following are conditions for using plastic method of analysis as per IS 800: (i) yield stress of steel should not be greater than 450MPa, (ii) members shall be hot-rolled or fabricated using hot-plates, (iii) cross section should be symmetrical about its axis perpendicular to the axis of plastic hinge rotation, (iv) cross section of members not containing plastic hinges should be ‘compact’ and those members containing plastic hinges should be ‘plastic’."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding plastic design methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) design needs to satisfy elastic strain compatibility conditions",
            "b) different factor of safety for all parts of the structure",
            "c) saving of material over elastic methods resulting in lighter structures",
            "d) design is effected by temperature changes, settlement of support, etc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The following are the advantages of plastic design methods: (i) realisation of uniform and realistic factor of safety for all parts of the structure\t, (ii)simplified analytical procedure and rapidity of obtaining moments since no need to satisfy elastic strain compatibility conditions, (iii) no effect due to temperature changes, settlement of support, etc, (iv) saving of material over elastic methods resulting in lighter structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding plastic design methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) difficult to design for fatigue",
            "b) more saving in column design",
            "c) lateral bracing requirements are less stringent than for elastic design",
            "d) moments produced by different loading conditions can be added together"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: (i) There is little saving in column design, (ii) lateral bracing requirements are more stringent than for elastic design, (iii) difficult to design for fatigue,(iv) moments produced by different loading conditions needs to be calculated separately(cannot be added together) and the largest plastic moment is selected."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "What is plastic hinge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) zone of bending due to flexure in a structural member",
            "b) zone of yielding due to flexure in a structural member",
            "c) zone of non-yielding due to flexure in a structural member",
            "d) zone of yielding due to twisting in a structural member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plastic hinge is a zone of yielding due to flexure in a structural member. It is used to describe a deformation of a section when plastic bending occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Plastic hinge behaves like a ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) friction mechanical hinge except that there is always a fixed moment constraint",
            "b) frictionless mechanical hinge except that there is no fixed moment constraint",
            "c) friction mechanical hinge except that there is no fixed moment constraint",
            "d) frictionless mechanical hinge except that there is always a fixed moment constraint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plastic hinge behaves like a frictionless mechanical hinge except that there is always a fixed moment constraint which is equal to plastic moment capacity of the section."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about hinged length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) value of moment adjacent to yield zone is more than yield moment up to hinged length of structural member",
            "b) value of moment adjacent to yield zone is less than yield moment up to hinged length of structural member",
            "c) value of moment adjacent to yield zone is half the yield moment up to hinged length of structural member",
            "d) value of moment adjacent to yield zone is equal to yield moment up to hinged length of structural member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of moment adjacent to yield zone is more than yield moment up to a certain length of structural member. This length is called hinged length."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Hinged length depends upon",
        "Options": [
            "a) weight of member",
            "b) type of connection",
            "c) type of loading",
            "d) number of bolts used in connection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hinged length depends upon the type of loading and the geometry of cross section of structural member."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "What is the hinged length for simply supported rectangular beam of span L with central concentrated load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L/√2",
            "b) 2L",
            "c) L/2",
            "d) L/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For simply supported rectangular beam with central concentrated load, the hinged length is equal to one-third of the span."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "What is the hinged length for simply supported rectangular beam  of span L with uniformly distributed load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L/√3",
            "b) L/√2",
            "c) L/2",
            "d) L/5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For simply supported rectangular beam with uniformly distributed load, the hinged length is equal to span/√3."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "What is plastic-collapse load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) load at which sufficient number of elastic hinges are formed",
            "b) load at which sufficient number of plastic hinges are not formed",
            "c) load at which sufficient number of plastic hinges are formed",
            "d) load at which structure fails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The load at which sufficient number of plastic hinges are formed in a structure such that a collapse mechanism is created is called plastic-collapse load or plastic-limit load."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "What is difference between plastic design and elastic design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In plastic design, redistribution of bending moment is considered",
            "b) In plastic design, redistribution of bending moment is not considered",
            "c) In elastic design, redistribution of bending moment is considered",
            "d) Both in plastic and elastic design, redistribution of bending moment is considered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The difference between plastic design and elastic design is that plastic design takes into account the favourable redistribution of bending moment which takes place in indeterminate structure after first hinge forms at the point of maximum bending moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": " Which of the following is true in a fixed beam having concentrated load at one-third point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) first hinge is formed at centre of beam",
            "b) after first hinge, moment at that point increases",
            "c) after first hinge, moment at that point decreases",
            "d) after first  hinge, moment at that hinge remains constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a fixed beam having concentrated load at one-third point, first hinge forms at one of the end supports. As load is increased further, moment at this hinge remains constant at Mp, while the moments at the other support and load point increase until second hinge is formed. When load is further increased, the moment at these two hinges remain constant at Mp, until third and final hinge is formed to make the beam a mechanism. The final ultimate load will be 33% higher than first hinge load."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "In a fixed beam having concentrated load at one-third point, final ultimate load will be ____ than first hinge load.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 33% lower",
            "b) 33% higher",
            "c) 50% higher",
            "d) 50% lower"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a fixed beam having concentrated load at one-third point, final ultimate load will be 33% higher than first hinge load."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plastic limit load is obtained by multiplying working load with load factor",
            "b) plastic limit load is obtained by dividing working load with load factor",
            "c) working load is obtained by multiplying plastic limit load with load factor",
            "d) working load is obtained by multiplying working load with load factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Plastic limit load is obtained by multiplying working load with load factor. Depending on combination of loads and their probability of acting at same time, different load factors are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Cantilevers and over hanging beams collapse as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) single-bar mechanism",
            "b) double-bar mechanism",
            "c) three-bar mechanism",
            "d) does not collapse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cantilevers and over hanging beams generally collapse as single-bar mechanisms with a single plastic hinge at one of the supports."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Single-span beams collapse as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) single-bar mechanism",
            "b) two-bar mechanism",
            "c) three-bar mechanism",
            "d) does not collapse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Single-span beams generally collapse as two-bar mechanisms with a hinge at each support and plastic hinge within the span."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Multi-span beams collapse in one span as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not collapse",
            "b) single-bar mechanism",
            "c) two-bar mechanism",
            "d) three-bar mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Multi-span beams generally collapse in one span as a local two-bar mechanism, within the span and a hinge at each support. It is possible to have a three-bar mechanism, where two adjacent spans combine to form a mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Among which of the following is the location of plastic hinge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) at supports",
            "b) at centre of beam",
            "c) at points away from concentrated load",
            "d) at centre for uniformly distributed load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Plastic hinges normally occur at supports, points of concentrated load, and points where cross section change. The location of plastic hinge in a beam with uniformly distributed load is not well defined."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "What is the condition for equilibrium in plastic analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bending moment distribution defined by assumed plastic hinges must not be in static equilibrium with applied loads and reactions",
            "b) shear force distribution defined by assumed plastic hinges must be in static equilibrium with applied loads and reactions",
            "c) bending moment distribution defined by assumed plastic hinges must be in static equilibrium with applied loads and reactions",
            "d) shear force distribution defined by assumed plastic hinges must not be in static equilibrium with applied loads and reactions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bending moment distribution defined by assumed plastic hinges must not be in static equilibrium with applied loads and reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ultimate load is reached when a mechanism is formed",
            "b) ultimate load is not reached when a mechanism is formed",
            "c) plastic hinges are not required for beam to form a mechanism",
            "d) frictionless hinges are not required for beam to form a mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There must be sufficient number of plastic and frictionless hinges for the beam/structure to form a mechanism. The ultimate load is reached when a mechanism is formed."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -Mp ≥ M",
            "b) M > Mp",
            "c) M ≥ Mp",
            "d) M ≤ Mp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bending moment in any section of a structure must be less than the plastic moment of the section -Mp ≤ M ≤ Mp."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Lowest plastic limit load is obtained when _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) only equilibrium condition of plastic analysis is satisfied",
            "b) only equilibrium and mechanism condition of plastic analysis are satisfied",
            "c) only mechanism condition of plastic analysis is satisfied",
            "d) equilibrium, mechanism and plasticity condition of plastic analysis are satisfied"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The lowest plastic limit load is obtained when all the conditions of equilibrium, mechanism and plasticity of plastic analysis are satisfied."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": " Which load is obtained when equilibrium and mechanism conditions of plastic analysis are satisfied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plastic limit load",
            "b) upper bound solution of true ultimate load",
            "c) lower bound solution of true ultimate load",
            "d) no solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When equilibrium and mechanism conditions of plastic analysis are satisfied, an upper bound solution of true ultimate load is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Which load is obtained when equilibrium and plasticity conditions of plastic analysis are satisfied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plastic limit load",
            "b) upper bound solution of true ultimate load",
            "c) lower bound solution of true ultimate load",
            "d) no solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When equilibrium and plasticity conditions of plastic analysis are satisfied, an lower bound solution of true ultimate load is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": " What is principle of virtual work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) work done by external forces is greater than work done by internal forces",
            "b) work done by external forces is less than work done by internal forces",
            "c) work done by external forces is equal to work done by internal forces",
            "d) work done by internal forces is greater than work done by external forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The principle of virtual work may be stated as if a system of forces in equilibrium is subjected to virtual displacement, the work done by external forces is equal to work done by internal forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Principle of virtual work is used to satisfy _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) mechanism condition",
            "b) equilibrium condition",
            "c) plasticity condition",
            "d) no condition is satisfied"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The principle of virtual work is used to satisfy equilibrium condition of plastic analysis. If the work condition is formulated correctly the equilibrium condition  is automatically satisfied."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Virtual work is used to determine _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) yield load",
            "b) elastic load",
            "c) plastic load",
            "d) collapse load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Virtual work principle is used to determine collapse load. It is the application of principle of least action to study forces and movement of a system."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": " What is static theorem ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) load must be greater than collapse load",
            "b) load must be less than collapse load",
            "c) load must be not equal to collapse load",
            "d) load cannot be related to collapse load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a given frame and loading if there exists any distribution of bending moments throughout the frame which is both safe and statically admissible with set of load P, then value of load P must be less than or equal to collapse load."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about static theorem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it represents upper limit to true ultimate load",
            "b) it represents plastic load",
            "c) it has minimum factor of safety",
            "d) it satisfies equilibrium and yield conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The static method represents the lower limit to the true ultimate load and has maximum factor of safety. The theorem satisfies equilibrium and yield conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is true for kinematic theorem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) load must be greater than collapse load",
            "b) load must be less than collapse load",
            "c) load must be not equal to collapse load",
            "d) load cannot be related to collapse load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a given frame subjected to a set of loads P, the value of P which is found to correspond to any assumed mechanism, must be greater than or equal to the collapse load Pu."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about kinematic theorem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it represents lower limit to true ultimate load",
            "b) it represents plastic load",
            "c) it has small factor of safety",
            "d) it satisfies equilibrium and yield conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Load computed on basis of this mechanism will always be greater than or at least equal to true ultimate load. Hence, kinematic method represents an upper limit to the true ultimate load and has a smaller factor of safety. This theorem satisfies equilibrium and continuity conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is true for uniqueness theorem?",
        "Options": [
            "a) load must be greater than collapse load",
            "b) load must be less than collapse load",
            "c) load must be equal to collapse load",
            "d) load cannot be related to collapse load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For given frame and loading, if at least one safe and statically admissible bending moment distribution can be found, and if in this distribution  bending moment is equal to fully plastic moment at sufficient cross sections to cause failure of frame as a mechanism due to rotation of plastic hinges, then corresponding load will be equal to collapse load."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Load is called as correct collapse load when",
        "Options": [
            "a) static theorem is not satisfied",
            "b) kinematic theorem is not satisfied",
            "c) only static theorem is satisfied",
            "d) both static and kinematic theorem are satisfied"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Load that satisfies both static and kinematic theorem at the same time is called correct collapse load. "
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about kinematic analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) virtual work equations are not used to determine collapse load",
            "b) virtual work equations are used to determine collapse load",
            "c) equilibrium condition is assumed",
            "d) plasticity condition is assumed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In kinematic method, a mechanism is assumed and virtual work equations are used to determine  the collapse load."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "The number of independent mechanism is related to number of possible plastic hinge locations by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) n = h * r",
            "b) n = h / r",
            "c) n = h + r",
            "d) n = h – r"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The number of independent mechanism (n) is related to number of possible plastic hinge locations (h) and number of degree of redundancy (r) of the frame by equation n = h-r."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "In static method of analysis, moment at any section is _______ plastic moment capacity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than",
            "b) two times",
            "c) less than",
            "d) three times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In static method of analysis, an equilibrium moment diagram is obtained such that the moment at any section is less than or equal to the plastic moment capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation between load factor, collapse load(Wc) and working load (W)",
        "Options": [
            "a) F = Wc / W",
            "b) F = W / Wc",
            "c) F = Wc W",
            "d) F = Wc + W"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Load factor is ratio of collapse load to working load. It is represented by, F = Wc / W."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Which of the following is load factor for simply supported beam with central point load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (fyfbc)v",
            "b) (fbc/ fy)v",
            "c) (fy/fbc)v",
            "d) (fy + fbc)v"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a simply supported beam with central point load,\nM = WL/4 = fbcZe, Mp = WcL/4 = fyvZe, where v is shape factor\nF = Mp/M = Wc/W = (fy/fbc)v. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "What is the value of load factor for I-section when fbc= 0.66fy and mean value of v is 0.14?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.727",
            "b) 2.7",
            "c) 1.56",
            "d) 3.98"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Load factor, F = (fy/fbc)v.  F = (1/0.66) x 0.14 = 1.27."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Single bay portal frames with fixed bases have _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) two redundancies",
            "b) three redundancies",
            "c) four redundancies",
            "d) zero redundancies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Single bay portal frames with fixed bases have three redundancies and require four hinges to produce a mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "If order of indeterminacy is r, then minimum number of plastic hinges required for total collapse is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) r-1",
            "b) r",
            "c) r+1",
            "d) r+2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If order of indeterminacy is r, then minimum number of plastic hinges required for total collapse is r+1."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which method is used when mechanism is applied to structures with sloping members?",
        "Options": [
            "a) method of instantaneous centre",
            "b) method of centre",
            "c) method of seismic centre",
            "d) method of metacentre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When mechanism is applied to structures with sloping members, the determination of displacements in the direction of applied forces is required. It is done using method of instantaneous centre or centre-of-rotation technique."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct for pin based frames?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mp =γL(wL2/8)[1-k+(1+k)0.5].",
            "b) Mp =γL(wL2/8)[1+k+(1-k)0.5].",
            "c) Mp =γL(wL2/8)[1+k-(1+k)0.5].",
            "d) Mp =γL(wL2/8)[1+k+(1+k)0.5]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When gravity load governs the design, a good estimate of required section may be obtained by using following formulae :\nFor pin based frames : Mp =γL(wL2/8)[1+k+(1+k)0.5]\nFor fixed=-base frame : Mp =γL(wL2/8)[1/[1+0.5k+(1+k)0.5]], where γL = 1.7 global load factor, k = h2/h1."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) combined mechanism is combination of elementary mechanism",
            "b) elementary mechanism is combination of combined mechanism",
            "c) combined mechanism is not combination of elementary mechanism",
            "d) elementary mechanism is combination of elementary and combined mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The possible mechanisms can be classified into two types : elementary and combined mechanism. Elementary mechanism is independent of each other, combined mechanism is linear combination of elementary mechanisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The presence of axial equation implies that _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sum of tension forces is always zero",
            "b) sum of compression forces is always zero",
            "c) sum of tension and compression forces is not zero",
            "d) sum of tension and compression forces is zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The presence of axial equation implies that sum of tension and compression forces is not zero and hence following equation is used : ∫A  fydA – P = 0, where P is the axial force."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct for rectangular section of width b and depth d subjected to axial force N together with moment M?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Mpr/Mp) + (N/Np)2 = 1",
            "b) (Mpr/Mp) – (N/Np)2 = 1",
            "c) (Mpr/Mp) + (N/Np) = 1",
            "d) (Mpr/Mp) – (N/Np) = 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a rectangular section of width b and depth d subjected to axial force N together with moment M, (Mpr/Mp) + (N/Np)2 = 1, where Mpr is moment with axial force, Mp is moment with axial force, Np is axial force without any moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct for I- section of width b and depth d subjected to axial force N together with moment M?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (N/Np) – (1/1.18)(M/Mp) ≤ 1, when N/Np > 0.15",
            "b) (N/Np) – (1/1.18)(M/Mp) ≤ 1, when N/Np < 0.15",
            "c) (N/Np) + (1/1.18)(M/Mp) ≤ 1, when N/Np < 0.15",
            "d) (N/Np) + (1/1.18)(M/Mp) ≤ 1, when N/Np > 0.15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For I- section subjected to axial force N together with moment M,\n(N/Np) + (1/1.18)(M/Mp) ≤ 1, when N/Np > 0.15\nM = Mp, when N/Np < 0.15 . "
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "When a member is subjected to uniaxial tensile or compressive stress in presence of shear stress  τ , yield occurs when ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) fy2 = f2 – 3 τ",
            "b) fy2 = f2 + 3 τ2",
            "c) fy2 = f2 – 3 τ2",
            "d)  fy2 = f2 + 3 τ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a member is subjected to uniaxial tensile or compressive stress in presence of shear stress  τ, yield occurs when fy2 = f2 + 3 τ2."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Yield in pure shear occurs when ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.58 fy",
            "b) 1.58 fy",
            "c) 2.8 fy",
            "d) 3.5 fy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yield in pure shear occurs when τy = fy/√3 = 0.58 fy."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "At full plasticity, the stress in web is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) fw = fy√[1+(τw/τy)2 ].",
            "b) fw = fy√[(τw/τy)2 ].",
            "c) fw = fy√[1-(τw/τy)2 ].",
            "d) fw = fy√[1+2(τw/τy)2 ]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When full plasticity is produced, the stress in web will be equal to fw, fw =√(fy2 -3τw2 ) = fy√[1-(w/τy)2 ]  where τy is shear strengths when yield is in pure shear."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Loss of web capacity is given by ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zpw / (fy – fw)",
            "b) Zpw (fy – fw)",
            "c) Zpw (fy + fw)",
            "d) Zpw /(fy + fw)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Loss of web capacity is given by Zpw (fy – fw)  = Zpw fy { 1-√[1-(τw/τy)2] }. "
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Buckling occurs to members or elements mainly subjected to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) seismic forces",
            "b) tensile forces",
            "c) compressive forces",
            "d) shear forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Buckling may be defined as structural behavior in which mode of deformation develops in direction or plane perpendicular to that of bending which produces it. Such deformation changes rapidly with increase in magnitude of applied loading. It occurs mainly members or elements that are subjected to compressive forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "The critical stress of infinite plate having width b and thickness t loaded by compressive forces acting on simply supported sides is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) (kπ2E)/ [12(1-μ2)(b/t)].",
            "b) (kπ2E)/ [12(1-μ2)(b/t)2].",
            "c) (kπ2E)/ [12(1+μ2)(b/t)].",
            "d) (kπ2E)/ [12(1+μ2)(b/t)2]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The critical stress of infinite plate having width b and thickness t loaded by compressive forces acting on simply supported sides is given by\n                                 fcr = (kπ2E)/ [12(1-μ2)(b/t)2],\nwhere μ is Poisson’s ratio of material, b/t is width-to-thickness ratio of plate, k is buckling coefficient and E is Young’s modulus of rigidity of material. The value of coefficient k depends on constraints along non-loaded edges of plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) stiffened elements are supported along one edge perpendicular to axial stress",
            "b) un-stiffened elements are supported along one edge perpendicular to axial stress",
            "c) stiffened elements are supported along one edge parallel to axial stress",
            "d) un-stiffened elements are supported along one edge parallel to axial stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Unstiffened elements are supported along one edge parallel to axial stress (eg : legs of single angles, flanges of beams, and stems of T-section). Stiffened elements are supported along both the edges parallel to axial stress (eg: flanges of square and rectangular hollow sections, perforated cover plates, and webs of I-sections and channel sections)."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Lowest value of buckling coefficient for simply supported plates is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.0",
            "b) 2.0",
            "c) 5.0",
            "d) 3.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lowest value of buckling coefficient for simply supported plates is 4.0. The buckilng stress depends upon buckling coefficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "The buckling stress fcr varies _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) inversely as plate slenderness or width-to-thickness ratio",
            "b) directly as plate slenderness or width-to-thickness ratio",
            "c) inversely as square of plate slenderness or width-to-thickness ratio",
            "d) directly as square of plate slenderness or width-to-thickness ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The buckling stress fcr varies inversely as square of plate slenderness or width-to-thickness ratio,  √(fy /fcr) = (b/t)√{(fy / E)[12(1-μ2)/(π2k)]} ."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The buckling coefficient for thin flat plate free along one longitudinal edge is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) k = 0.425 + (b/a)",
            "b) k = 0.425 + (b/a)2",
            "c) k = 0.425 + (a/b)2",
            "d) k = 0.425 – (b/a)2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a thin plate simply supported along both transverse edged and one longitudinal edge and free along the other longitudinal edge, the buckling coefficient can be approximated by k = 0.425 + (b/a)2."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "The elastic buckling stress of thin flat plate of length L, depth d and thickness t simply supported along four edges and loaded by shear stresses distributed uniformly along its edges is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) fcr = kπ2E / [12(1-μ2)(d/t)2].",
            "b) fcr = kπ2E / [12(1+μ2)(d/t)2].",
            "c) fcr = kπ2E / [12(1-μ2)(d/t)].",
            "d) fcr = kπ2E / [12(1+μ2)(d/t)]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The elastic buckling stress fcr of thin flat plate of length L, depth d and thickness t simply supported along all four edges and loaded by shear stresses distributed uniformly along its edges is given by fcr = kπ2E / [12(1-μ2)(d/t)2], where buckling coefficient can be approximated by  k=5.35 + 4(d/L)2, when L ≥ d and k = 5.35(d/L)2 + 4, when L ≤ d."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "The elastic buckling stress for thin flat plate of length L, depth d and thickness t simply supported along four edges and loaded by bending stress distribution is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) fcr  = π2E/k[12(1-μ2)(d/t)2].",
            "b) fcr  = π2E/k[12(1+μ2)(d/t)2].",
            "c) fcr  = kπ2E/[12(1+μ2)(d/t)2].",
            "d) fcr  = kπ2E/[12(1-μ2)(d/t)2]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The elastic buckling stress for thin flat plate of length L, depth d and thickness t simply supported along all four edges and loaded by bending stress distribution, which varies linearly across its width is given by fcr  = kπ2E/[12(1-μ2)(d/t)2], where buckling coefficient k depends on aspect ratio L/d and the number of buckles along the plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Which of following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) elastic buckling stress may be decreased by using longitudinal stiffeners",
            "b) elastic buckling stress may be decreased by using intermediate stiffeners",
            "c) elastic buckling stress may be increased by using intermediate  transverse stiffeners",
            "d) elastic buckling stress is not affected by intermediate or longitudinal stiffeners"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The elastic buckling stress may be increased by using intermediate transverse stiffeners (which will decrease the aspect ratio L/d, thus increasing the value of buckling coefficient), or by using longitudinal stiffeners to decrease the depth-thickness ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "10. Match the following values of limiting b/t or d/t ratio for various cases<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\tPlates\t\t\t                 (b/t))√(fy /250) or (d/t)√(fy /250)\n&nbsp;\ni. Simply supported plates\t\t\t\t\tA) 17.5\nii. Long plate elements in shear\t\t\t\tB) 131.4\niii. Long plate elements free along one longitudinal edge\tC) 81.9\niv. Long plate elements in bending\t\t\t\tD) 53.8</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) i-A, ii-B, iii-C, iv-D",
            "b) i-D, ii-C, iii-A, iv-B",
            "c) i-C, ii-D, iii-B, iv-A",
            "d) i-D, ii-C, iii-B, iv-A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: i) For simply supported plates, if material ceases to be linearly elastic at yield stress fy, the width-to-thickness ratio b/t is given by (b/t)√(fy /250) = 53.8\nii) For long plate elements simply supported along both transverse edges and one longitudinal edge and free along other longitudinal edge, elastic buckling stress is equal to yield stress if (b/t)√(fy/250) = 17.5\niii) The elastic buckling stress is equal to yield stress in shear τy = fy/√3 when (d/t)√(fy/250) = 81.9\niv) For long plates elements simply supported along four edges and loaded by bending stress distribution, limiting ratio d/t may be given as (d/t)√(fy/250) = 131.4."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor is considered for classification of cross section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) location where member is used",
            "b) width-to-thickness ratio",
            "c) length of member",
            "d) seismic force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cross section are classified into four behavioural groups depending upon  the material yield strength, width-to-thickness ratio of individual components (e.g. webs and flanges) within the cross section, and the loading arrangement."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "What is a plastic section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cross section which can develop plastic moment",
            "b) cross section which can resist seismic force",
            "c) cross section in which buckling can occur",
            "d) cross section which can develop plastic hinges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plastic or class I sections are cross sections which can develop plastic hinges and have a rotation capacity required for failure of structure by formation of plastic mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "What is a compact section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cross section which can develop plastic moment resistance",
            "b) cross section which can resist seismic force",
            "c) cross section in which buckling can occur",
            "d) cross section which can develop plastic hinges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compact or class II sections are cross sections which can develop plastic moment resistance, but have inadequate plastic hinge rotation capacity because of local buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "What is a semi-compact section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cross section which can develop plastic moment resistance",
            "b) cross section which can resist seismic force",
            "c) cross section in which elastically calculated stress in extreme compression fibre can reach yield strength",
            "d) cross section which can develop plastic hinges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Semi-compact or class III sections are cross sections in which elastically calculated stress in extreme compression fibre of steel can reach yield strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "What is a slender section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cross section which can develop plastic moment resistance",
            "b) cross section which can resist seismic force",
            "c) cross section in which elastically calculated stress in extreme compression fibre can reach yield strength",
            "d) cross section in which local buckling will occur before yield stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Slender or class IV sections are cross section in which local buckling occurs even before the yield stress is attained in one or more parts of the cross section."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct regarding class I section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are not fully effective under pure compression",
            "b) They are capable of reaching and maintaining full plastic moment in bending",
            "c) They are not capable of reaching and maintaining full plastic moment in bending",
            "d) They does not exhibit sufficient ductility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Class I sections are fully effective under pure compression, and capable of reaching and maintaining full plastic moment in bending and hence used in plastic design. These sections will exhibit sufficient ductility."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "7. Match the following design moment capacity with the classes of cross section<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">                    Cross section\t\t\tDesign moment capacity\n                       i) Compact\t\t\tA) Md = Zpfy\n                      ii) Semi-Compact\t\t\tB) Md &lt; Zefy\n                     iii) Plastic\t\t\tC) Md = Zefy\n                     iv) Slender</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) i – B, ii – C, iii – A, iv – B",
            "b) i – A, ii – B, iii – C, iv – B",
            "c) i – A, ii – C, iii – A, iv – B",
            "d) i – C, ii – C, iii – A, iv – B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The design moment capacity Md of each of the four classes of cross sectioncan be calculated as i) Plastic – Md = Zpfy, ii) Compact – Md = Zpfy, iii) Semi-Compact – Md = Zefy, iv) Slender – Md < Zefy, where Zp = plastic modulus, Ze = elastic modulus."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal elements are elements attached along both longitudinal edges to other elements",
            "b) Outstanding elements are elements attached along both longitudinal edges to other elements",
            "c) Outstanding elements are elements which are free along both the edges",
            "d) Internal elements are elements which are free along both the edges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Internal elements are elements attached along both longitudinal edges to other elements or to longitudinal stiffeners connected at suitable intervals to transverse stiffeners connected at suitable intervals to  transverse stiffeners (e.g. web of I-sections and flange and web of box sections). Outstanding elements are attached along only one of the longitudinal edges to an adjacent element, the other edge being free to displace out of plan (e.g. flange overhang of an I-section, stem of T-section, leg of angle section)."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "What is the fundamental path in graph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) line along load axis up to P > Pcr",
            "b) line along load axis up to P < Pcr",
            "c) line along load axis up to P = Pcr",
            "d) line along load axis up to P ≥ Pcr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If axial load verses lateral displacement is plotted, we get a line along the load axis up to P=Pcr, this is called fundamental path."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about secondary path?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lateral displacement increases indefinitely at constant load",
            "b) lateral displacement decreases indefinitely at constant load",
            "c) lateral displacement remains same at constant load",
            "d) lateral displacement increases indefinitely and decreases at constant load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the axial load reaches the Euler bucking load, the lateral displacement increases indefinitely at constant load. This is called secondary path, which bifurcates from fundamental path at the buckling load. "
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plate cannot carry loads higher than elastic critical load",
            "b) plate cannot carry loads lesser than elastic critical load",
            "c) secondary path for a plate is unstable",
            "d) secondary path for a plate is stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The secondary path shows that plate can carry loads higher than elastic critical load. The secondary path for a plate is stable."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "What is apparent modulus of elasticity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ratio of average strain carried by plate to average stress",
            "b) ratio of average stress carried by plate to average strain",
            "c) product of average strain carried by plate to average stress",
            "d) product of average stress carried by plate to average strain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Elastic post-buckling stiffness is measured in terms of apparent modulus of elasticity, E*. It is the ratio of average stress carried by plate to average strain. In most of the cases, the value of E* is in the range 0.408 – 0.5 E and may be approximately taken as 0.5E. "
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "The effective width of hot-rolled and welded plates is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) be/b = α √(fy/fcr)",
            "b) be/b = α √(fcr x fy)",
            "c) be/b = α √(fcr +fy)",
            "d) be/b = α √(fcr/fy)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The effective width of hot-rolled and welded plates is given by be/b = α √(fcr/fy), where α is the parameter that indicates the inclusions of influence of initial curvatures and residual stress. Generally α=0.65."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "The effective width of cold-formed steel sections is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) be/b = (fcr/fy)[1-0.22√(fcr/fy)].",
            "b) be/b = (fcr/fy)[1+0.22√(fcr/fy)].",
            "c) be/b = (fy/fcr)[1-0.22√(fcr/fy)].",
            "d) be/b = (fcr/fy)[1+0.22√(fy/fcr)]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effective width based on tests on cold-formed steel sections is given by be/b = (fcr/fy)[1-0.22√(fcr/fy)]. This formula was first adopted in AISC specification for light gauge cold-formed sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about local buckling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) failure occurs by twisting of one or more individual elements of member",
            "b) failure occurs by buckling of one or more individual elements of member",
            "c) failure occurs by both buckling and twisting of one or more individual elements of member",
            "d) cannot be prevented by selecting suitable width-to-thickness ratio of elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Local buckling is failure which occurs by buckling of one or more individual elements of member. It can be prevented by selecting suitable width-to-thickness ratio of elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "What is squash load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) yield stress + area of cross section",
            "b) yield stress – area of cross section",
            "c) yield stress / area of cross section",
            "d) yield stress x area of cross section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When length of column is relatively small and its component elements are prevented from local buckling, then column will be able to attain its full strength or squash load (squash load = yield stress x area of cross section)."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "What is overall flexural buckling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) failure occurs by excessive deflection in plane of weaker principal axis",
            "b) failure occurs by excessive deflection in plane of stronger principal axis",
            "c) failure occurs by twisting of member",
            "d) failure caused by seismic load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Overall flexural buckling is failure which occurs by excessive deflection caused by bending or flexure, about axis corresponding to weaker principal axis(minor) – one with smallest radius of gyration, largest slenderness ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about torsional buckling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) failure occurs by bending about shear centre in longitudinal axis",
            "b) failure occurs when torsional rigidity of member is greater than bending rigidity",
            "c) standard hot rolled shapes are not susceptible to torsional buckling",
            "d) it cannot occur with doubly symmetric cross section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In torsional buckling, failure occurs by twisting about shear centre in longitudinal axis. It occurs when torsional rigidity of member is appreciably smaller than bending rigidity. It can occur only with doubly symmetric cross section with very slender cross sectional elements. Standard hot rolled shapes are not susceptible to torsional buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a solution for torsional buckling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) increasing length of members subjected to torsion",
            "b) by careful arrangement of members",
            "c) by providing bracing to prevent lateral movement and twisting",
            "d) box section fabricated by adding welding side plates to ISHB sections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Torsional buckling can be prevented by careful arrangement of members, by providing bracing to prevent lateral movement and twisting. In situations where torsion is expected either a box section fabricated by adding welding side plates to ISHB sections or by shortening box section fabricated by adding welding side plates to ISHB sections becomes the solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Flexural torsional buckling cannot occur in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) unsymmetrical members",
            "b) cross section with one axis of symmetry",
            "c) cross section with no axis of symmetry",
            "d) doubly symmetric members"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flexural torsional buckling is a combination of flexural and torsion buckling. The member bends and twists simultaneously. It can occur only with open sections that have unsymmetrical cross section – both with one axis of symmetry(eg: channels, double angled shapes) and those with no axis of symmetry (eg: unequal leg single angles). Since the shear centre and centroid coincide with each other, doubly symmetric or point symmetric open sections are not subjected to flexural torsional buckling. Close sections are also immune to flexural torsional buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": " What is compression member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) structural member subjected to tensile force",
            "b) structural member subjected to compressive force",
            "c) structural member subjected to bending moment",
            "d) structural member subjected to torsion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Structural member which is subjected to compressive forces along its axis is called compression member. Compression members are subjected to loads that tend to decrease their lengths."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about axially loaded column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) member subjected to bending moment",
            "b) member subjected to axial force and bending moment",
            "c) net end moments are not zero",
            "d) net end moments are zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: if the net end moments are zero, the compression member is required to resist load acting concentric to original longitudinal axis of member and is called axially loaded column or simply column."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about beam column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) member subjected to bending moment",
            "b) member subjected to axial force only",
            "c) member subjected to axial force and bending moment",
            "d) net end moments are zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the net end moments are not zero, the member will be subjected to axial force and bending moments along its length. Such members are called beam-columns."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "What are columns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical compression members in a building supporting floors or girders",
            "b) vertical tension members in a building supporting floors or girders",
            "c) horizontal compression members in a building supporting floors or girders",
            "d) horizontal tension members in a building supporting floors or girders"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vertical compression members in a building supporting floors or girders are normally called as columns. They are sometimes called as stanchions. They are subjected to heavy loads. Vertical compression members are sometimes called posts."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Which of the following are true about roof trusses?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  principal rafter are compression members used in buildings",
            "b) principal rafter is bottom chord member of roof truss",
            "c) struts are compression members used in roof trusses",
            "d) struts are tension members used in roof trusses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The compression members used in roof trusses and bracings are called as struts. They may be vertical or inclined and normally have small lengths. the top chord members of a roof truss are called principal rafter."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Knee braces are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) long compression members",
            "b) short compression members",
            "c) long tension members",
            "d) short tension members"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Short compression members at junction of columns and roof trusses or beams are called knee braces. They are provided to avoid moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a load on columns in buildings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) load from floors",
            "b) load from foundation",
            "c) load from roofs",
            "d) load from walls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Axial loading on columns in buildings is due to loads from roofs, floors, and walls transmitted to the column through beams and also due to its  own self weight."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) moment due to wind loads is not considered in unbraced buildings",
            "b) wind load cause large moments in braced buildings",
            "c) wind loads in multi-storey buildings are not usually applied at respective floor levels",
            "d) wind loads in multi-storey buildings are usually applied at respective floor levels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Wind loads in multi-storey buildings are usually applied at respective floor levels and are assumed to be resisted by bracings. Hence in braced buildings wind loads do not cause large moments. But, in unbraced rigid framed  buildings, the moment due to wind loads should also be taken into account in the design of columns."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "What are loads on columns in industrial buildings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) wind load only",
            "b) crane load only",
            "c) wind and crane load",
            "d) load from foundation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In industrial buildings, loads from crane and wind cause moments in columns. In such cases, wind load is applied to the column through sheeting rails and may be taken as uniformly distributed throughout the length of column."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "The strength of column does not depend on",
        "Options": [
            "a) width of building",
            "b) material of column",
            "c) cross sectional configuration",
            "d) length of column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The strength of column depends on material of column, cross sectional configuration, length of column, support conditions at the ends, residual stresses, imperfections."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an imperfection in column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) material not being isotropic",
            "b) geometric variations of columns",
            "c) material being homogenous",
            "d) eccentricity of load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Imperfections in column include material not being isotropic and homogenous, geometric variations of columns and eccentricity of load."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "For very short compression member",
        "Options": [
            "a) failure stress will be greater than yield stress",
            "b) failure stress will be less than yield stress",
            "c) failure stress will equal yield stress",
            "d) failure stress will be  twice the yield stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For very short compression members, the failure stress will the equal yield stress and no buckling will occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The length of member should be _________ for a short column",
        "Options": [
            "a) L ≤ 88.5r",
            "b) L ≥ 88.5r",
            "c) L ≥ 125r",
            "d) L > 150r"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a member to be classified as short column, length of member should be L ≤ 88.5r , where r is radius of gyration. The slenderness ratio of column defines the column as short or long column."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Long compression members will ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) not buckle",
            "b) buckle inelastically",
            "c) buckle plastically",
            "d) buckle elastically"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Long compression members will buckle elastically where axial buckling stress remains below proportional limit."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about intermediate length compression members?",
        "Options": [
            "a) members will fail by yielding only",
            "b) members will fail by both yielding and buckling",
            "c) their behaviour is elastic",
            "d) all fibres of the members will be elastic during failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For intermediate length compression members, some fibres would have yielded and some fibres will still be elastic. They will fail by both yielding and buckling and their behaviour is said to be inelastic."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "What is squash load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) load at which member will not deform axially",
            "b) load at which member deforms laterally",
            "c) load at which member deforms axially",
            "d) load at which member will not deform axially"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Large deformation is possible only when fc reached the yield stress. At this stage the member deforms axially. The value of axial force at which this deformation occurs is called squash load."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a parameter for decrease in strength of slender  member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) seismic load",
            "b) initial lack of straightness",
            "c) residual stress",
            "d) variation of material properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The decrease in strength of slender  member is due to following parameter : imperfections- initial lack of straightness, accidental eccentricities of loading, residual stress, and variation of material properties over the cross section."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Which of the following is property of compression member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) member must be sufficiently rigid to prevent general buckling",
            "b) member must not be sufficiently rigid to prevent local buckling",
            "c) elements of member should be thin to prevent local buckling",
            "d) elements of member need not prevent local buckling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Member must be sufficiently rigid to prevent general buckling in any possible direction, and each element of member must be thick enough to prevent local buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "How can moment of inertia be increased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) by increasing load",
            "b) by spreading material of section towards its axis",
            "c) by spreading material of section away from its axis",
            "d) by spreading material of section at its axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most important property of section in compression member is radius of gyration and thus moment of inertia. it can be increased by spreading material of section away from its axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Which is an ideal section for compression member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) one having different moment of inertia about any axis through its centre of gravity",
            "b) one having same moment of inertia about any axis through its centre of gravity",
            "c) one having larger length",
            "d) one made up of costly material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ideal section is the one which has same moment of inertia about any axis through its centre of gravity."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Rods and bars are recommended when length is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than 4m",
            "b) greater than 5m",
            "c) greater than 3m",
            "d) less than 3m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rods and bars withstand very little compression when length is more. Hence these are recommended for lengths less than 3m only."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about tubular section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tubes have low buckling strength",
            "b) tubes have same radius of gyration in all direction",
            "c) tubes do not have torsional resistance",
            "d) weight of tubular section is more than the weight required for open profile sections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tubes have same radius of gyration in all direction. They have high buckling strength and have excellent torsional resistance. Weight of tubular section is less than one half the weight required for open profile sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) unequal angles are desirable over equal angles",
            "b) least radius of gyration of equal angle is less than that of unequal angle for same area of steel",
            "c) single angle sections are suitable for long lengths",
            "d) least radius of gyration of single angle section is small compared to channel and I-sections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Equal angle are desirable and economical over unequal angles because least radius of gyration of equal angle is greater than that of unequal angle for same area of steel. Single angle sections are not suitable for long lengths. Least radius of gyration of single angle section is small compared to channel and I-sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Effective length of compression member is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) distance between ends of members",
            "b) distance between end point and midpoint of member",
            "c) distance between points of contraflexure",
            "d) distance between end point and centroid of member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Effective length of compression member is distance between points of contraflexure. It should be derived from actual length and end conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Magnitude of effective length depends upon",
        "Options": [
            "a) material of member",
            "b) rotational restraint supplied at end of compression member",
            "c) load applied on member",
            "d) location where member is used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnitude of effective length depends upon rotational restraint supplied at end of compression member and upon resistance to lateral movement provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater the effective length, greater the load carrying capacity",
            "b) smaller the effective length, smaller the load carrying capacity",
            "c) smaller the effective length, more the danger of lateral buckling",
            "d) smaller the effective length, smaller the danger of lateral buckling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Smaller the effective length of particular compression member, smaller is  the danger of lateral buckling and greater is the load carrying capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "What is the effective length when both ends of compression member are fixed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65L",
            "b) 0.8L",
            "c)  L",
            "d) 2L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effective length of compression member when both ends of compression member are fixed is 0.65L (i.e. L/√2), where L is the length of the member."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "What is the effective length when both ends of compression member are hinged?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65L",
            "b) 0.8L",
            "c) L",
            "d) 2L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The effective length of compression member when both ends of compression member are hinged is L, where L is the length of the member."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "What is the effective length when one end of compression member is fixed and other end is free?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65L",
            "b) 0.8L",
            "c) L",
            "d) 2L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The effective length of compression member when one end is fixed and other end is free is 2L, where L is the length of the member."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "What is the effective length when one end of compression member is fixed and other end is hinged?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65L",
            "b) 0.8L",
            "c) L",
            "d) 2L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The effective length of compression member when one end is fixed and other end is hinged is 0.8L, where L is the length of the member."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "What is slenderness ratio of compression member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ratio of effective length to radius of gyration",
            "b) ratio of radius of gyration to effective length",
            "c) difference of radius of gyration and effective length",
            "d) product of radius of gyration and effective length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tendency of member to buckle is usually measured by its slenderness ratio. Slenderness ratio of member is ratio of effective length to appropriate radius of gyration (λ = kL/r). This is valid only when column has equal unbraced heights for both axes and end condition is same for particular section."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Maximum radius of gyration (minimum slenderness ratio) can be obtained by",
        "Options": [
            "a) by increasing load",
            "b) by spreading material of section towards its axis",
            "c) by spreading material of section away from its axis",
            "d) by spreading material of section at its axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Maximum radius of gyration is obtained when material of section is farthest from centroid i.e. away from its axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the attribute of ideal column according to Euler?",
        "Options": [
            "a) material is non homogenous",
            "b) material is isotropic",
            "c) load does not act along centroidal axis",
            "d) column ends are fixed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Euler, the following are the attributes of ideal column: (i) Material is  isotropic, homogenous and is assumed to be perfectly elastic, (ii) column is initially straight and load acts along centroidal axis (no eccetricity of loads), (iii) column has no imperfections, (iv) column ends are hinged."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Euler critical load for column with both the ends hinged is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pcr = 2π2EI/L2",
            "b) Pcr= π2EIL2",
            "c) Pcr = 2π2EIL2",
            "d) Pcr = π2EI/L2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Euler critical load for column with both the ends hinged is given by Pcr= π2EI/L2, where E is elastic modulus of material, I is moment of inertia and L is length of column."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) increasing member length causes reduction in stiffness",
            "b) decreasing member length causes reduction in stiffness",
            "c) member with high stiffness will buckle early than that with low stiffness",
            "d) stiffness of member is not influenced by amount and distribution of material in cross section of column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Member with low stiffness will buckle early than that the one with high stiffness. Increasing member length causes reduction in stiffness. Stiffness of member is influenced by amount and distribution of material in cross section of column, the value of radius of gyration reflects the way in which material is distributed."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Euler critical load for column with both the ends fixed is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pcr = 2π2EI/L2",
            "b) Pcr = π2EIL2",
            "c) Pcr = 4π2EI/L2",
            "d) Pcr= π2EI/L2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Euler critical load for column with both the ends hinged is given by Pcr = 4π2EI/L2, where E is elastic modulus of material, I is moment of inertia and L is length of column, effective length of column in this case = 2L."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "What is the relation between critical stress and slenderness ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) critical stress is directly proportional to  slenderness ratio",
            "b) critical stress is inversely proportional to  slenderness ratio",
            "c) critical stress is square of slenderness ratio",
            "d) critical stress is cube of slenderness ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: fcr  = Pcr/Ag = π2E/λ2, critical stress is inversely proportional to  slenderness ratio of column and very large values can be obtained by using L/r → 0 ."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Why is built up section used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) to sustain seismic loads only",
            "b) for aesthetic appearance",
            "c) used when rolled section do not furnish required sectional area",
            "d) for resisting bending moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Size and shape of rolled sections are limited because of limitation of rolling mills. When rolled section do not furnish required sectional area or when special shape or large radius of gyration is required in two different direction, a built up section is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "The shear in column may not be due to",
        "Options": [
            "a) material used in column",
            "b) lateral loads from wind",
            "c) lateral loads from earthquake",
            "d) end eccentricity of load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shear in column may be due to (i) lateral loads from wind, earthquake, gravity or other loads, (ii)slope of column with respect to line of thrust due to both unintentional and initial curvature and increased curvature during bending, (iii)end of eccentricity of load due to either end connection or fabrication imperfections."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) function of lacing and battens is to hold main component members",
            "b) tie plates are provided at top and bottom of column",
            "c) lacing bars and batten plates are not designed as load carrying elements",
            "d) lacing bars and batten plates are designed as load carrying elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lacing bars and batten plates are not designed as load carrying elements. Their function is to hold main component members of built up column in relative position and equalize stress distribution in them. At ends and at intermediate points where it is necessary to interrupt the lacings, open sides are connected with tie plates. Tie plates are also provided at top and bottom of column."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) built up column lacings or battens are uneconomical if load carrying members permit greater reduction in weight than what is added by lacing or batten",
            "b) built up column lacings or battens are economical if load carrying members permit greater reduction in weight than what is added by lacing or batten",
            "c) no related shear stress force in plane of cross section",
            "d) built up column designed as axially loaded column can never be eccentrically loaded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Built up column lacings or battens are economical if load carrying members permit greater reduction in weight than what is added by lacing or batten. Built up column designed as axially loaded column may be accidentally loaded eccentrically or may have initial crookedness. Variable bending moment will be induced in such column because of eccentricity between centroidal axis of column and line of action of applied load due to this, there will be related shear stress force in plane of cross section and in connecting system."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The buckling strength of latticed column is ___________ that of solid column having ame area and same slenderness ratio",
        "Options": [
            "a) smaller than",
            "b) greater than",
            "c) equal to",
            "d) cannot be compared"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The buckling strength of latticed column is smaller than that of solid column having same area and same slenderness ratio provided that solid column does not buckle locally because of thinness of material. This is because shear component of axial load produces deformation in lattice which tends to reduce overall stiffness of column and therefore reduce buckling strength of column."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is not considered in design of built up column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) buckling of column as whole",
            "b) failure of lattice member",
            "c) material to be used for fabrication",
            "d) buckling of component column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In design of built up column, following conditions are considered : (i) buckling of column as whole under axial load, (ii) buckling of component column, (iii) failure of lattice member, (iv) distortion of cross section."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The radius of gyration of combined column about axis perpendicular to plane of lacing should be _____ than about axis parallel to plane of lacing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cannot be compared",
            "b) smaller",
            "c) greater",
            "d) equal to"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The radius of gyration of combined column about axis perpendicular to plane of lacing should be greater than about axis parallel to plane of lacing."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lacings and battens should not be provided on opposite sides of same member",
            "b) lacing system should not be uniform throughout length of column",
            "c) single and double laced systems should be provided on opposite sides of same member",
            "d) single laced system on opposite of main component shall be in opposite direction view from either side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lacing system should be uniform throughout length of column. Single and double laced systems should not be provided on opposite sides of same member. Lacings and battens should not be provided on opposite sides of same member. Single laced system can be in same direction view from either side on opposite of main component so that one is shadow of other."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Lacing shall be designed to resist a total transverse shear equal to ____ of axial force in member",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5%",
            "b) 1%",
            "c) 4.3%",
            "d) 2.5%"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: Lacing can be designed to resist a total transverse shear at any point in the member equal to 2.5% of axial force in member. This shear shall be divided among lacing systems in parallel planes. Lacings should also be designed to resist any shear due to bending moment or lateral load on member."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Slenderness ratio of lacing is limited to",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200",
            "b) 145",
            "c) 500",
            "d) 380"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Slenderness ratio is the ratio of effective length by radius of gyration. Slenderness ratio of lacing shall not exceed 145."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about effective length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) effective length shall be taken as length between inner end bolts/rivets of bars for single lacings",
            "b) effective length shall be taken as length between inner end bolts/rivets of bars for double lacings",
            "c) for welded bars, effective length shall be taken as 0.9 times distance between  inner end welds connecting single bars to members",
            "d) effective length shall be taken as 1.5 times length between inner end bolts/rivets of bars for double lacings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Effective length shall be taken as length between inner end bolts/rivets of bars for single lacings and 0.7 times length between inner end bolts/rivets of bars for double lacings. For welded bars, effective length shall be taken as 0.7 times distance between  inner end welds connecting single bars to members."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Minimum width of lacing bars shall _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) be less than 3 times diameter of connecting bolt/rivet",
            "b) be less than 5 times diameter of connecting bolt/rivet",
            "c) not be less than 3 times diameter of connecting bolt/rivet",
            "d) be less than 2 times diameter of connecting bolt/rivet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Minimum width of lacing bars shall not be less than approximately 3 times the diameter of connecting bolt/rivet."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Thickness of lacing member should be",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than 1/40th of the effective length for single lacing",
            "b) not less than 1/60th of the effective length for double lacing",
            "c) less than 1/60thof the effective length for double lacing",
            "d) less than 1/60th of the effective length for single lacing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thickness of lacing member should not be less than 1/40th of the effective length for single lacing and not less than 1/60th of the effective length for double lacing."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition should be satisfied for spacing of lacings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum slenderness ratio of component of main members between two consecutive lacing connection should be greater than 50",
            "b) maximum slenderness ratio of component of main members between two consecutive lacing connection should be not greater than 50",
            "c) maximum slenderness ratio of component of main members between two consecutive lacing connection should be more than 0.7 x most unfavourable slenderness ratio of combined column",
            "d) maximum slenderness ratio of component of main members between two consecutive lacing connection should not be more than 0.9 x most unfavourable slenderness ratio of combined column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The spacing of lacing bars should be such that maximum slenderness ratio of component of main members between two consecutive lacing connection is not greater than 50. It should not be greater than 0.7 times most unfavourable slenderness ratio of combined column."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) when welded lacing bars overlap main members, amount of lap should not be less than 4 times thickness of bar",
            "b) welding is to be provided along each side of bar for full length of lap",
            "c) lacing bars fitted between main members should be connected by fillet welds on each side",
            "d) when lacing bars are not lapped to form connection to components of members, appreciable interruption in triangulated system is allowed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When welded lacing bars overlap main members, amount of lap should not be less than 4 times thickness of bar. Welding is to be provided along each side of bar for full length of lap. Lacing bars fitted between main members should be connected by full penetration butt weld  or fillet welds on each side. Lacing bars shall be connected such that there is no appreciable interruption in triangulated system when lacing bars are not lapped to form connection to components of members."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "lacing bars shall be inclined at an angle of ___ to axis of built up member.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20o",
            "b) 35o",
            "c) 50o",
            "d) 90o"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lacing bars shall be inclined at an angle of 40o to 70o to axis of built up member."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Effective slenderness ratio of laced column shall be _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) equal to the maximum slenderness ratio of column",
            "b) 1.05 times the maximum slenderness ratio of column",
            "c) 0.5 times the maximum slenderness ratio of column",
            "d) 2 times the maximum slenderness ratio of column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Effective slenderness ratio of laced column shall be taken as 5% more than the maximum slenderness ratio of column i.e. 1.05 times the maximum slenderness ratio of column, to account for shear deformation effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Compressive strength in lacing bars in single lacing system is equal to",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vt /(N secΘ)",
            "b) Vt /(N cosecΘ)",
            "c) Vt N cosecΘ",
            "d) (Vt /N) cosecΘ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Compressive strength in lacing bars is equal to (Vt /N) cosecΘ for single lacing system and (Vt/2N) cosecΘ for double lacing system, where N = number of shear resisting elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Minimum radius of gyration for lacing flats is",
        "Options": [
            "a) t/√12",
            "b) t/12",
            "c) t/√24",
            "d) t/24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Minimum radius of gyration for lacing flats is t/√12 , where t is thickness of flat."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "The load on rivet/bolt when two lacing flats are connected at same point is",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Vt / N) cotΘ",
            "b) 2(Vt / N) cotΘ",
            "c) 2Vt N cotΘ",
            "d) Vt NcotΘ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Strength of bolt /rivet should be greater than load coming over rivet/bolt. The load on rivet/bolt when two lacing flats are connected at same point is 2(Vt/N)cotΘ."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "The load on rivet/bolt when two lacing flats are connected at different point is",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Vt / N) cotΘ",
            "b) 2(Vt / N) cotΘ",
            "c) 2Vt N cotΘ",
            "d) Vt NcotΘ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Strength of bolt /rivet should be greater than load coming over rivet/bolt. The load on rivet/bolt when two lacing flats are connected at different point is (Vt/ N) cotΘ."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of battens in a column should be such that member is divided into not less than three bays",
            "b) Number of battens in a column should be such that member is divided into less than three bays",
            "c) Number of battens in a column should be such that member is divided into less than two bays",
            "d) No restriction on number of battens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Battens are plates or any other rolled section used to connect the main components of compression members. Battens should be placed opposite to each other on the two parallel faces of compression members.  Number of battens in a column should be such that member is divided into not less than three bays."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Battens should be designed to resist transverse shear force which is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5% of axial force",
            "b) 0.5% of axial force",
            "c) 2.5% of axial force",
            "d) 7.2% of axial force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Battens should be designed to resist transverse shear force which is 2.5% of total axial force on whole compression member. This transverse shear force is divided equally in all parallel planes in which, there is shear resisting elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Battens should be designed to resist longitudinal shear equal to",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vt L0 ns",
            "b) Vt L0 / ns",
            "c) Vt /L0 ns",
            "d) Vt L0n/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Battens should be designed to resist longitudinal shear equal to V = Vt L0 / ns , where Vt is transverse shear force, L0 is distance between centre-to-centre of battens longitudinally, s is minimum transverse distance between centroids of bolt/rivet group/ welding connecting batten to main member, n is number of parallel planes of battens."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Battens should be designed to resist moment equal to",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vt L0 n",
            "b) Vt L0 / n",
            "c) Vt /L0 n",
            "d) Vt L0 /2n"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Battens should be designed to resist moment equal to Vt L0/2n , where Vt = transverse shear force, L0 = distance between centre-to-centre of battens longitudinally, n = number of parallel planes of battens."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about effective depth of battens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than perpendicular distance between centroids for end battens",
            "b) less than three quarters of the perpendicular distance between centroids for intermediate battens",
            "c) not less than twice the width of one member in plane of batten",
            "d) less than twice the width of one member in plane of batten"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When plates are used for battens, effective depth between end bolts/rivets or welds should not be less than twice the width of one member in plane of batten, not less than perpendicular distance between centroids for end battens and not less than three quarters of the perpendicular distance between centroids for intermediate battens."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Thickness of batten plates shall be",
        "Options": [
            "a) not less than 1/50th of distance between innermost connecting transverse bolts/rivets",
            "b) less than 1/50th of distance between innermost connecting transverse bolts/rivets",
            "c) less than 1/60th of distance between innermost connecting transverse bolts/rivets",
            "d) less than 1/80th of distance between innermost connecting transverse bolts/rivets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thickness of batten plates shall be not less than 1/50th of distance between innermost connecting transverse bolts/rivets or welds perpendicular to main member i.e. t > (1/50)(s + 2g), where g is gauge distance for particular section."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) length of weld connecting each end of batten should be less than one fourth the depth of plate",
            "b) length of weld and depth of batten shall be measured perpendicular to longitudinal axis of member",
            "c) weld shall be returned only along other two edges for length less than minimum lap",
            "d) length of weld connecting each end of batten should be such that at least one third of its length should be placed on each end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Length of weld connecting each end of batten shall be more than half the depth of plate. Length of weld connecting each end of batten should be such that at least one third of its length should be placed on each end. Weld shall be returned only along other two edges for length less than minimum lap. Length of weld and depth of batten shall be measured along  longitudinal axis of main member. "
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Effective slenderness ratio of battened column shall be ____ of actual slenderness ratio of column",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 times",
            "b) 1.1 times",
            "c) 2 times",
            "d) 2.5 times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Effective slenderness ratio of battened column shall be 1.1 times the maximum actual slenderness ratio of column to account for shear deformation effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Maximum spacing of batten should be such that slenderness ratio of component member should be",
        "Options": [
            "a) not greater than 50",
            "b) greater than 50",
            "c) greater than 0.7 times slenderness ratio of member as a whole",
            "d) greater than slenderness ratio of member as a whole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum spacing of batten should be such that slenderness ratio of component member should be not greater than 50 or 0.7 times slenderness ratio of member as a whole, about axis parallel to end of battens."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about effective depth of end batten?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it should be less than distance between centre of gravity of component",
            "b) it should be half the distance between centre of gravity of component",
            "c) it should be less than twice the width of component member",
            "d) it should be greater than twice the width of component member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Effective depth of end batten should not be less than distance between centre of gravity of component and should be greater than twice the width of component member."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Depth of intermediate batten = _______ depth of end batten",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/2",
            "b) 3/4",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Depth of intermediate batten is taken as three fourth of the effective depth of end batten and should be more than twice the width of component member."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Thickness of batten should not be less than",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/40th of distance between innermost connecting lines of bolts",
            "b) 1/50th of distance between innermost connecting lines of bolts",
            "c) 1/100th of distance between innermost connecting lines of bolts",
            "d) 1/10th of distance between innermost connecting lines of bolts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thickness of batten should not be less than 1/50th of distance between innermost connecting lines of rivets/bolts/welds perpendicular to main member."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "A laced column is_____ than battened column for same load",
        "Options": [
            "a) equally strong",
            "b) weaker",
            "c) stronger",
            "d) cannot be compared"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A laced column is stronger than battened column for same load, unsupported length and end conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "The slenderness ratio of each member when placed back-to-back or separated by small distance shall be",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than 40",
            "b) not greater than 40",
            "c) 0.8 times the slenderness ratio of column as a whole",
            "d) greater than 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Two rolled sections placed back-to-back or separated by small distance should be connected together by rivets/bolts/welds so that slenderness ratio of each member when placed back-to-back or separated by small distance is not greater than 40 or 0.6 times the slenderness ratio of column as a whole.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Minimum number of bolts for connecting end of strut is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ends of strut should be connected with minimum of 2 bolts/rivets or equivalent length of weld length (length must not be less than maximum width of member)."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) when there is small spacing between the two sections placed  back-to-back, washers and packing should be provided",
            "b) when there is small spacing between the two sections placed  back-to-back, washers and packing should not be provided",
            "c) there should be additional connection in between along the length of member",
            "d) when leg of angles greater than 125mm wide or web of channel is mm wide, minimum  bolt is sufficient for connection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There should be minimum of two additional connection in between, spaced equidistant along the length of member. When there is small spacing between the two sections placed  back-to-back, washers(in case of bolts) and packing(in case of welding) should be provided to make connection. When leg of angles greater than 125mm wide or web of channel is mm wide, minimum two bolts/rivets should be for connection. "
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Minimum diameter of bolt when member is less than 16mm thick is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 22",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rivets/bolts should not be less than 16mm in diameter for member less than 10mm thick, 20mm in diameter for member less than 16mm thick and 22mm in diameter for member more than 16mm thick."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) spacing of tack bolt should be less than 600mm",
            "b) spacing of tack bolt should be greater than 600mm",
            "c) if bolts are used, they should be spaced longitudinally at less than 4 times the bolt diameter",
            "d) connection should extend at least 1.5 times the width of the member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spacing of tack bolt should be less than 600mm. If bolts are used, they should be spaced longitudinally at less than 4 times the bolt diameter. Connection should extend at least 1.5 times the width of the member."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Members connected back-to-back connected by bolts should be",
        "Options": [
            "a) not be used",
            "b) subjected to transverse loading in plane perpendicular to bolted surface",
            "c) subjected to twice the transverse loading in plane perpendicular to bolted surface",
            "d)  not subjected to transverse loading in plane perpendicular to bolted surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Members connected back-to-back connected by bolts should not be subjected to transverse loading in plane perpendicular to riveted/bolted/welded surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "For members placed back-to-back, the spacing of bolt should not exceed",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12t",
            "b) 16t",
            "c) 18t",
            "d) 20t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For members placed back-to-back, the spacing of bolt should not exceed 12t or 200mm, where t is thickness of member."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Longitudinal spacing between intermittent welds used for connection should be",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than 18t",
            "b) greater than 16t",
            "c) not greater than 16t",
            "d) equal to 18t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Longitudinal spacing between intermittent welds used for connection should not be greater than 16t, where t is thickness of thinner connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "A column that can support same load in compression as it can in tension is called",
        "Options": [
            "a) intermediate column",
            "b) long column",
            "c) short column",
            "d) cannot be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A column that can support same load in compression as it can in tension is called short column. Short column usually fail by crushing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "The strength of compression members subjected to axial compression is defined by curves corresponding to _______ classes",
        "Options": [
            "a) a, b, c and d",
            "b) a, d",
            "c) b, e, f",
            "d) e, f, g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The strength of compression members subjected to axial compression is defined by curves corresponding to a, b, c and d classes. The value of imperfection factor depends on type of buckling curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a compression member?",
        "Options": [
            "a) strut",
            "b) boom",
            "c) tie",
            "d) rafter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Strut, boom and rafter are compression members, whereas tie is a tension member."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "The best compression member section generally used is",
        "Options": [
            "a) single angle section",
            "b) I-section",
            "c) double angle section",
            "d) channel section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally, ISHB sections are used as compression members."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "The best double-angle compression member section is",
        "Options": [
            "a) unequal angles with short leg connected",
            "b) unequal angles with long leg connected",
            "c) unequal angles on opposite side of gusset plate",
            "d) unequal angles on same side of gusset plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unequal angles with short leg connected are preferred as compression member section."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "The flange is classified as semi-compact if outstand element of compression flange of  rolled section is less than",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.4ε",
            "b) 10.5ε",
            "c) 15.7ε",
            "d) 9.4ε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The flange is classified as semi-compact if outstand element of compression flange of rolled section is less than 15.7ε and for a welded section, less than 13.6ε."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "The flange is classified as plastic if outstand element of compression flange of  rolled section is less than",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.4ε",
            "b) 9.4ε",
            "c) 10.5ε",
            "d) 15.7ε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flange is classified as plastic if outstand element of compression flange of rolled section is less than 9.4ε and for a welded section, less than 8.4ε."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "The outstand element of compression flange of a rolled section is 10.2 (ε=1). The flange will be classified as",
        "Options": [
            "a) compact",
            "b) plastic",
            "c) semi-compact",
            "d) slender"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flange is classified as compact if outstand element of compression flange of rolled section is less than 10.5ε and for a welded section, less than 9.4ε."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": " The design compressive stress of compression member in IS 800 is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rankine Formula",
            "b) Euler Formula",
            "c) Perry-Robertson formula",
            "d) Secant-Rankine formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The design compressive stress of axially loaded compression member in IS 800 is given by Perry-Robertson formula. IS 800:2007 proposes multiple columns curves in nin-dimensional form based on Perry-Robertson approach."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "The design compressive strength of member is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aefcd",
            "b) Ae /fcd",
            "c) fcd",
            "d) 0.5Aefcd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design compressive strength of member is given by Pd  = Aefcd, where Ae is effective sectional area, fcd is design compressive stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "The design compressive stress, fcd of column is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) [fy / γm0]/ [φ – (φ2-λ2)2].",
            "b) [fy / γm0] / [φ + (φ2-λ2)].",
            "c) [fy / γm0]/[φ – (φ2-λ2)0.5].",
            "d) [fy / γm0] / [φ + (φ2-λ2)0.5]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design compressive stress, fcd of column is given by fcd = [fy / γm0] / [φ + (φ2-λ2)0.5], where fy is yield stress of material, φ is dependent on imperfection factor, λ is non dimensional effective slenderness ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "What is the value of imperfection factor for buckling class a?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.34",
            "b) 0.75",
            "c) 0.21",
            "d) 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of imperfection factor, α for buckling class a is 0.21. The imperfection factor considers all the relevant defects in real structure when considering buckling, geometric imperfections, eccentricity of applied loads and residual stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "If imperfection factor α = 0.49, then what is the buckling class?",
        "Options": [
            "a) a",
            "b) c",
            "c) b",
            "d) g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For buckling class c, the value of imperfection factor is 0.49. The imperfection factor takes into account all the relevant defects in real structure when considering buckling, geometric imperfections, eccentricity of applied loads and residual stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "The value of φ in the equation of design compressive strength is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) φ = 0.5[1-α(λ-0.2)+λ2].",
            "b) φ = 0.5[1-α(λ-0.2)-+λ2].",
            "c) φ = 0.5[1+α(λ+0.2)-λ2].",
            "d) φ = 0.5[1+α(λ-0.2)+λ2]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of φ in the equation of design compressive strength is given by φ = 0.5[1+α(λ-0.2)+λ2], where α is imperfection factor(depends on buckling class) and λ is non-dimensional effective slenderness ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Euler buckling stress fcc is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) (π2E)/(KL/r)2",
            "b) (π2E KL/r)2",
            "c) (π2E)/(KL/r)",
            "d) (π2E)/(KLr)2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Euler buckling stress fcc is given by fcc = (π2E)/(KL/r)2, where E is modulus of elasticity of material and KL/r is effective slenderness ratio i.e. ratio of effective length, KL to appropriate radius of gyration, r."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "What is the value of non dimensional slenderness ratio λ in the equation of design compressive strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (fy /fcc)",
            "b) √(fy fcc)",
            "c) √(fy /fcc)",
            "d) (fy fcc)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of non dimensional slenderness ratio λ in the equation of design compressive strength is given by λ = √(fy /fcc) , where fy is yield stress of material and fcc = (π2E)/(KL/r)2, where E is modulus of elasticity of material and KL/r is effective slenderness ratio i.e. ratio of effective length."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "The design compressive strength in terms of stress reduction factor is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xfy",
            "b) Xfy / γm0",
            "c) X /fy γm0",
            "d) Xfy γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design compressive strength in terms of stress reduction factor is given by fcd = Xfy / γm0 , where X = stress reduction factor for different buckling class, slenderness ratio and yield stress = 1/ [φ + (φ2-λ2)0.5], fy is yield stress of material and γm0 is partial safety factor for material strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "The value of design compressive strength is limited to",
        "Options": [
            "a) fy + γm0",
            "b) fy",
            "c) fy  γm0",
            "d) fy / γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of design compressive strength is given by fcd = [fy / γm0] / [φ + (φ2-λ2)0.5] ≤ fy / γm0 i.e. fcd should be less than or equal to fy / γm0."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "The compressive strength for ISMB 400 used as a column for length 5m with both ends hinged is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 275 kN",
            "b) 375.4 kN",
            "c) 453 kN",
            "d) 382 kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: K = 1 for both ends hinged, KL = 1×5000 = 5000, r = 28.2mm (from steel table), Ae = 7846 mm2(from steel table)\nKL/r = 5000/28.2 = 177.3\nh/bf = 400/140 = 2.82, t = 16mm Therefore, buckling class = b\nFrom table in IS code, fcd = 47.85MPa\nPd = Ae fcd = 7846 x 47.85 = 375.43 kN."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "What is beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) structural member subjected to transverse loads",
            "b) structural member subjected to axial loads only",
            "c) structural member subjected to seismic loads only",
            "d) structural member subjected to transverse loads only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Beam is a structural member subjected to transverse loads that is loads perpendicular to its longitudinal axis. The mode of deflection of beam is primarily by bending."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Structural members subjected to bending and large axial compressive loads are known as",
        "Options": [
            "a) strut",
            "b) purlin",
            "c) beam-column",
            "d) lintel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Structural members subjected to bending accompanied by large axial compressive loads  at the same time are known as beam-column. A beam-column differs from column only by presence of eccentricity of load application, end moment, transverse load."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "What is girt?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vertical beam spanning between wall column of industrial buildings",
            "b) horizontal beam spanning between wall column of industrial buildings",
            "c) vertical beam spanning between wall column of residential buildings",
            "d) horizontal beam spanning between wall column of residential buildings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Girt is horizontal member fastened to and spanning between peripheral column of industrial buildings. It is used to support wall cladding such as corrugated metal sheet."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Members used to carry wall loads over wall openings are called",
        "Options": [
            "a) purlin",
            "b) rafter",
            "c) girder",
            "d) lintels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lintels are beam members used to carry wall loads over wall openings for doors, windows, etc.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Load transfer by a beam is primarily by",
        "Options": [
            "a) bending only",
            "b) shear only",
            "c) bending and shear",
            "d) neither bending nor shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The load transfer by beam is primarily by bending and shear. The mode of deflection of beam is primarily by bending."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "What are spandrels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) exterior beams at floor level of buildings",
            "b) interior beams at floor level of buildings",
            "c) exterior columns",
            "d) interior columns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spandrels are exterior beams at floor level of buildings, which carry part of floor load and exterior wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Members used in bridges parallel to traffic are called",
        "Options": [
            "a) spandrel",
            "b) stringers",
            "c) purlin",
            "d) joist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stringers are members used in bridges parallel to traffic to carry the deck slab. They will be connected by transverse floor beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "8. Match the pair<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\t     I \t\t\t        II\n\t(A) joist\t\t(i) tension member in roof truss\n\t(B) girder\t\t(ii) member supporting purlin\n\t(C) tie\t\t\t(iii) member supporting roof in a building\n\t(D) rafter\t\t(iv) major floor beam in building</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii, D-iv",
            "b) A-iv, B-iii, C-ii, D-i",
            "c) A-ii, B-iv, C-iii, D-i",
            "d) A-iii, B-iv, C-i, D-ii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Joist is a member supporting roof in a building. Girder is a major floor beam in building. Tie is tension member in roof truss and rafter is a member supporting purlin."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) beams are termed as fixed beams when end condition do not carry end moments",
            "b) beams are termed as simply supported beams when ends are rigidly connected to other members",
            "c) beams are termed as fixed beams when ends are rigidly connected to other members",
            "d) beams are termed as continuous beams when they do not extend across more than two support"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Beams may be termed as simply supported beams when end condition do not carry any end moments from any continuity developed by connection.  A beam is called continuous beam when it extends continuously across more than two supports. A fixed beam has its ends rigidly connected to other members, so that moments can be carried across the connection."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Complex stresses may occur when",
        "Options": [
            "a) loads are inclined to principal axes",
            "b) loads are along principal axes",
            "c) symmetrical section are used",
            "d) small values of shear and bending moment occur at section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Complex stresses may arise when loads are inclined to principal axes, when unsymmetrical sections are used or when large values of shear and bending moment occur at section."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Simple bending takes place if",
        "Options": [
            "a) loading passes above shear centre for single symmetric open section",
            "b) loading passes below shear centre for single symmetric open section",
            "c) loading plane coincides with one of the principal planes of doubly symmetric section",
            "d) loading plane do not coincide with one of the principal planes of doubly symmetric section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Simple bending takes place if loading plane coincides with one of the principal planes of doubly symmetric section such as I-section or in case of singly symmetric open section such as channel section, the loading passes through shear centre and is parallel to the principal plane. Unsymmetrical bending occurs if loading does not pass through shear centre."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of the following buckling does not occur in beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lateral buckling of whole beam",
            "b) local buckling of web",
            "c) local buckling of flanges",
            "d) longitudinal buckling of web"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Buckling may take place in many ways : (i) lateral buckling of whole beam between supports, (ii) local buckling of flanges, (iii) longitudinal buckling of web and buckling in depth direction under concentrated loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angles and T section are strong in bending",
            "b) Channels can be used only for light loads",
            "c) I sections are most efficient and economical shapes",
            "d) I section with cover plates are provided when large section modulus is required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A beam section is provided on the basis of (i) section modulus, (ii) deflection, (iii) shear. The beam should be economical with furnishing required modulus of section."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Local buckling can be prevented by",
        "Options": [
            "a) limiting width-thickness ratio",
            "b) increasing width-thickness ratio",
            "c) changing material",
            "d) changing load on member"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angles and T section are weak in bending. Channels can be used only for light loads. I sections (rolled and built-up) are most efficient and economical shapes. I section with cover plates are provided when large section modulus is required. Generally, ISLB or ISMB are provided in such cases."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) in case of rolled section, less thickness of plate is adopted to prevent local buckling",
            "b) for built-up section and cold formed section, longitudinal stiffeners are not provided to reduce width to smaller sizes",
            "c) local buckling cannot be prevented by limiting width-thickness ratio",
            "d) in case of rolled section, high thickness of plate is adopted to prevent local buckling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Local buckling of compression members of beam causes loss of integrity of beam cross section. It is a function of width-thickness ratio and can be prevented by limiting width-thickness ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) only plastic section can be used in intermediate frames",
            "b) slender sections are preferred in hot rolled structural steelwork",
            "c) compact sections can be used in simply supported beams",
            "d) semi-compact sections can be used for elastic designs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of rolled section, higher thickness of plate is adopted to prevent local buckling. Local buckling cannot be prevented by limiting width-thickness ratio. For built-up section and cold formed section, longitudinal stiffeners are provided to reduce width to smaller sizes."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "As per IS specification, the beam sections should be",
        "Options": [
            "a) not symmetrical about any principal axes",
            "b) at least symmetrical about one of the principal axes",
            "c) symmetrical about all principal axes",
            "d) unsymmetrical about all principal axes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only plastic section can be used in intermediate frames which form collapse mechanism. Compact sections can be used in simply supported beams which fail after reaching Mp at one section. Semi-compact sections can be used for elastic designs where section fails after reaching My at extreme fibres. Slender sections are not preferred in hot rolled structural steelwork, but they are extensively used in cold formed members."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) for optimum bending resistance, beam material should be near neutral axis",
            "b) for optimum bending resistance, beam material should be far away from neutral axis",
            "c) for optimum bending resistance, web area of beam has to be adequate for resisting shear",
            "d) maximum bending and maximum shear usually occur at different cross section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The beam sections should be at least symmetrical about one of the principal axes as per IS specification. Angle and T-sections are inherently weak in bending while channels can only be used for light loads. Rolled I0section is generally preferred as beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Which of the following assumptions is not an ideal beam behaviour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) local and lateral instabilities of beam are prevented",
            "b) any form of local buckling is prevented",
            "c) compression flange of beam is restrained from moving laterally",
            "d) compression flange of beam is not restrained from moving laterally"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Two important assumptions are made to achieve ideal beam behaviour: (i) compression flange of beam is restrained from moving laterally, (ii) any form of local buckling is prevented. A beam loaded predominantly in flexure would attain its full moment capacity if local and lateral instabilities of beam are prevented."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "In beam design, sections are proportioned as such that _____ to achieve economy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) moment of inertia about principal axis parallel to the web is equal to moment of inertia about principal axis normal to the web",
            "b) moment of inertia about principal axis parallel to the web is considerable larger than moment of inertia about principal axis normal to the web",
            "c) moment of inertia about principal axis normal to the web is considerable larger than moment of inertia about principal axis parallel to the web",
            "d) moment of inertia about principal axis normal to the web is considerable lesser than moment of inertia about principal axis parallel to the web"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In beam design, sections are proportioned as such that moment of inertia about principal axis normal to the web is considerable larger than moment of inertia about principal axis parallel to the web to achieve economy. Such sections are relatively weak in bending resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "To ensure that compression flange of beam is restrained from moving laterally, the cross section must be",
        "Options": [
            "a) plastic",
            "b) semi-compact",
            "c) slender",
            "d) thin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To ensure that compression flange of beam is restrained from moving laterally, the cross section must be plastic or compact. if significant ductility is required, section must invariably be plastic."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "What are laterally restrained beams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) adequate restraints are provided to beam",
            "b) adequate restraints are not provided to beam",
            "c) economically not viable",
            "d) unstable beams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In laterally restrained beams, adequate restraints are provided to beam in plane of compression flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Characteristic feature if lateral buckling is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) entire cross section do not rotate as rigid disc without any cross sectional distortion",
            "b) entire cross section rotates as rigid disc without any cross sectional distortion",
            "c) entire cross section rotates as rigid disc with cross sectional distortion",
            "d) entire cross section do not rotate as rigid disc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The characteristic feature if lateral buckling is entire cross section rotates as rigid disc without any cross sectional distortion. This behaviour is similar to axially compresses long column which after initial shortening in axial direction, deflects laterally when it buckles."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Lateral buckling in beam is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not occur in beam",
            "b) one dimensional",
            "c) two dimensional",
            "d) three dimensional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lateral buckling in beam is three dimensional in nature. It involves coupled lateral deflection and twists that is when beam deflects laterally, the applied moment exerts a torque about the deflected longitudinal axis, which causes the beam to twist."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "What is elastic critical moment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bending moment at which beam do not fail by lateral buckling",
            "b) bending moment at which beam fails by lateral buckling",
            "c) shear force at which beam do not fail by lateral buckling",
            "d) shear force at which beam fails by lateral buckling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bending moment at which beam fails by lateral buckling when subjected to a uniform end moment is called elastic critical moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition causes lateral instabilities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) section possesses different stiffness in two principal planes",
            "b) section possesses same stiffness in two principal planes",
            "c) applied loading does not induce bending in stiffer plane",
            "d) applied loading induce twisting in stiffer plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lateral instabilities occurs only if following conditions are satisfied : (i) section possesses different stiffness in two principal planes, (ii) applied loading induces bending in stiffer plane (about major axis)."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "What is lateral torsional buckling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) buckling of beam loaded in plane of its weak axis and buckling about its stronger axis accompanied by twisting",
            "b) buckling of beam loaded in plane of its strong axis and buckling about its weaker axis accompanied by twisting",
            "c) buckling of beam loaded in plane of its strong axis and buckling about its weaker axis and not accompanied by twisting",
            "d) buckling of beam loaded in plane of its weak axis and buckling about its stronger axis and not accompanied by twisting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The buckling of beam loaded in plane of its strong axis and buckling about its weaker axis accompanied by twisting (torsion) is called as torsional buckling. The load at which such beam buckles can be much less than that causing full moment capacity to develop."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Critical bending moment capacity of a beam undergoing lateral torsional buckling is a function of",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not depend on anything",
            "b) pure torsional resistance only",
            "c) warping torsional resistance only",
            "d) pure torsional resistance and warping torsional resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Critical bending moment capacity of a beam undergoing lateral torsional buckling is a function of pure torsional resistance and warping torsional resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Elastic critical moment is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) (π/L){√[(EIyGIt) + (πE/L)2IwIy]}",
            "b) (π/L){√[(EIyGIt) – (πE/L)2IwIy]}",
            "c) (π/L){√[(EIyGIt) + (πE/L) IwIy]}",
            "d) (π/L){ [(EIyGIt) – (πE/L)2IwIy]}"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Elastic critical moment is given by Mcr = (π/L){√[(EIyGIt) + (πE/L)2IwIy]}, where EIy = flexural rigidity(minor axis), GIt = torsional rigidity, It  = St.Venant torsion constant, Iw = St.Venant warping constant, L = unbraced length of beam subjected to constant moment in plane of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Lateral torsional buckling is not possible to occur if",
        "Options": [
            "a) moment of inertia about bending axis is twice than moment of inertia out of plane",
            "b) moment of inertia about bending axis is greater than moment of inertia out of plane",
            "c) moment of inertia about bending axis is equal to or less than moment of inertia out of plane",
            "d) moment of inertia about bending axis is equal to or greater than moment of inertia out of plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is not possible for lateral torsional buckling to occur if moment of inertia of section  about bending axis is equal to or less than moment of inertia out of plane."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Limit state of lateral torsion buckling is not applicable to",
        "Options": [
            "a) square shapes",
            "b) doubly symmetric I shaped beams",
            "c) I section loaded in plane of their webs",
            "d) I section singly symmetric with compression flanges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lateral torsional buckling is applicable to doubly symmetric I shaped beams, I section loaded in plane of their webs, I section singly symmetric with compression flanges. It is not possible for lateral torsional buckling to occur if moment of inertia of section  about bending axis is equal to or less than moment of inertia out of plane. So, limit state of lateral torsion buckling is not applicable for shapes bent about their minor axis for shapes with Iz ≤ Iy or for circular or square shapes."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which of the following assumptions were not made while deriving expression for elastic critical moment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) beam is initially undisturbed and without imperfections",
            "b) behaviour of beam is elastic",
            "c) load acts in plane of web only",
            "d) ends of beam are fixed support"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The following assumptions were made while deriving expression for elastic critical moment: (i) beam is initially undisturbed and without imperfections, (ii) behaviour of beam is elastic,(iii) beam is loaded with equal and opposite end moments in plane of web, (iv) load acts in plane of web only, (v) ends of beam are simply supported vertically and laterally, (vi) beam does not have residual stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "For different loading conditions, the equation of elastic critical moment is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mcr = c1  (EIyGIt) γ",
            "b) Mcr = c1 [(EIyGIt)2] γ",
            "c) Mcr = c1 [√(EIyGIt)] γ",
            "d) Mcr = c1 (EIy /GIt) γ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For different loading conditions, the equation of elastic critical moment is given by Mcr = c1 [√(EIyGIt)] γ, where c1 = equivalent uniform moment factor or moment coefficient, EIy = flexural rigidity(minor axis), GIt = torsional rigidity, γ = (π/L){√[1 + (πE/L)2IwIy]}, It  = St.Venant torsion constant, Iw = St.Venant warping constant, L = unbraced length of beam subjected to constant moment in plane of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about moment coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) for torsionally simple supports the moment coefficient is greater than or equal to unity",
            "b) for torsionally simple supports the moment coefficient is less than unity",
            "c) moment coefficient accounts for the effect of differential moment gradient on lateral torsional buckling",
            "d) it depends on type of loading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The moment coefficient accounts for the effect of differential moment gradient on lateral torsional buckling and depends on type of loading. For torsionally simple supports the moment coefficient is greater than or equal to unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "√EIyGIt  depends on",
        "Options": [
            "a) shape of beam only",
            "b) material of beam only",
            "c) shape and material of beam",
            "d) does not depend on anything"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: √EIyGIt  depends on shape and material of beam, where = flexural rigidity(minor axis), GIt = torsional rigidity."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) sections with greater lateral bending and torsional stiffness have great resistance to bending",
            "b) sections with lesser lateral bending and torsional stiffness have great resistance to bending",
            "c) sections with greater lateral bending and torsional stiffness have less resistance to bending",
            "d) lateral instability of beam cannot be reduced by selecting appropriate shapes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lateral instability of beam can be reduced by selecting appropriate shapes. Sections with greater lateral bending and torsional stiffness have great resistance to bending."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "In the equation Mcr = c1 [√(EIyGIt)] γ, γ depends on",
        "Options": [
            "a) load on beam",
            "b) shape of beam",
            "c) material of beam",
            "d) length of beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the equation Mcr = c1 [√(EIyGIt)] γ, c1 varies with loading and support conditions, [√(EIyGIt)] varies with material properties and shape of beam and γ varies with length of beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) long shallow girders have high warping stiffness",
            "b) short and deep girders have very low warping resistance",
            "c) long shallow girders have low warping stiffness",
            "d) short and shallow girders have very low warping resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Short and deep girders have very high warping stiffness while long shallow girders have low warping stiffness or resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Elastic critical moment for long shallow girders is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) (π/L){√(EIyGIt)}",
            "b) (πL){√(EIyGIt)}",
            "c) (π/L){√(EIy /GIt)}",
            "d) (πL){√(EIy  /GIt)}"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Long shallow girders have low warping stiffness or resistance. So, elastic critical moment for long shallow girders is given by (π/L){√(EIyGIt)}, where EIy = flexural rigidity(minor axis), GIt = torsional rigidity, L = unbraced length of beam subjected to constant moment in plane of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not affect lateral stability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cross sectional shape",
            "b) support conditions",
            "c) type of loading",
            "d) height of building"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors affecting lateral stability are cross sectional shape, support conditions, effective length, level of application of transverse loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I-section has high torsional stiffness",
            "b) Closed section has high torsional stiffness",
            "c) Closed section has less stiffness",
            "d) Hollow circular tube has more efficiency as flexural member"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: I-section with the larger in-plane bending stiffness does not have matching stability. in contrast, closed sections such as tubes, boxes and solid shafts have high torsional stiffness, often high as 100 times that of an open section."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is  not correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hollow circular tube has more efficiency as flexural member",
            "b) Hollow circular tube has lesser efficiency as flexural member",
            "c) It is the most efficient shape for torsional resistance",
            "d) It us rarely used as a beam element"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hollow circular tube is the most efficient shape for torsional resistance, but is rarely employed as beam element because of difficulties encountered in connecting it to other members and lesser efficiency as a flexural member."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Open cross sections have major part of material distributed",
        "Options": [
            "a) is not distributed",
            "b) on the centroid",
            "c) towards centroid",
            "d) away from centroid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In open cross sections ( I and channel sections), major part of material is distributed at the flanges, i.e. away from their centroids, to improve their resistance to in-plane bending stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "The effective length factor is _____ for beams flanges fully restrained",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 0.75",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The effective length factor K is 0.5 theoretically for flanges fully restrained. But for design purpose, it may be taken as 0.7."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "The effective length of compression flange of simply supported beam not restrained against torsion at ends is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2 L",
            "b) 1.0 L",
            "c) 0.8 L",
            "d) 0.5 L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effective length of compression flange of simply supported beam not restrained against torsion at ends is 1.2 L, where L is span length."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Effective length of compression flanges at the ends unrestrained against lateral buckling is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 L",
            "b) 0.85 L",
            "c) 0.5 L",
            "d) L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Effective length of compression flanges at the ends unrestrained against lateral buckling (i.e. free to rotate in plan) is L, where L is length of span."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Effective length of compression flanges at the ends partially restrained against lateral buckling is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.75 L",
            "b) 1.0 L",
            "c) 0.85 L",
            "d) 0.5 L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Effective length of compression flanges at the ends partially restrained against lateral buckling (i.e. free to rotate in plane in the bearings) is 0.85 L, where L is length of span."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "The most severe loading condition for cantilever is",
        "Options": [
            "a) point load acting at centre",
            "b) point load acting at tip",
            "c) point load acting between centre and fixed end",
            "d) point load acting at L/4 distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Restraint against torsion can be provided by  (i) web or flange cleats, (ii) bearing stiffeners acting together with the bearing of beam, (iii) lateral end frames or external supports to ends of compression flanges, (iv)the beam built into the supporting walls."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Provision of intermediate lateral supports ______ lateral stability of beam",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) does not change",
            "d) cannot say"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For cantilevers, the most severe loading condition is point load acting at the tip because the tip is unsupported."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "The requirement of effective bracing is",
        "Options": [
            "a) it should not have sufficient strength not to withstand forces transferred to it by beam",
            "b) it should not have sufficient strength to withstand forces transferred to it by beam",
            "c) it should have sufficient stiffness so that buckling of beam occurs in between braces",
            "d) it should not have sufficient stiffness so that buckling of beam occurs in between braces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Provision of intermediate lateral supports increases the lateral stability of beam. For bracings to be effective, the braces should be prevented from moving in axial direction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) torsional bracing attached near bottom flange should bend in single curvature",
            "b) torsional bracing attached near bottom flange should not bend in single curvature",
            "c) its flexural stiffness should be 4EIb/S",
            "d) its flexural stiffness should be 6EIb/S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The requirements of effective bracing are (i) it should have sufficient strength to withstand forces transferred to it by beam, (ii) it should have sufficient stiffness so that buckling of beam occurs in between braces."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "The lateral stability of tranversely loaded beam is dependent on",
        "Options": [
            "a) arrangement of load only",
            "b) level of application of load only",
            "c) both arrangement and level of application of load",
            "d) is not dependent on any of these"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Torsional bracing attached near bottom flange should bend in single curvature and its flexural stiffness should be 2EI/S, where Ib is moment of inertia of brace, S is spacing between girders."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "As the beam undergoes bending under applied loads, axial strain distribution at a point in beam",
        "Options": [
            "a) axial strain is not produced",
            "b) remains constant",
            "c) varies along depth of beam",
            "d) varies along length of beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the beam undergoes bending under applied loads, axial strain distribution at a point in beam varies along the depth of beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "The beam buckles elastically if",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mcr < My",
            "b) Mcr > My",
            "c) Mcr = My",
            "d) Mcr = 2My"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If Mcr critical moment of a section is less than yield moment My , then beam buckles elastically."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "If Mcr > My of a beam section, then",
        "Options": [
            "a) beam does not buckle",
            "b) beam buckles fully elastically",
            "c) beam buckles completely plastically",
            "d) some amount of plasticity is experienced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When critical moment of a section Mcr  is greater than My , some amount of plasticity is experienced at the outer edges before buckling is initiated."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Beams with intermediate slenderness fail by",
        "Options": [
            "a) elastic buckling",
            "b) inelastic lateral buckling",
            "c) attains Mp without buckling",
            "d) do not fail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Beams with intermediate slenderness (0.4 < √Mp/Mcr < 1.2)  fail by inelastic lateral buckling at loads below Mp and above Mcr ."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "What are residual stresses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) stresses developed during construction",
            "b) stresses developed due to seismic load",
            "c) stresses developed due to vibration",
            "d) stresses developed during manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During the process of manufacture,  steel sections are subjected to large thermal expansions resulting in yield level strains in sections. As subsequent cooling is not uniform throughout the section, self-equilibrating patterns of stresses are formed. These stresses are called residual stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) yielding of section starts at lower moments",
            "b) yielding of section starts at higher moments",
            "c) yielding of section does not start at lower moments",
            "d) yielding of section does not occur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to presence of residual stresses, yielding of section starts at lower moments. Then with increase in moment, yielding spreads through the cross section."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "7. Match the pair<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">(i) high slender beams\t\t \t   (A) attain M&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt; without buckling\n(ii) stocky beams\t\t\t   (B) fail by inelastic buckling\n(iii) intermediate slender beams           (C) fail by elastic buckling</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) i-A, ii-B, iii-C",
            "b) i-C, ii-B, iii-A",
            "c) i-C, ii-A, iii-B",
            "d) i-A, ii-C, iii-B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Beams with high slenderness fail by elastic lateral buckling at Mcr. Beams of intermediate slenderness fail by inelastic lateral buckling at loads below Mp and above Mcr. Stocky beams attains Mp without buckling with negligible lateral deformations."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) torsional bracing attached to top flange should bend in single curvature",
            "b) torsional bracing attached to top flange should not bend in reverse curvature",
            "c) its flexural stiffness should be 6EIb/S",
            "d) its flexural stiffness should be 4EIb/S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Torsional bracing attached to top flange should bend in reverse curvature and its flexural stiffness should be 6EIb/S, where S is spacing between girders."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Which of the following aspects need not be considered for beam design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) deflection",
            "b) material of beam",
            "c) buckling",
            "d) lateral supports"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The important aspects which need to be considered for beam design are moments, shears, deflection, crippling, buckling, and lateral support."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "The design bending strength of laterally supported beams is governed by",
        "Options": [
            "a) torsion",
            "b) bending",
            "c) lateral torsional buckling",
            "d) yield stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design bending strength of laterally supported beams is governed by yield stress and that of laterally unsupported beams is governed by lateral torsional buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "The web is susceptible to shear buckling when d/tw",
        "Options": [
            "a) <67ε",
            "b) < 2×67ε",
            "c) >67ε",
            "d) < 70ε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For beams with plastic, compact, semi-compact flanges and slender web (d/tw > 67ε), the web is susceptible to shear buckling before yielding."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "When there is no shear buckling,",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vp = Vn",
            "b) Vp > Vn",
            "c) Vp < Vn",
            "d) Vp = 2Vn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When there is no shear buckling (d/tw ≤ 67ε), the nominal shear resistance Vn equals plastic shear strength Vp. "
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Plastic shear resistance is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) fy/√3",
            "b) shear area x fy x √3",
            "c) shear area x fy/√3",
            "d) shear area / (fy/√3)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plastic shear resistance is given by Vp = shear area x fy/√3."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "The design shear strength is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vn",
            "b) Vn/γm0",
            "c) Vn x γm0",
            "d) γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design shear strength is given by Vd = Vn/γm0 , where Vn= plastic shear resistance, γm0  = partial factor of safety."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "The web area will be fully effective when shear force V",
        "Options": [
            "a) ≥ 0.6Vd",
            "b) < 0.6Vd",
            "c) ≤ 0.6Vd",
            "d) >2×0.6Vd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When shear force V ≤ 0.6Vd, the web area will be fully effective and entire cross section of beam will be effective in resisting the moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about sections with high shear case V>0.6Vd ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) web area is ineffective",
            "b) web area is fully effective",
            "c) flanges will not resist moment",
            "d) moment is not reduced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When shear exceed the limit V&gt0.6Vd, web area will be ineffective and only flanges will resist the moment. Because of this for high shear case, moment capacity of beam is reduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "The design bending strength of beams when V ≤ 0.6Vd is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) βb /Zpfy γm0",
            "b) βbZpfy / γm0",
            "c) βbZp /fy γm0",
            "d) βbZpfy γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design bending strength of beams when V ≤ 0.6Vd is given by Md = βbZpfy / γm0 , where βb is a constant, Zp = plastic section modulus of cross section, fy is yiled stress of material, γm0 = 1.1,partial safety factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength for plastic section is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 2.0",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 1.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength is 1 for plastic and compact sections. The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength for semi-compact section depends on section modulus."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength for semi-compact section is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ze/Zp",
            "b) ZeZp",
            "c) Zp/ Ze",
            "d) Ze+Zp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength for semi-compact section is given by βb = Ze/Zp , where Ze, Zp are elastic and plastic moduli of the cross section."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "The check for design bending strength for simply supported beams is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Md = 2.4Zpfy/γm0",
            "b) Md < 1.2Zpfy/γm0",
            "c) Md ≤ 1.2Zpfy/γm0",
            "d) Md ≥ 1.2Zpfy/γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The check for design bending strength for simply supported beams is given by Md ≤ 1.2Zpfy/γm0 to ensure that onset of plasticity under unfactored loads is prevented."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "The check for design bending strength for cantilever beams is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Md = 2.4Zpfy/γm0",
            "b) Md ≤ 1.5Zpfy/γm0",
            "c) Md ≤ 1.2Zpfy/γm0",
            "d) Md ≥ 1.5Zpfy/γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The check for design bending strength for cantilever beams is given by Md ≤ 1.5Zpfy/γm0 to ensure that onset of plasticity under unfactored loads – dead loads, imposed loads and wind load- is prevented."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "The design bending strength for slender sections is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Md = Zefy‘",
            "b) Md = fy‘",
            "c) Md = Ze /fy‘",
            "d) Md = Ze +fy‘"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design bending strength for slender sections is given by Md = Zefy‘ , where Ze is elastic section modulus of cross section and fy‘ is reduced design strength for slender sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "IS 800 permits bolt holes in the flanges to be ignored when",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.9fuAnf/γm1 ≤ 2fyAgf/γm0",
            "b) 0.9fuAnf/γm1 ≤ fyAgf/γm0",
            "c) 0.9fuAnf/γm1 ≥ fyAgf/γm0",
            "d) 0.9fuAnf/γm1 ≤ 0.5fyAgf/γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS 800 permits bolt holes in the flanges to be ignored when the tensile fracture strength of flange is at least equal to tensile yield strength i.e. when 0.9fuAnf/γm1 ≥ fyAgf/γm0  or (Anf/Agf) ≥ (fy/fu)x(γm1 /γm0)x(1/0.9), where Anf/Agf = ratio of net area to gross area of tension flange, fy/fu  = ratio of yield stress to ultimate stress of material, γm1 /γm0  = ratio of partial safety factors against ultimate stress to yield stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "The moment capacity of semi-compact section for V > 0.6Vd is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Md = Zefyγm0",
            "b) Md = Zefy",
            "c) Md = fy/γm0",
            "d) Md = Zefy/γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Few I-and channel sections are semi-compact because of width-thickness ratio. The moment capacity of semi-compact section for V > 0.6Vd is given by Md = Zefy/γm0, where Ze = elastic section modulus of whole section, fy = yield stress of material, γm0 = partial safety factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "What is shear lag effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) the phenomenon of non uniform bending stress not due to influence of shear strain induced on bending stresses in flanges",
            "b) the phenomenon of uniform bending stress not due to influence of shear strain induced on bending stresses in flanges",
            "c) the phenomenon of uniform bending stress due to influence of shear strain induced on bending stresses in flanges",
            "d) the phenomenon of non uniform bending stress due to influence of shear strain induced on bending stresses in flanges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The shear strain induced influences bending stresses in flanges and causes sections to warp. This consequently modifies the bending stresses determined by simple bending theory and results in higher stresses near junction of web to flange elements with stress dropping as distance from beam web increases. The resultant stress distribution across flange is therefore non uniform and this phenomenon is known as shear lag."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "As per IS 800:2007, shear lag effects in flanges may be disregarded for outstand elements if",
        "Options": [
            "a) bo ≥ L0 / 20",
            "b) bo ≤ L0 / 20",
            "c) bo > L0 / 20",
            "d) bo = L0 / 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As per IS 800:2007, shear lag effects in flanges may be disregarded for outstand elements if bo ≤ L0 / 20, where bo = width of flange outstand, L0 = length between points of zero moment in the span."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "As per IS 800:2007, shear lag effects in flanges may be disregarded for internal elements if",
        "Options": [
            "a) bi ≤ L0 / 10",
            "b) bi ≤ L0 / 20",
            "c) bi > L0 / 10",
            "d) bi = L0 / 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per IS 800:2007, shear lag effects in flanges may be disregarded for internal elements if bi ≤ L0 / 10, where bi = width of internal element, L0 = length between points of zero moment in the span."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Shear lag effect depends on",
        "Options": [
            "a) material of beam",
            "b) width of beam only",
            "c) width-to-span ratio",
            "d) cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shear lag effect depends upon width-to-span ratio, beam end restraints, and type of load."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) point load causes less shear lag than uniform load",
            "b) point load causes more shear lag than uniform load",
            "c) point load causes half times the shear lag than uniform load",
            "d) point load causes equal shear lag as uniform load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resultant stress distribution across flanges is non-uniform and is called shear lag. Point load causes more shear lag than uniform load."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "The moment capacity of plastic section for V > 0.6Vd is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mdv = Md – β(Md – Mfd)",
            "b) Mdv = Md + β(Md – Mfd)",
            "c) Mdv = Md – β(Md + Mfd)",
            "d) Mdv = Md + β(Md + Mfd)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moment capacity of plastic or compact section for V > 0.6Vd is given by Mdv = Md – β(Md – Mfd), where Md = plastic design moment of whole section disregarding high shear force effect but considering web buckling effect, Mfd = plastic design strength of area of cross section excluding shear area, considering partial safety factor γm0, β is constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The value of β in equation of moment capacity of plastic section for V > 0.6Vd is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) ([Vd/V] -1)2",
            "b) (2[Vd/V] +1)2",
            "c) (2[Vd/V] -1)2",
            "d) (2[Vd/V] -1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of β in equation of moment capacity of plastic section for V > 0.6Vd is given by β = (2[Vd/V] -1)2, where Vd =  design shear strength as governed by web yielding or web buckling, V = factored applied shear force."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The check for moment capacity of plastic section for V > 0.6Vd is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mdv ≥ 1.2Zefy/γm0",
            "b) Mdv ≤ 1.2Zefy/γm0",
            "c) Mdv > 1.2Zefy/γm0",
            "d) Mdv = 2.2Zefy/γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The check for moment capacity of plastic section for V > 0.6Vd is given by Mdv ≤ 1.2Zefy/γm0, where Ze = elastic section modulus of whole section, fy = yield stress of material, γm0 = partial safety factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "The design bending strength of laterally unsupported beams is governed by",
        "Options": [
            "a) torsion",
            "b) bending",
            "c) lateral torsional buckling",
            "d) yield stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Beams with major axis bending and compression flange not restrained against lateral bending (or inadequate lateral support) fail by lateral torsional buckling before attaining their bending strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "The effect of lateral-torsional buckling need not be considered when",
        "Options": [
            "a) λLT ≤ 0.4",
            "b) λLT ≥0.4",
            "c) λLT > 0.8",
            "d) λLT = 0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effect of lateral-torsional buckling need not be considered when λLT ≤ 0.4, where λLT is the non dimensional slenderness ratio for lateral torsional buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "The bending strength of laterally unsupported beams is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Md  = βbZp /fbd",
            "b) Md  = βb /Zpfbd",
            "c) Md  = βbZp",
            "d) Md  = βbZpfbd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bending strength of laterally unsupported beams is given by Md  = βbZpfbd, where βb is a constant, Zp is plastic section modulus, fbd is design bending compressive stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength of laterally unsupported beams for plastic sections is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 2.5",
            "c) 1.0",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength of laterally unsupported beams for plastic and compact sections is 1.0. This constant depends on elastic and plastic section modulus for semi-compact sections."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength of laterally unsupported beams for semi-compact sections is",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ze/Zp",
            "b) ZeZp",
            "c) Zp/Ze",
            "d) Zp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of βb in the equation of design bending strength of laterally unsupported beams for semi-compact sections is Ze/Zp, where Ze is elastic section modulus, Zp is plastic section modulus."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "The value of design bending compressive stress fbd is",
        "Options": [
            "a) XLT fy",
            "b) XLT fy /fy",
            "c) XLT fy fy",
            "d) XLT /fy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of design bending compressive stress fbd is XLT fy /fy, where XLT is bending stress reduction factor to account for lateral torsional buckling, fy is yield stress, fy is partial safety factor for material (=1.10)."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "The bending stress reduction factor to account for lateral buckling is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) XLT = 1/{φLT + (φ2LT – λ2LT)}",
            "b) XLT = 1/{φLT  – (φ2LT + λ2LT)}",
            "c) XLT = 1/{φLT  – (φ2LT + λ2LT)0.5}",
            "d) XLT = 1/{φLT + (φ2LT – λ2LT)0.5}"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bending stress reduction factor to account for lateral buckling is given by XLT = 1/{φLT + (φ2LT – λ2LT)0.5}, where φLT depends upon imperfection factor and non dimensional slenderness ratio, λLT is non dimensional slenderness ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "The value of φLT in bending stress reduction factor is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) φLT  = [ 1 – αLT (λLT + 0.2) + λ2LT].",
            "b) φLT  = [ 1 + αLT (λLT – 0.2) + λ2LT].",
            "c) φLT  = 0.5 [ 1 – αLT (λLT + 0.2) + λ2LT].",
            "d) φLT  = 0.5 [ 1 + αLT (λLT – 0.2) + λ2LT]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of φLT in bending stress reduction factor is given by φLT  = 0.5 [ 1 + αLT (λLT – 0.2) + λ2LT], where αLT  is imperfection factor, λLT is non dimensional slenderness ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Imperfection factor for rolled section is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 0.21",
            "c) 2.1",
            "d) 4.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Imperfection factor for rolled section is 0.21. The imperfection factor takes into account all the relevant defects in real structure when considering buckling, geometric imperfections, eccentricity of applied loads and residual stresses. It depends on the buckling curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Imperfection factor for welded section is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.9",
            "b) 0.21",
            "c) 2.1",
            "d) 0.49"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Imperfection factor for welded section is 0.49. The imperfection factor depends on the buckling curve and takes into account all the relevant defects in real structure when considering buckling, geometric imperfections, eccentricity of applied loads and residual stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Non-dimensional slenderness ratio is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) λLT = √(βbZpfy/Mcr)",
            "b) λLT = √(βbZpfyMcr)",
            "c) λLT = √(βbZp/Mcr)",
            "d) λLT = √(βbZpfy)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Non-dimensional slenderness ratio is given by λLT = √(βbZpfy/Mcr), where βb  = 1 for plastic and compact sections, βb  = Ze/Zp for semi-compact sections, Ze = elastic section modulus, Zp = plastic section modulus, Mcr  is elastic critical moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "The check for non- dimensional slenderness ratio is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) λLT =  2.4 √(Zefy/Mcr)",
            "b) λLT > 2 .4 √(Zefy/Mcr)",
            "c) λLT ≤ 1.2 √(Zefy/Mcr)",
            "d) λLT ≥ 1.2 √(Zefy/Mcr)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The non- dimensional slenderness ratio is given by λLT = √(βbZpfy/Mcr). The check for it is given by λLT ≤ 1.2 √(Zefy/Mcr), where Ze = elastic section modulus, Mcr  is elastic critical moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) λLT = √(fy/fcr,b)",
            "b) λLT = fy/fcr,b",
            "c) λLT = (fy/fcr,b)2",
            "d) λLT = √(fy fcr,b)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: λLT = √(βbZpfy/Mcr) = √(fy/fcr,b), where βb  = 1 for plastic and compact sections, βb  = Ze/Zp for semi-compact sections, Ze = elastic section modulus, Zp = plastic section modulus, Mcr  is elastic critical moment, fcr,b is extreme compressive elastic buckling stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "The elastic critical moment is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mcr  = βb fcr,b",
            "b) Mcr  = βbZp / fcr,b",
            "c) Mcr  = βbZp",
            "d) Mcr  = βbZp fcr,b"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The elastic critical moment is given by Mcr  = √{[π2EIy/ L2MLT][ GIt + (π2EIw/L2LT)]} = βbZp fcr,b , Iy = moment of inertia about minor axis, Iw =  warping constant, It = St. Venant’s constant, G = Shear modulus."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Warping constant in elastic critical moment is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) (1+βf)βf Iy h2f",
            "b) (1-βf)βf Iy h2f",
            "c) βf Iy h2f",
            "d) (1-βf)/βf Iy h2f"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Warping constant in elastic critical moment is given by Iw = (1-βf)βf Iy h2f  , where βf is ratio of moment of inertia of compression flange to sum of moments of inertia of compression and tension flanges, Iy = moment of inertia about minor axis, hf = centre-to-centre distance between flanges."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "St. Venant’s constant is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) ∑biti2/3",
            "b) ∑biti2",
            "c) ∑biti3/3",
            "d) ∑biti"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: St. Venant’s constant is given by It = ∑biti3/3. For open section (e.g. I -section) : It = 2bft3f/3 + bft3w/3."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "The value of fcr,b is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) fcr,b = [1.1π2E/(LLT/ry)2]{1+1/20[(LLT/ry)/(hf/tf)]2}",
            "b) fcr,b = [1.1π2E/(LLT/ry)]{1-1/20[(LLT/ry)/(hf/tf)]}",
            "c) fcr,b = [1.1π2E/(LLT/ry)2]{1+1/20[(LLT/ry)/(hf/tf)]2}0.5",
            "d) fcr,b = [1.1π2E/(LLT/ry)2]{1-1/20[(LLT/ry)/(hf/tf)]2}0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of fcr,b is given by fcr,b = [1.1π2E/(LLT/ry)2]{1+1/20[(LLT/ry)/(hf/tf)]2}0.5, where ry = radius of gyration about weaker axis, LLT = effective length for lateral-torsional buckling, tf = thickness of flange, hf = centre-to-centre distance between flanges."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "A beam can be subjected to which of the following shear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal shear only",
            "b) transverse shear only",
            "c) longitudinal or transverse shear",
            "d) beam is not subjected to shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A beam is subjected to two types of shear: transverse (vertical) shear and longitudinal shear."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Shear forces will govern the design of beam if",
        "Options": [
            "a) beam is short",
            "b) beam is long",
            "c) beam carry light loads",
            "d) shear forces will never act in beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shear forces will govern the design of beam if beams are short and are heavily loaded (heavy concentrated load) or deeply coped."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Longitudinal shear occurs due to",
        "Options": [
            "a) light load on beam",
            "b) bending of beam",
            "c) twisting of beam",
            "d) does not occur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Longitudinal or horizontal shear occurs due to bending of beam. The fibers above  shorten in length and those below neutral axis elongate under sagging bending moments. Therefore, the fibers tend to slip over each other and the effect is maximum at the neutral axis. The tendency to slip is resisted by shear strength of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "The shear stress distribution of I-section varies",
        "Options": [
            "a) cubically with depth",
            "b) as straight line with depth",
            "c) as horizontally with depth",
            "d) parabolically with depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The shear stress distribution of I-section varies parabolically with depth with maximum occurring at the neutral axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "The longitudinal shear is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) τ = VAyIzt",
            "b) τ = VAy/Izt",
            "c) τ = VAy/Iz",
            "d) τ = Vy/Izt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The longitudinal shear is given by τ = VAy/Izt, where V is vertical shear force at section under consideration, Iz is moment of inertia of entire section about zz-axis, neutral axis, Ay is static moment of area of cross section, t is thickness of portion of cross section at which longitudinal shear is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases shear does not govern design of beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) when web thickness is large in plate girders",
            "b) when depth of beam section is small and loaded uniformly",
            "c) when large concentrated loads are placed near support",
            "d) when two members are rigidly connected together with their webs lying in same plane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shear determines design of beam when depth of beam section is small and loaded uniformly, when large concentrated loads are placed near beam supports, when two members are rigidly connected together with their webs lying in same plane, when web thickness is small in plate girders."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding I-section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) average shear is very larger than maximum shear",
            "b) maximum shear is very larger than average shear",
            "c) flanges resist very small portion of shear",
            "d) webs resist very small portion of shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For an I-section, flanges resist very small portion of shear and a significant portion is resisted by web. The maximum and average shear for I-section are almost same."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Average stress is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) τav = V/d",
            "b) τav = Vdtw",
            "c) τav = V/tw",
            "d) τav = V/dtw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: for practical purposes, average shear stress is used and is given by τav = V/Av = /dtw, where d = depth of web, tw = thickness of web, Av is shear area."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Nominal shear strength based on Von-Mises yield criterion is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vn = Avfyv",
            "b) Vn = Avfyv/√3",
            "c) Vn = fyv/√3",
            "d) Vn = Avfyv/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nominal shear strength based on Von-Mises yield criterion is given by Vn = Avfyv/√3, where fyv is yield strength of web, Vn is nominal shear resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) web in rolled section behaves like a column when not placed under concentrated loads",
            "b) web in rolled section behaves like a column when placed under concentrated loads",
            "c) web in rolled section does not behave like a column when placed under concentrated loads",
            "d) web in rolled section cannot be compared with column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The web in rolled section behaves like a column when placed under concentrated loads. The web is quite thin and is therefore, subjected to buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The effective depth when top flanges are restrained against lateral deflection and rotation is",
        "Options": [
            "a) d/3",
            "b) d",
            "c) 2d",
            "d) d/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bottom flange is assumed to be restrained against lateral deflection and rotation. for top flanges, the end restraints and effective depth of the web are to be considered. The effective depth when top flanges are restrained against lateral deflection and rotation is d/2, where d is depth of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The effective depth when top flanges are restrained against lateral deflection but not against rotation is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2d/3",
            "b) d",
            "c) 2d",
            "d) d/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effective depth when top flanges are restrained against lateral deflection but not against rotation is 2d/3, where d is depth of web. Bottom flange is assumed to be restrained against lateral deflection and rotation. for top flanges, the end restraints and effective depth of the web are to be considered."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "The effective depth when top flanges are restrained against rotation but not against lateral deflection is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2d/3",
            "b) 2d",
            "c) d",
            "d) d/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bottom flange is assumed to be restrained against lateral deflection and rotation. for top flanges, the end restraints and effective depth of the web are to be considered. The effective depth when top flanges are restrained against rotation but not against lateral deflection is d, where d is depth of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "The effective depth when top flanges are not restrained against rotation and lateral deflection is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2d/3",
            "b) 2d",
            "c) d",
            "d) d/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The effective depth when top flanges are not restrained against rotation and lateral deflection is 2d, where d is depth of web. Bottom flange is assumed to be restrained against lateral deflection and rotation. for top flanges, the end restraints and effective depth of the web are to be considered."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "The maximum diagonal compression in plate girder simply supported occurs",
        "Options": [
            "a) does not occur",
            "b) above neutral axis",
            "c) below neutral axis",
            "d) at neutral axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum diagonal compression in plate girder simply supported occurs at neutral axis . It will be inclined at 45˚ to the neutral axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Web buckling strength at support of simply supported plate girder is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fwb =Btwfcd",
            "b) Fwb =twfcd",
            "c) Fwb =Btw",
            "d) Fwb =Bfcd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Web buckling strength at support of simply supported plate girder is given by Fwb =Btwfcd , where B is length of stiff portion of bearing plus additional length given by dispersion at 45˚to the level of neutral axis, tw is thickness of web, fcd is allowable compressive stress corresponding to assumed web strut according to buckling curve c."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Slenderness ratio when ends are assumed to be fixed for a plate girder is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.45 d",
            "b) 8.5 d/t",
            "c) 2.45 d/t",
            "d) 8.5 t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When ends are assumed to be fixed, effective length = d√2/2 = d/√2, minimum radius of gyration = t/√12. Therefore slenderness ratio = (d/√2)/( t/√12) = 2.45d/t, where d = depth of web, t = thickness of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "What is web crippling ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) web is of large thickness",
            "b) flange near portion of stress concentration tends to fold over web",
            "c) web near portion of stress concentration tends to fold over flange",
            "d) flange is of large thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Webs of rolled section are subjected to large amount of stresses just below concentrated loads and above reactions from support. Stress concentration occurs at junction of web and flange. As a result, large bearing stresses are developed below concentrated load. Consequently, the web near portion of stress concentration tends to fold over flange. This type of local buckling phenomenon is called crippling or crimpling of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) web crippling is buckling of web caused by compressive force delivered through flange",
            "b) web crippling is buckling of flange caused by compressive force delivered through web",
            "c) web crippling is buckling of web caused by tensile force delivered through flange",
            "d) web crippling is buckling of flange caused by tensile force delivered through web"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Web crippling is buckling of web caused by compressive force delivered through flange. To keep bearing stresses within permissible limits, the concentrated load should be transferred from flanges to web on sufficiently large bearing areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "The most critical location for failure due to web crippling is",
        "Options": [
            "a) flange cross section",
            "b) middle of web",
            "c) start of fillet",
            "d) root of fillet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most critical location for failure due to web crippling is root of fillet since resisting area has the smallest value here."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "The angle of dispersion of load for web crippling is assumed to be",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2:1",
            "b) 1:2.5",
            "c) 4:5",
            "d) 2:3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The angle of dispersion of load for web crippling is assumed to be 1:2.5 .With reference to this, bearing length is calculated."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "The crippling strength of web at supports is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fcrip = (b+n1)fyw",
            "b) Fcrip = (b+n1) t",
            "c) Fcrip = (b+n1)/fywt",
            "d) Fcrip = (b+n1)fywt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The crippling strength of web at supports is given by Fcrip = (b+n1)fywt, where b+n1 is length obtained by dispersion through flange, t is thickness of web, fyw is design yield strength of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "The crippling strength of web at interior point where concentrated load is acting is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fcrip = (b+2n1)fyw",
            "b) Fcrip = (b+2n1) t",
            "c) Fcrip = (b+2n1)fywt",
            "d) Fcrip = (b+n1)/fywt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The crippling strength of web at interior point where concentrated load is acting is given by Fcrip = (b+2n1)fywt, where b+2n1 is length obtained by dispersion through flange, t is thickness of web, fyw is design yield strength of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Which off the following will be a remedy to web crippling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) spreading load over small portion of flange",
            "b) provide stiffeners which bear against flanges at load points",
            "c) provide web of small thickness",
            "d) web crippling cannot be prevented"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Web crippling can be prevented by spreading load over large portion of flange. The other remedy is provide stiffeners which bear against flanges at load points and are connected to web to transfer force to it gradually. The other remedy is to make the web thicker."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Which of the following may not occur due to excessive deflection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ponding problem in roofs",
            "b) misalignment of supporting machinery",
            "c) cracking of plaster ceilings",
            "d) twisting of beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Excessive deflection may cause cracking of plaster ceilings, misalignment of supporting machinery and cause excessive vibration, ponding problem in roofs, etc.  Hence deflection in beam needs to be limited."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "What is ponding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) excessive deflection of flat roof resulting in accumulation of rainwater",
            "b) excessive deflection of flat roof not resulting in accumulation of rainwater",
            "c) small deflection of flat roof resulting in accumulation of rainwater",
            "d) small deflection of flat roof not resulting in accumulation of rainwater"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Excessive deflection of flat roof resulting in accumulation of water during rainstorms is called ponding and it causes damage to the roof material."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Deflection can be reduced by",
        "Options": [
            "a) proving less restraints",
            "b) increasing span",
            "c) increasing depth of beam",
            "d) decreasing depth of beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Deflection can be reduced by increasing depth of beam, reducing the span, providing greater end restraints or by other means such as providing camber."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Beam deflection is not a function of",
        "Options": [
            "a) loading",
            "b) span",
            "c) length of column",
            "d) geometry of cross section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Beam deflection is a function of loading, span, modulus of elasticity and geometry of cross section. Small deflections of beams do not cause structural problems in general except for discomfort to the users. But excessive deflections may lead to crack in plaster or ceilings and may damage material attached to or supported by beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "What is the maximum vertical deflection in industrial building for purlins and girts subjected to live load/wind load for elastic cladding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) span/150",
            "b) span/180",
            "c) span/250",
            "d) span/100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum deflection in industrial building for purlins and girts subjected to live load/wind load for elastic cladding is span/150 and for brittle cladding is span/180."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "What is the maximum vertical deflection in other buildings (other than industrial buildings)for floor subjected to live load and elements not susceptible to cracking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) span/150",
            "b) span/180",
            "c) span/300",
            "d) span/100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum deflection in other buildings (other than industrial buildings) for floor subjected to live load and elements not susceptible to cracking is span/300."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "What is the maximum vertical deflection in other buildings (other than industrial buildings) for floor subjected to live load and elements susceptible to cracking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) span/150",
            "b) span/360",
            "c) span/300",
            "d) span/100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum deflection in other buildings (other than industrial buildings) for floor subjected to live load and elements susceptible to cracking is span/360."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "What is the maximum lateral deflection in other buildings (other than industrial buildings) subjected to wind load and for brittle cladding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) height/300",
            "b) height/250",
            "c) height/100",
            "d) height/500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum lateral deflection in other buildings (other than industrial buildings) subjected to wind load and for brittle cladding is height /500 and for elastic cladding is height/300."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "What is the maximum vertical deflection for a cantilever member in other buildings (other than industrial buildings) subjected to live load and elements not susceptible to cracking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) span/150",
            "b) span/180",
            "c) span/300",
            "d) span/100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum vertical deflection for a cantilever member in other buildings (other than industrial buildings) subjected to live load and elements not susceptible to cracking is span/150 and for elements susceptible to cracking is span/180."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "What is the maximum lateral deflection of column/frame in industrial buildings subjected to crane load plus wind load and for brittle cladding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) height/300",
            "b) height/250",
            "c) height/400",
            "d) height/500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum lateral deflection of column/frame in industrial buildings subjected to crane load plus wind load and for brittle cladding (pendant operated)  is height/400 and for elastic cladding (cab operated) is height/200."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "The strength of steel beam depends on",
        "Options": [
            "a) strength of tension flange",
            "b) strength of compression flange",
            "c) strength of web",
            "d) does not depend on strength of section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The strength of steel beam depends on the strength of compression flange. An open hole in the compression flange affects the strength of steel beam more than a hole in tension flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "A hole in flange of beam causes",
        "Options": [
            "a) increase in stress",
            "b) decrease in stress",
            "c) makes the stress to half",
            "d) does not affect the stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A hole in flange of beam causes an increase in stress. If the hole in compression flange contains rivet or bolt, the strength reduction is lessened as fastener can transmit compression."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Holes in beam webs should be placed at  ____ and in flanges it should be placed at ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high shear, high bending moment",
            "b) high bending moment, high shear",
            "c) low bending moment, low shear",
            "d) low shear, low bending moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Holes in beam webs have less effect on flexural strength than holes in the flanges. Holes in beam webs should be placed only at sections of low shear. In the flanges, the holes should be cut at points of low bending moment. If this is not possible, the effect of the holes should be accounted for design."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "The strength of the beams with openings may be governed by plastic deformations due to",
        "Options": [
            "a) moment only",
            "b) shear only",
            "c) both moment and shear",
            "d) does not depend on moment or shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The strength of the beams with openings may be governed by plastic deformations due to both moment and shear at the openings. The strength realised will depend upon the interaction between moment and shear. The reduction in moment capacity at the openings is small while the reduction in shear capacity may be significant."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of the following are correct regarding design of beams with openings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) web opening should be away from support by twice the beam depth",
            "b) hole should be eccentrically placed in web",
            "c) hole should not be placed within middle one third of the span",
            "d) clear spacing between openings should be less than beam depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: General guidelines for design of beams with openings are as follows : (i)The hole should be centrally placed in web and eccentricity should be avoided, (ii) The best location for the opening is within the middle one third of the span, (iii) Web opening should be away from support and it should be away by twice the depth of beam, (iv) Clear spacing between openings should be more than depth of beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not correct regarding design of beams with openings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diameter of circular opening should be restricted to 0.5D",
            "b) for rectangular stiffened openings depth should be less than 0.7D and length less 2D",
            "c) for rectangular unstiffened openings, depth should be less than 0.5D and length less than 1.5D",
            "d) point load should be applied within a distance d from adjacent opening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: General guidelines for design of beams with openings are as follows : (i) The diameter of circular opening should be restricted to 0.5D, where D is depth of beam, (ii) For rectangular unstiffened openings, depth should be less than 0.5D and length less than 1.5D, where D is depth of beam (iii) For rectangular stiffened openings, depth should be less than 0.7D and length less 2D, where D is depth of beam (iv) Point loads should not be applied within a distance d from the adjacent opening."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "What is castellated beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) beam with no openings in web",
            "b) beam with number of regular openings in web and flange",
            "c) beam with number of regular openings in web",
            "d) beam with number of regular openings in flange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A beam with number of regular openings in its web is called castellated beam. A castellated beam is formed by flame cutting a single rolled wide flange beam in a definite predetermined pattern and then rejoining the segments by welding to form a regular pattern of holes in the web."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "The new rolled section of castellated beam will have depth",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50% more than original section",
            "b) 50% less than original section",
            "c) 25% less than original section",
            "d) depth does not change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The new rolled section of castellated beam will have depth at least  50% more and its section modulus increases by 2.25 times the original section. This allows the beam to span further than parent rolled section."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "Castellated beams have ______ shear capacity than original beams",
        "Options": [
            "a) shear capacity does not change",
            "b) twice",
            "c) increased",
            "d) reduced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Castellated beams have reduced shear capacity. It has reduced shear capacity due to stress concentrations near the openings."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Which of the following measures can be taken to improve shear capacity of castellated beams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) openings can be made away from neutral axis",
            "b) openings can be made close to neutral axis",
            "c) making cuts in straight manner",
            "d) by not using stiffenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Shear capacity of castellated beams can be improved by making openings close to neutral axis and making cuts in a wavy manner. Stiffening can be provided at load concentrations and reaction points to improve its shear carrying capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of castellated beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) light in weight",
            "b) can be assembled fast",
            "c) cheaper",
            "d) high fire resistance than original rolled section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Castellated beams are light in weight, cheaper, they have relatively high resistance and can be assembled fast at the construction site. They are less fire resistant than normal rolled sections. Castellated beams can very easily be cambered and cranked."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases are castellated beam desirable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) when more span to be covered than rolled section",
            "b) when beam subjected to substantial concentrated loads",
            "c) when beam to be used as continuous beam",
            "d) when higher fire resistance than rolled section required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The section of castellated beam will have more depth and section modulus than original rolled section. This allows the beam to span further than parent rolled section. Castellated beams may not be desirable when beam is subjected to substantial concentrated loads, or when castellated beam is used as a continuous beam across several supports. Castellated beams are less attractive when very high requirements for fire resistance are required because the fire resistant coating has to be around 20% thicker than for rolled sections in order to obtain the same fire resistance as rolled section."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "7. Match the pairs<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">   (A) Vierendeel mechanism\t\t  (i) caused by heavy loading and short span\n   (B) Lateral torsional buckling of web  (ii) caused due to excessive horizontal shear\n   (C) Rupture of welded joint in web\t  (iii) due to excessive deformation across openings in web\n   (D) Web Buckling\t\t\t  (iv)caused by large shear</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii, D-iv",
            "b) A-iv, B-iii, C-ii, D-i",
            "c) A-iii, B-iv, C-ii, D-i",
            "d) A-i, B-iv, C-iii, D-ii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are number of possible modes of failure for castellated beams. Some of them are as follows: (i) Vierendeel mechanism – occurs due to excessive deformation across one of the openings in web and formation of hinges in corners of castellation, (ii) Lateral torsional buckling of web – caused by large shear at welded joint, (iii) Rupture of welded joint in web – caused due to excessive horizontal shear at welded joint in the web, (iv) Web Buckling – caused by heavy loading and short span of beam, this may be avoided at support by filling firt castellation by welding plate in the hole."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "What are lintels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) beams provided in foundation",
            "b) beams on roof of building",
            "c) columns above openings in wall",
            "d) beams above openings in wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Beams provided above the openings in walls to support masonry that comes in between the opening and slab above are called as lintels. It is desirable that lintel is built flush from both the sides of the walls."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "_____ section is suitable for small openings  and _____ section is suitable for large openings",
        "Options": [
            "a) flat, I-section",
            "b) I-section, flat",
            "c) angles, flat",
            "d) angles, angles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flats and plate sections are used for small openings. For openings of moderate dimension, back-to-back angles and inverted T-sections are best options. For large openings, channels, I-sections or built-up sections are preferred. If there is any doubt about lateral support from the wall, I-section with plates can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Design of lintel is carried out for",
        "Options": [
            "a) weight of slab",
            "b) no load is considered from masonry load above the opening",
            "c) small portion of masonry load above the opening",
            "d) large portion of masonry load above the opening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Design loads for lintels are not well defined because it is not certain as how much load from masonry will come over lintel. It is assumed that after setting of mortar, load from masonry is distributed by arch action. Design of lintel is carried out for small portion of masonry load above the opening."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "When the slab over lintel is above apex of equilateral triangle formed on lintel, load of masonry is considered as",
        "Options": [
            "a) rectangular load",
            "b) triangular load",
            "c) trapezoidal load",
            "d) no load is considered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the slab over lintel is above apex of equilateral triangle formed on lintel, the load of masonry in the triangle thus formed is assumed to act over it. When the design load is from triangular portion of masonry , the maximum moment will be  Wl/6, where W =  triangular load from masonry and l = effective span of lintel."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "When the slab over lintel is below apex of equilateral triangle formed on lintel, load of masonry is considered as",
        "Options": [
            "a) rectangular load",
            "b) triangular load",
            "c) trapezoidal load",
            "d) no load is considered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the slab over lintel is below apex of equilateral triangle formed on lintel, the load of masonry in the rectangle is considered. The load of masonry in the rectangle is assumed to act over by taking length equal to span of lintel and height equal to clear height of slab above the lintel."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "What are purlins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) beams provided in foundation",
            "b) beams provided above openings",
            "c) beams provided over trusses to support roofing",
            "d) beams provided on plinth level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Purlins are beams provided over trusses to support sloping roof system between adjacent trusses. Channels, angle sections, and old formed Z-sections are widely used as purlins."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Theoretically, purlins are generally placed at",
        "Options": [
            "a) only at panel points",
            "b) only at edges",
            "c) only at mid span",
            "d) only at corners of roof"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Theoretically, it is desirable to place purlins only at panel points. They are placed at panel points to avoid bending in the top chords of roof trusses. For large trusses, it is more economical to space purlins at closer intervals."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Purlin section is subjected to",
        "Options": [
            "a) not subjected to bending or twisting",
            "b) twisting only",
            "c) symmetrical bending",
            "d) unsymmetrical bending"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The wind force is assumed to act normal to roof truss and gravity load pass through centre of gravity of purlin section. Hence, the purlin section is subjected to twisting in addition to bending. Such bending is called unsymmetrical bending."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "If purlins are assumed to be simply supported, the moments will be",
        "Options": [
            "a) wl2/10",
            "b) wl/8",
            "c) wl/10",
            "d) wl2/8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Purlins can be designed simple, continuous or cantilever beams. If purlins are assumed to be simply supported, the moments will be wl2/8. If they are assumed to be continuous, the moments will be slightly less and taken as wl2/10. IS 800 recommends the purlins to be designed as continuous beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "While erecting channel section purlins, it is desirable that they are erected over rafter with their flange",
        "Options": [
            "a) facing down slope",
            "b) facing up slope",
            "c) does not depend whether up slope or down slope",
            "d) flanges are placed randomly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While erecting angle, channel or I- section purlins, it is desirable that they are erected over rafter with their flange facing up slope. In this position, the twisting moment does not cause any instability. The twisting moment will cause instability if the purlins are kept in such a way that the flanges face the downward slope."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Sag rods are provided at",
        "Options": [
            "a) one-third points between roof trusses",
            "b) end of span",
            "c) two-third points between roof trusses",
            "d) are never provided"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Purlin sections have tendency to sag in the direction of sloping roof . So, sag rods are provided midway or at one-third points between roof trusses to take up the sag."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not true about sag rods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) sag rods are provided at midway or at one-third points between roof trusses",
            "b) these rods reduce the moment  Myy",
            "c) these rods increase the moment  Myy",
            "d) these rods result in smaller purlin sections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sag rods are provided midway or at one-third points between roof trusses to take up the sag in the direction of sloping roof by purlins. These rods provide lateral support with resprct to y-axis bending. Consequently, moment Myy is reduced and thereby result in smaller purlin section. they are useful in keeping the purlins in proper alignment during erection until roofing is installed and connected to purlins."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "When one sag rod is used, the moment about web axis",
        "Options": [
            "a) reduces by 50%",
            "b) increases  by 50%",
            "c) increases by 75%",
            "d) reduces by 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If sag rods are not used, the maximum moment about web axis would be wl2/8. When one sag rod is used, the moments are reduced by 75% and when two sag rods are used at one-third points, the moments are reduced by 91%."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "The maximum bending moment for design of channel/I-section purlin is calculated by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wl/10, where W= concentrated load",
            "b) Wl/8, where W= concentrated load",
            "c) W/10, where W= concentrated load",
            "d) W/8, where W= concentrated load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gravity load, P1 and load due to wind component, H1 are computed. The loads are multiplied by load factors. Thus, P = γfP1, H = γfH1 . The maximum bending moment are calculated as Mz = Pl/10 and My = Hl/10, where P= factored load along z-axis, H = factored load along y-axis, l= span of purlin (c/c distance between adjacent trusses)."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "The required section modulus of the channel/I-section purlin can be determined by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zpz = Myγm0/fy + (b/d)(Mzγm0/fy)",
            "b) Zpz = Mzγm0/fy + (b/d)(Myγm0/fy)",
            "c) Zpz = Mzγm0/fy + 2.5(b/d)(Myγm0/fy)",
            "d) Zpz = Myγm0/fy + 2.5(b/d)(Mzγm0/fy)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The required section modulus of the purlin section can be determined by Zpz = Mzγm0/fy + 2.5(b/d)(Myγm0/fy ), where γm0 is partial safety factor for material = 1.1, d is depth of trial section, b is the breadth of the trial section, Mz and My are factored bending moments about Z and Y axes, respectively, and fy is yield stress of steel. Since the above equation involves b and d of a section, trial section must be used and from the above equation , it is checked whether chosen section is adequate or not."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "The design capacity of channel/I-section purlin is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) M = Zp/fy",
            "b) M = Zpγm0fy",
            "c) M = Zpγm0/fy",
            "d) M = γm0/fy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design capacity of channel/I-section purlin is given by Mdz = Zpzγm0/fy and Mdy = Zpyγm0/fy , Mdz and Mdy are design moment capacity about Z and Y axes, respectively, Zpz and Zpy  are plastic section modulus about Z and Y axes, respectively and fy is yield stress of steel. For safety, design moment capacity should be always greater than or equal to factored bending moments."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "The check for design capacity of channel/I-section purlin is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mdz ≤ 1.2Zeyfy/γm0, Mdy ≤ 2.4Zezfy/γm0",
            "b) Mdz ≤ Zezfy/γm0, Mdy ≤ 1.2Zeyfy/γm0",
            "c) Mdz ≤ γfZeyfy/γm0, Mdy ≤ 1.2Zezfy/γm0",
            "d) Mdz ≤ 1.2Zezfy/γm0, Mdy ≤ γfZeyfy/γm0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The check for design capacity of channel/I-section purlin is given by Mdz ≤ 1.2Zezfy/γm0 , Mdy ≤ γyZeyfy/γm0 , where Mdz and Mdy are design moment capacity about Z and Y axes, respectively, Zez and Zey  are elastic section modulus about Z and Y axes, respectively and fy is yield stress of steel. Since in y-direction, the shape factor Zp/Ze will be greater than 1.2, γf is used instead of 1.2. If 1.2 is used the onset of yielding under unfactored loads cannot be prevented."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Which of the following relation is correct for design of channel/I-section purlin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (Mz/Mdz) + (My/Mdy) ≥ 1",
            "b) (Mz/Mdz) + (My/Mdy) ≤ 1",
            "c) (Mdz/Mz) + (My/Mdy) ≤ 1",
            "d) (Mdz/Mz) + (Mdy/My) ≥ 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The local capacity of the section is checked by interaction equation. It is given by (Mz/Mdz) + (My/Mdy) ≤ 1 , where Mdz and Mdy are design moment capacity about Z and Y axes, respectively, and Mz and My are factored bending moments about Z and Y axes, respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "For which of the following slope of roof truss, angle section purlin can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25˚",
            "b) 50˚",
            "c) 75˚",
            "d) 60˚"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angle sections are unsymmetrical about both the axes. Angle sections can be used as purlin section. provided slope of the roof truss is less than 30˚."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "The modulus of section required for angle section purlin is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Z = M/(0.66xfy)",
            "b) Z = M/(1.33×0.66xfy)",
            "c) Z = M/(1.33×0.66xfy)",
            "d) Z = M/(1.33xfy)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The modulus of section required for angle section purlin is given by Z = M/(1.33×0.66xfy), M = maximum bending moment = wl2/10, w = unfactored uniformly distributed load, l = span of purlin, fy is yield stress. The gravity and wind loads are determined to calculate bending moment and both loads are assumed to be normal to roof truss."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "A plate girder is used when",
        "Options": [
            "a) span is large and loads are heavy",
            "b) span is small and loads are heavy",
            "c) span is small and loads are light",
            "d) span is large and loads are light"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A plate girder is deep flexural member used to carry loads that cannot be economically carried by rolled beams. When load is heavier and span is also large, there are three options : i) two or more I0sections, connected appropriately (ii) plate girder (iii)truss girder. Of the above alternatives, first is uneconomical. So, plate girder or truss girder can be used.  Plate girder is used since cost of fabrication of truss girder is high."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Why plate girder is preferred over truss girder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) plate girder requires costly maintenance",
            "b) higher vertical clearance required for plate girder than truss girder",
            "c) cost of fabrication of plate girder is high",
            "d) cost of fabrication of truss girder is high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When load is heavier and span is also large, either plate girder or truss girder can be used. But, plate girder is preferred because of the disadvantages of truss girder. The disadvantages of truss girder are higher cost of fabrication and erection, problem of vibration and impact, requirements of higher vertical clearance and costly maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Bending resistance of plate girders can be increased by",
        "Options": [
            "a) decreasing distance between flanges",
            "b) increasing distance between flanges",
            "c) reducing distance between flanges to half",
            "d) bending resistance cannot be increased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plate girders are built-up flexural members. Their bending resistance can be increased by increasing the distance between flanges. This also increases the shear resistance as web area increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Which of the following is economical if depth is limited and loads are too large?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rolled section beam",
            "b) truss girder",
            "c) welded box plate girder",
            "d) bolted box plate girder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the loads and span are large, plate girder sections either with riveted/bolted connections or welded connections may be provided. The number of flange plates can be increased depending upon the moment to be resisted. If depth is limited and loads are too large, welded box plate girder is provided. A box girder with riveted/bolted connections can b e provided but it is too costly as compared to welded one. Box girders have great resistance to lateral buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "An ideal bolted plate girder section consists of",
        "Options": [
            "a) flange angles and cover plates for both compression flange and tension flange",
            "b) flange angles and cover plates for compression flange and only flange angle for tension flange",
            "c) only flange angle for compression flange and flange angles and cover plates for tension flange",
            "d) flange angles for both compression flange and tension flange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An ideal bolted plate girder section consists of flange angles and cover plates for compression flange and only flange angle for tension flange. The various elements of riveted/bolted/welded plate girder are : web plate, flange angles with or without cover plates for riveted/bolted plate girder and only flange angles for welded plate girder, stiffeners – bearing, transverse and longitudinal, splices for web and flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "The modes of failure of plate girder are",
        "Options": [
            "a) by yielding of compression flange only",
            "b) by buckling of tension flange only",
            "c) by yielding of tension flange and buckling of compression flange",
            "d) by yielding of compression flange and buckling of tension flange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The limit states considered for plate girder are yielding of tension flange and buckling of compression flange. The compression flange buckling can take place in various ways, such as vertical buckling into the web or flange local buckling. Flange buckling can also be caused due to lateral-torsional buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "At high shear locations in the girder web, principal plane will be ______ to longitudinal axis of member",
        "Options": [
            "a) inclined",
            "b) parallel",
            "c) perpendicular",
            "d) coincides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At high shear locations in the girder web, usually near supports and neutral axis, the principal planes will be inclined to longitudinal axis of the member. The principal stresses will be diagonal tension and diagonal compression along the principal planes."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Which of the following causes web buckling in plate girder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diagonal tension",
            "b) diagonal compression",
            "c) diagonal tension and diagonal compression",
            "d) neither diagonal tension nor diagonal compression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The principal planes will be inclined to longitudinal axis of the member at high shear locations in the girder web. Along the principal planes, the principal stresses will be diagonal tension and diagonal compression. Diagonal tension does not cause any problem but diagonal compression causes the web to buckle in the direction perpendicular to its action."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct for reducing web buckling due to diagonal compression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) not providing web stiffeners to increase shear strength",
            "b) providing web stiffeners to reduce shear strength",
            "c) increasing depth-to-thickness ratio",
            "d) reducing depth-to-thickness ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Diagonal compression causes web to buckle in the direction perpendicular to its action. This problem can be solved by any of the following ways : (i) reduce depth-to-thickness ratio of web such that problem is eliminated, (ii) provide web stiffeners to form panels that would enhance shear strength of web, (iii) provide web stiffeners to form panels that would develop tension field action to resist diagonal compression. "
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct during tension field action?",
        "Options": [
            "a) web can resist diagonal compression",
            "b) horizontal component of diagonal compression is supported by flanges",
            "c) vertical component of diagonal compression is supported by flanges",
            "d) vertical component of diagonal compression is supported by stiffeners"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As web begins to buckle , the web loses its ability to resist diagonal compression. The diagonal compression is transferred to transverse stiffeners and flanges. The vertical component of diagonal compression is supported by stiffeners and horizontal component is resisted by flanges. The web resists only diagonal tension and this behaviour of web is called tension field action."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Which of the statement is not true about intermediate stiffeners?",
        "Options": [
            "a) they reduce shear capacity of web",
            "b) they improve shear capacity of web",
            "c) they can be used to develop tension field action",
            "d) their main purpose is to provide stiffness to the web"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Intermediate stiffeners can be used to develop tension field action and improve shear capacity of web. The main purpose of these stiffeners is to provide stiffness to the web rather than to resist the applied loads. Additional stiffeners called bearing stiffeners are provided at points of concentrated loads to protect the web from the direct compressive loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "The depth-to-thickness ratio of web connected to flanges along one longitudinal edge only when transverse stiffeners are not provided is _____ to meet serviceability criteria.",
        "Options": [
            "a) >180ε",
            "b) ≥90ε",
            "c) ≤90ε",
            "d) >90ε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When transverse stiffeners are not provided, the depth-to-thickness ratio of web connected to flanges along one longitudinal edge only is ≤ 90ε and when web connected to flanges along both longitudinal edges is ≤ 200ε to meet the serviceability criteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "The depth-to-thickness ratio of web when only transverse stiffeners are provided and 3d ≥ c ≥d, where c is clear distance between stiffeners and d is depth of web is_____ to meet serviceability criteria",
        "Options": [
            "a) ≤ 200εw",
            "b) ≥ 200 εw",
            "c) > 200 εw",
            "d) ≤ 400 εw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For serviceability criteria, when only transverse stiffeners are provided, the depth-to-thickness ratio of web should be ≤ 200 εw, when 3d ≥ c ≥d and for c > 3d, the web is considered as unstiffened, where c is clear distance between stiffeners and d is depth of web, εw = √(250/fyw), fyw is yield stress of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": " The depth-to-thickness ratio of web when only transverse stiffeners are provided and c < 0.74d, where c is clear distance between stiffeners and d is depth of web is_____ to meet serviceability criteria",
        "Options": [
            "a) ≤ 200 εw",
            "b) ≥ 270 εw",
            "c) > 200 εw",
            "d) ≤ 270 εw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For serviceability criteria, when only transverse stiffeners are provided, the depth-to-thickness ratio of web should be ≤ 270 εw when c < 0.74d and c/tw ≤ 200 εw, when 0.74d ≤ c ≤d, where c is clear distance between stiffeners and d is depth of web, εw = √(250/fyw), fyw is yield stress of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "What is the range of c to meet serviceability criteria when transverse and longitudinal stiffeners are provided at one level only, at 0.2d from compression flange and c/tw ≤ 250 εw ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) c < 0.74d",
            "b) 0.74d ≤ c ≤ d",
            "c) c ≥ d",
            "d) c > 2d"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For serviceability criteria, when transverse and longitudinal stiffeners are provided at one level only, at 0.2d from compression flange d/tw ≤ 250 εw for 2.4d ≥c ≥ d, c/tw ≤ 250 εw for 0.74d ≤ c ≤ d and d/tw ≤ 340 εw for c < 0.74d, where c is clear distance between stiffeners and d is depth of web, εw = √(250/fyw), fyw is yield stress of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "When second longitudinal stiffener is provided, d/tw to meet serviceability criteria is",
        "Options": [
            "a) ≤ 400 εw",
            "b) ≥ 400 εw",
            "c) > 800 εw",
            "d) ≤ 800 εw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When second longitudinal stiffener is provided at neutral axis, d/tw ≤ 400 εw to meet serviceability criteria, where d is depth of web, εw = √(250/fyw), fyw is yield stress of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "When a plate girder bends, vertical compression in web is due to",
        "Options": [
            "a) downward vertical component of compression flange bending stress only",
            "b) downward vertical component of tension flange bending stress only",
            "c) downward vertical component of compression flange and upward vertical component of tension flange bending stress",
            "d) upward vertical component of compression flange and downward vertical component of tension flange bending stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When a plate girder bends, its curvature creates vertical compression in web is due to downward vertical component of compression flange and upward vertical component of tension flange bending stress. The web must have sufficient vertical buckling strength to withstand this squeezing effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "The d/tw should be ___ to avoid buckling of compression flange into web when transverse stiffeners are not provided",
        "Options": [
            "a) ≥ 500 εf2",
            "b) ≤ 345 εf2",
            "c) ≥ 345 εf2",
            "d) ≤ 500 εf2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To avoid buckling of compression flange into web when transverse stiffeners are not provided, d/tw ≤ 345 εf2, where d is depth of web, εf = √(250/fyf), fyf is yield stress of compression flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "When only transverse stiffeners are provided and d/tw < 345 εf to meet compression flange buckling criteria, the range of c should be",
        "Options": [
            "a) c ≥ 4.5d",
            "b) c > 3d",
            "c) c > 1.5d",
            "d) c < 1.5d"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To avoid buckling of compression flange into web, d/tw ≤ 345 εf2 for c ≥ 1.5d, d/tw < 345 εf  for c < 1.5d when only transverse stiffeners are provided, where c is clear distance between stiffeners, d is depth of web, εf = √(250/fyf), fyf is yield stress of compression flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "The optimum depth of web of plate girder is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) (k/fy)0.33",
            "b) (Mzk/fy)",
            "c) (Mzk/fy)0.33",
            "d) (Mzk/fy)2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The depth of plate girder for which area of steel used is minimum and will have minimum weight is called optimum depth. It is given by (Mzk/fy)0.33, Mz is moment resisted entirely by flanges, k = d/tw, d is depth of web, tw is thickness of web, fy = design strength of flanges."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "The minimum area of flange angles with cover plate for riveted/ bolted plate girder should be",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/6th of calculated flange area",
            "b) 1/3rd of calculated flange area",
            "c) 1/8th of calculated flange area",
            "d) 1/4th of calculated flange area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flanges of riveted/ bolted plate girder consists of pair of angles with or without cover plates. The flange angles should form as large part of the area of the flange as practicable and preferably not less than 1/3rd of the calculated flange area to keep the centre of gravity of flange within back of angles and not in the flange cover plate else stability is affected."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Which of the following angle should be ideally used in bolted plate girder flange?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bulb angle",
            "b) equal angle",
            "c) unequal angle with short leg horizontal",
            "d) unequal angle with long leg horizontal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Unequal angles with long leg horizontal are preferred. It is because the moment of inertia of the section will be more and a large length will be available for making the connection with the flange plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "For which of the following cases are equal angles preferred in bolted plate girder flange?",
        "Options": [
            "a) when large number of connectors are required to connect flange angle to web",
            "b) when very few number of connectors are required to connect flange angle to web",
            "c) for reducing cost",
            "d) for aesthetic  appearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When shear is heavy, large number of connectors are required to connect flange angle to web. In such case, equal angles may be preferred, if unequal angles are used, the longer leg msy be placed parallel to the web."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Flange cover plates are used in plate girder when",
        "Options": [
            "a) flange cover plates are not used",
            "b) for aesthetic appearance",
            "c) when moment resisting capacity has to be increased",
            "d) when moment resisting capacity has to be decreased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When moment resisting capacity of the plate girder has to be increased, flange cover plates are provided over flange angles. The moment of inertia and consequently the moment resisting capacity of the girder is increased considerably as the flange cover plates are at the greatest distance from neutral axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "The thickness of flange cover plate should be ______ flange angle in bolted connections",
        "Options": [
            "a) less",
            "b) more",
            "c) twice",
            "d) can be more or less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flange cover plates should not be thicker than the flange angles in riveted/bolted connections. Hence, more than one plate may be required. It is preferred that all cover plates should have same thickness. If they are of different thickness, then outer plates should not be thicker thin the inner plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "The shear capacity of web comprises of strength",
        "Options": [
            "a) before onset of buckling strength only",
            "b) post buckling strength only",
            "c) before onset of buckling strength and post buckling strength",
            "d) compression strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shear capacity of web comprises of strength before onset of buckling strength and post buckling strength. strength before onset of buckling is contributed because of elastic behaviour wherein stresses are entirely elastic and the only requirement for the stiffeners is to keep the web flat."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "What will happen when d/tw is sufficiently low?",
        "Options": [
            "a) web will yield under buckling before shear",
            "b) web will yield under shear before buckling",
            "c) web will not yield under shear",
            "d) web will not yield under both shear and buckling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When d/tw ratio is sufficiently low, the elastic critical stress increases above the value of yield shear stress and the web will yield under shear before buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "The nominal shear strength according to simple post-critical method is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Av",
            "b) Avτb",
            "c) τb",
            "d) Av /τb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Simple post-critical method based on the shear buckling strength can be used for web of I-section girders, with or without intermediate transverse stiffeners, provided that web has transverse stiffeners at the supports. The nominal shear strength is given by Vn=  Avτb, where Av = area of web, τb = shear stress corresponding to web buckling."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "The value of τb in the nominal shear strength equation according to simple post-critical method is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) fyw / √ λw",
            "b) fyw/λw",
            "c) fyw/λw²",
            "d) fyw/(√3 λw²)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of τb in the nominal shear strength equation according to simple post-critical method is given by τb = fyw/√3 for λw ≤0.8, [1-0.8(λw -0.8)](fyw/√3) for 0.8 < λw<1.2, fyw/(√3 λw²) for λw ≥1.2, where fyw is yield strength of web, λw is non-dimensional web slenderness ratio for shear buckling stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "The value of non-dimensional web slenderness ratio in the nominal shear strength equation according to simple post-critical method is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) √(fyw/(√3τcr,e))",
            "b) (fyw/(√3τcr,e))",
            "c) (fyw/(τcr,e))",
            "d) (fyw/(√3τcr,e))2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of non-dimensional web slenderness ratio in the nominal shear strength equation according to simple post-critical method is given by λw =√(fyw/(√3τcr,e)), where fyw is yield strength of web, τcr,e is elastic critical shear stress of the web."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "The elastic critical shear stress of the web is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) kvπ2/[12(1+μ2)(d/tw)2].",
            "b) kvπ2E/[12(1+μ2)(d/tw)2].",
            "c) kvπ2E/[12(1-μ2)(d/tw)2].",
            "d) kvE/[12(1-μ2)(d/tw)]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The elastic critical shear stress of the web is given by τcr,e = kvπ2E/[12(1-μ2)(d/tw)2], where E is elastic modulus, μ is Poisson’s ratio, kv is constant which depends on spacing of transverse stiffeners and depth of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "The value of kv in the elastic critical shear stress equation for c/d < 1 is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.0 – [5.35/(c/d)].",
            "b) 4.0 + [5.35/(c/d)2].",
            "c) 5.35 + [4/(c/d)2].",
            "d) 5.35 – [4/(c/d)]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of kv in the elastic critical shear stress equation is given by kv = 5.35 when transverse stiffeners are provided only at supports, kv = 4.0 + [5.35/(c/d)2] for c/d < 1.0, kv = 5.35 + [4/(c/d)2] for c/d ≥ 1.0, where c and d are spacing of transverse stiffeners and depth of web respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditions are true when tension field method is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) it is based on pre-buckling strength",
            "b) c/d < 1.0",
            "c) it may not be used for webs with intermediate stiffeners",
            "d) it may be used for webs with intermediate stiffeners"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tension field method, based on the post-shear buckling strength, may be used for webs with intermediate transverse stiffeners at supports, provided the panels adjacent to the panel angle tension field action or the end posts provide anchorage for the tension field and is c/d>1.0. "
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "What is the value of nominal shear strength according to tension field method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Avτb",
            "b) 0.9wtftwfvsinφ",
            "c) Avτb – 0.9wtftwfvsinφ",
            "d) Avτb + 0.9wtftwfvsinφ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In tension field method, the nominal shear strength is given by Vn = Avτb + 0.9wtftfvsinφ, where Av is area of web, τb is buckling strength or shear stress corresponding to web buckling, fv is yield strength of tension field which depends on inclination of tension field, wtf is the width of tension field, tw is width of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "The value of fv in the nominal shear strength according to tension field method is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) [fyw2+3 τb2+Ψ2]0.5+Ψ",
            "b) [fyw2-3 τb2+Ψ2]0.5-Ψ",
            "c) [fyw2-3 τb2-Ψ2] -Ψ",
            "d) [fyw2+3 τb2+Ψ2]+Ψ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of fv in the nominal shear strength according to tension field method is given by fv = [fyw2-3 τb2+Ψ2]0.5-Ψ , where fyw is yield stress of web, τb is buckling strength or shear stress corresponding to web buckling, Ψ is a parameter which depends on inclination of tension field and buckling strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "What is the expression for Ψ in the fv for nominal shear strength according to tension field method is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 τb sin2φ",
            "b) sin2φ",
            "c) 1.5 τb",
            "d) 1.5 τb /sin2φ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of Ψ in the fv for nominal shear strength according to tension field method is given by Ψ =1.5 τb sin2φ, where τb is buckling strength or shear stress corresponding to web buckling, φ is inclination of tension field which depends on depth of web and spacing of stiffeners."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "The inclination of tension field is",
        "Options": [
            "a) tan(c/d)",
            "b) tan(d/c)",
            "c) tan-1(c/d)",
            "d) tan-1(d/c)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The inclination of tension field is given by φ = tan-1(d/c), where d is depth of web and c is spacing between stiffeners. The change in angle of inclination of tension field affects the width and yield strength of tension field."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an expression for width of tension field?",
        "Options": [
            "a) wtf = d sinφ + (c-sc-st)cosφ",
            "b) wtf = d cosφ + (c-sc-st)sinφ",
            "c) wtf = d cosφ – (c+sc-st)sinφ",
            "d) wtf = d sinφ – (c+sc-st)cosφ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The width of tension field in the tension field action method is given by wtf = d cosφ + (c-sc-st)sinφ, where d is depth of beam, φ = inclination of tension field = tan-1(d/c), c is spacing between stiffeners, sc and st   are anchorage lengths of tension field along the compression and tension flanges respectively and depends on reduced plastic moment capacity, inclination of tension field, thickness of web and yield stress of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "The anchorage length of tension field is",
        "Options": [
            "a) s = (2 sinφ)(Mfr/fywtw)0.5",
            "b) s = (2/ sinφ)(Mfr/fywtw)",
            "c) s = (2/ sinφ)(Mfr/fywtw)0.5",
            "d) s = (2/ sinφ)(Mfrfywtw)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The anchorage length of tension field is s = (2/ sinφ)(Mfr/fywtw)0.5 where φ = inclination of tension field = tan-1(d/c), c is spacing between stiffeners, d is depth of beam, Mfr is reduced plastic moment capacity of the respective flange plate, fyw is yield stress of web and tw is thickness of web. The anchorage length should be less than or equal to spacing between stiffeners."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which of the following expression for reduced plastic moment capacity is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mfr = 0.25bftf2fyf {1-[Nf/( bftffyf/γm0)2]}",
            "b) Mfr = bftffyf {1-[Nf/( bftffyf/γm0)]}",
            "c) Mfr = 0.25bftf {1+[Nf/( bftffyf/γm0)]}",
            "d) Mfr = 0.25bf {1+[Nf( bftffyfγm0)2]}"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reduced plastic moment capacity of respective flange plate is calculated after accounting for axial force in flange, due to overall bending and any external axial force in the cross section. It is given by Mfr = 0.25bftf2fyf {1-[Nf/( bftffyf/γm0)2]}, where bf and tf are width and thickness of flange respectively, fyf is yield stress of flange and Nf is the axial force in flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "The function of bearing stiffener is to",
        "Options": [
            "a) improve buckling strength of web",
            "b) preclude any crushing of web",
            "c) restrain against torsional effects",
            "d) increase buckling resistance of web"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The function of bearing stiffener is to preclude any crushing of web at locations of heavy concentrated loads. Thus, they transfer heavy reactions or concentrated loads to the full depth of web. They are placed in pairs on the web of plate girders at unframed girder ends and where required for concentrated loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "2. Match the following<div class=\"hk1_style-wrap4\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap3\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap2\"><div class=\"hk1_style-wrap\"><div class=\"hk1_style\"><div class=\"txt\"><pre class=\"de1\">\tStiffeners\t\t\t\tFunction\nA) Load carrying stiffener\t\t(i) increases buckling resistance of web\nB) Torsional stiffener\t\t\t(ii) local strengthening of web\nC) Diagonal stiffener\t\t\t(iii) prevent local buckling of web\nD) Tension stiffener\t\t\t(iv) restrain against torsional effects\nE) Longitudinal stiffener\t\t(v) transmit tensile forces</pre></div></div></div></div></div></div>",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-i, B-ii, C-iii, D-iv, E-v",
            "b) A-v, B-iv, C-iii, D-ii, E-i",
            "c) A-iv, B-v, C-i, D-ii, E-iii",
            "d) A-iii, B-iv, C-ii, D-v, E-i"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Load carrying stiffener prevents local buckling of web due to any concentrated load. Torsional stiffener are provided at supports to restrain girders against torsional effects. Local strengthening of web under the combination of shear and bending is provided by diagonal stiffeners. The tensile forces from the flange are transmitted to the web through the tension stiffener. A longitudinal stiffener increases the buckling resistance of web."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "The outstand of stiffener from face of web is restricted to",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20tq/ε",
            "b) 120tqε",
            "c) 20tqε",
            "d) 50tqε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Unless the outer edge is continuously stiffened, the outstand of stiffener from face of web should not exceed 20tqε,where tq is thickness of stiffener. When the outstands of web is between 14tqε and 20tqε, then the stiffener design should be on the basis of a core section with an outstand of 14tqε."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "What is the stiff bearing length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) length which cannot deform appreciably in bending",
            "b) length which deform appreciably in bending",
            "c) length of outer end of flange",
            "d) length of web"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stiff bearing length of any element b1 is that length which cannot deform appreciably in bending. To determine b1, the dispersion of load through a steel bearing element should be taken as 45˚ through solid material, such as bearing plates, flange plates, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "The effective length of web on each side of centreline of stiffeners for interior stiffeners is limited to",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 tw",
            "b) 50 tw",
            "c) 40 tw",
            "d) 15 tw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The effective length of web on each side of centreline of stiffeners is limited to 20 times the web thickness, i.e. 40tw for interior stiffeners and 20tw for end stiffeners . The effective section is the full area or core area of stiffener together with effective length of web on each side of centreline of stiffeners."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "The effective length of intermediate transverse stiffener is taken as",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 times the length of stiffener",
            "b) 0.7 times the length of stiffener",
            "c) 1.4 times the length of stiffener",
            "d) 0.5 times the length of stiffener"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The effective length of intermediate transverse stiffener is taken as 0.7 times the length of stiffener. The intermediate transverse stiffener is provided mainly to improve shear buckling resistance of the web."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "The second moment of area of transverse web stiffeners not subjected to external loads or moments is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) Is ≤ 0.75dtw2",
            "b) Is ≥ 0.75dtw2",
            "c) Is ≤ 1.5dtw2",
            "d) Is ≥ 12.5dtw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transverse stiffeners not subjected to external loads or moments should have second moment of area Is about centreline of the web, if stiffeners are on both sides of the web and about face of the web, if stiffener is on only one side of the web such that Is ≥ 0.75dtw2 for c/d ≥ √2 and Is ≥ 1.5dtw2/c2 for c/d < √2."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Which of the following buckling check is applied to stiffeners?",
        "Options": [
            "a) [(V+Vc)/γm0] ≤ Fqd",
            "b) [(V+Vc)γm0] ≥ Fqd",
            "c) [(V-Vc)/γm0] ≤ Fqd",
            "d) [(V-Vc)γm0] ≥ Fqd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stiffeners not subjected to external loads or moments should be checked for buckling for a force Fd = [(V-Vc)/γm0] ≤ Fqd, where Fqd is design resistance of intermediate stiffeners, V is factored shear force adjacent to the stiffener, Vcr is shear buckling resistance of the web panel designed without using tension field action. This check is required for intermediate stiffeners only when tension field action is utilized in webs."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "The interaction expression for stiffeners subjected to external loads or moments is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) [(Fq-Fs)/Fqd]+(Fs/Fsd)+(Mq/Myq) < 1",
            "b) [(Fq-Fs)/Fqd]+(Fs/Fsd)+(Mq/Myq) > 1",
            "c) [(Fq-Fs)/Fqd]-(Fs/Fsd)-(Mq/Myq) < 1",
            "d) [(Fq+Fs)/Fqd]-(Fs/Fsd)-(Mq/Myq) > 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stiffeners subjected to external loads and moments should meet the conditions of load carrying stiffeners. In addition, they should satisfy the following interaction equation: [(Fq-Fs)/Fqd]+(Fs/Fsd)+(Mq/Myq) < 1, where Fq is stiffener force, Fqd is design resistance of intermediate stiffeners corresponding to buckling about axis parallel to the web, Fs is external load or reaction at stiffener, Fsd is design resistance of load carrying stiffener corresponding to buckling about axis parallel to the web, Md is moment on the stiffener due to eccentrically applied load and transverse load, Myq is yield moment capacity of stiffener based on its elastic modulus about its centroidal axis parallel to the web."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true regarding longitudinal stiffeners?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal stiffeners increase buckling resistance considerably as compared to transverse stiffeners",
            "b) they consist of plane section for welded plate girder",
            "c) first horizontal stiffener is provide at one-fifth of distance from compression flange",
            "d) first horizontal stiffener is provide at neutral axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Longitudinal stiffeners are also called horizontal stiffeners. They increase buckling resistance considerably as compared to transverse stiffeners when the web is subjected to buckling. They consist of angle section for riveted/bolted plate girder and plane section for welded plate girder and are provided in the compression zone of the web. The first horizontal stiffener is provide at one-fifth of distance from compression flange to tension flange. If required another stiffener is provided at the neutral axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "The connection of intermediate transverse stiffeners are designed for shear of",
        "Options": [
            "a) twbs",
            "b) tw2/5bs",
            "c) tw25bs",
            "d) tw5bs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Intermediate transverse stiffeners not subjected to external loading should be connected to the web so as to withstand a shear between each component of the stiffener and the web not less than tw2/5bs, where tw is thickness of web, bs is outstand width of stiffener."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "The second moment of area of torsional stiffeners about center line of the web is given as",
        "Options": [
            "a) Is ≤ αssD3",
            "b) Is ≤ 0.34αsD3Tcf",
            "c) Is ≥ 0.34αsD3Tcf",
            "d) Is ≥ αsD3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When bearing stiffeners are required to provide torsional restraint at the support of the beams, the second moment of area of the stiffener section about center line of the web should be such that Is ≥ 0.34αsD3Tcf , where αs = 0.006 for LLT/ry ≤50, 0.3/( LLT/ry) for 50< LLT/ry≤100, 30/( LLT/ry)2 for LLT/ry ≥100, D = overall depth of beam at the support, Tcf = maximum thickness of compression flange in the span under consideration, KL = laterally unsupported effective length of compression flange of beam, ry = radius of gyration of the beam about minor axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct regarding gantry girders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is laterally supported except at the columns",
            "b) It is subjected to impact load",
            "c) It should not be analysed for unsymmetrical bending",
            "d) It is not subjected to longitudinal load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gantry girder are different from beams in buildings. It is generally laterally unsupported except at the columns. It is subjected to impact load. It must be analysed for unsymmetrical bending because of lateral thrust from the starting and stopping of the crab. It is subjected to longitudinal load due to starting and stopping of crane bridge itself. They are always simply supported."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Which of the following loads are not considered in the design of gantry girders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal loads",
            "b) gravity loads",
            "c) lateral loads",
            "d) wind loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The loads considered in the design of gantry girders are vertical loads or gravity loads, longitudinal loads, lateral loads and impact loads. The vertical force is the reaction from crane girder, acting vertically downward. The longitudinal thrust is due to starting and stopping of crane acting in longitudinal direction. The lateral thrust is due to starting and stopping of the crab acting horizontally normal to the gantry girder."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "The wheel load transferred from trolley to gantry girder is given by",
        "Options": [
            "a) W1 = [Wt(Lc+L1)]/(2Lc)",
            "b) W1 = [Wt(Lc-L1)](2Lc)",
            "c) W1 = [Wt(Lc-L1)]/(2Lc)",
            "d) W1 = [Wt(Lc+L1)]/( Lc)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since trolley moves on the crane girder along the span of truss, its weight is transferred to the crane wheels as the axle load and finally to gantry girder. The wheel load transferred from trolley to gantry girder is given by W1 = [Wt(Lc-L1)]/(2Lc), where W1 is load of each wheel on gantry girder, Wt is weight of trolley or crab car, Lc is distance between gantry giders, L1 is distance between centre of gravity of trolley and gantry."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "For gantry girders carrying electrically operated overhead travelling cranes, the lateral forces are increased by ____ for impact allowance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10% of weight of crab and weight lifted on the crane",
            "b) 20% of weight of crab and weight lifted on the crane",
            "c) 25% of maximum static wheel load",
            "d) 50% of maximum static wheel load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For gantry girders carrying electrically operated overhead travelling cranes, the lateral forces are increased by 10% of weight of crab for impact allowance and weight lifted on the crane. The vertical forces can be increased by 25% of maximum static wheel load."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "For gantry girders carrying hand operated cranes, the vertical forces are increased by____ for impact allowance",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10% of maximum static wheel load",
            "b) 25% of maximum static wheel load",
            "c) 10% of weight of crab and weight lifted on the crane",
            "d) 20% of weight of crab and weight lifted on the crane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For gantry girders carrying hand operated cranes, the vertical forces are increased by 10% of maximum static wheel load  for impact allowance. The lateral forces can be increased by 5% of weight of crab and weight lifted on the crane."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Fatigue effect for light and medium duty cranes need not be checked if",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nsc > 10×106 [(27/γmft)/γmt].",
            "b) Nsc < 5×106 [(27/γmft)/γmt]3",
            "c) Nsc > 5×106 [(27/γmft)/γmt]2",
            "d) Nsc < 5×106 [(27/γmft)γmt]."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fatigue effect for light and medium duty cranes need not be checked if normal and shear design stress ranges f ≤ (27/γmft) or if actual number of stress cycles, Nsc < 5×106 [(27/γmft)/γmt]3, where f = actual fatigue stress range, γmft = partial safety factor for strength, γmf = partial safety factor for material = 1.10."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "The maximum wheel load is obtained when",
        "Options": [
            "a) crane crab is farthest to gantry girder",
            "b) crane crab is closest to gantry girder",
            "c) crane crab is not attached",
            "d) crane crab is at mid span"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The maximum wheel load is obtained when crane crab is closest to gantry girder. The crab in such position on the crane girder gives maximum reaction on the gantry girder. The vertical reaction of crane girder is transferred through its two wheels on to the gantry girder. Therefore, the maximum wheel load is half of this reaction. This maximum wheel load is then increased for impact and used for design of gantry girder."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "The bending moment due to dead load of girder is maximum at",
        "Options": [
            "a) one-third distance at span",
            "b) two-third distance at span",
            "c) end of span",
            "d) centre of span"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bending moment considered in the design of gantry girder are the bending moment due to maximum wheel loads (with impact) and the bending moment due to dead load of the girder and rails.  The bending moment due to dead loads is maximum at the centre of span. "
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "What is the maximum vertical deflection allowed for a gantry girder where the cranes are manually operated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L/500",
            "b) L/700",
            "c) L/600",
            "d) L/800"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The vertical deflection of gantry girder where the cranes are manually operated should not exceed L/500, where L is the span of gantry girder. The maximum vertical deflection allowed for a gantry girder where the cranes are travelling overhead and operated electrically upto 500kN is L/750 and operated electrically over 500kN is L/1000. When gantry girders carry moving loads such as charging cars, the deflection should not exceed L/600."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "The minimum recommended rise of trusses with Galvanised Iron sheets is",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 12",
            "b) 1 in 6",
            "c) 1 in 10",
            "d) 1 in 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pitch of truss depends upon the roofing material. The minimum recommended rise of trusses with galvanised iron sheets is 1 in 6 and with asbestos cement sheets is 1 in 12."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "The economic spacing of roof truss depends on",
        "Options": [
            "a) cost of purlins only",
            "b) cost of purlins and cost of roof covering",
            "c) dead loads",
            "d) cost of roof covering and dead loads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The economic spacing of the truss is the spacing that makes the overall cost of trusses, purlins, roof coverings, columns, etc. the minimum. It depends upon the relative cost of trusses, purlins, roof coverings, spacing of columns, etc. If the spacing is large, the cost of these trusses per unit area decreases but the cost of purlin increases. But if the spacing of trusses is small, the cost of trusses per unit area increases. Roof coverings cost more if the spacing of trusses is large."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for economic spacing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cost of trusses should be equal to twice the cost of purlins",
            "b) cost of trusses should be equal to twice the cost of purlins minus cost of roof coverings",
            "c) cost of trusses should be equal to the cost of purlins plus cost of roof coverings",
            "d) cost of trusses should be equal to twice the cost of purlins plus cost of roof coverings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For economic spacing of roof trusses, the cost of trusses should be equal to twice the cost of purlins plus cost of roof coverings. This equation is used for checking the spacing of trusses and not for design of trusses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Which of the following load combination is not considered for design of roof trusses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dead load + crane load",
            "b) Dead load + wind load",
            "c) Dead load + earthquake load",
            "d) Dead load + live load + wind load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Earthquake loads are not significant for roof trusses because of the small self weights. The following load combinations can be considered : (i) Dead load + snow load, (ii) Dead load + partial/full live load, (iii) dead load + live load + internal positive air pressure, (iv) dead load + live load + internal suction air pressure, (v) dead load + live load + wind load."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Live load for roof truss should not be less than",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4kN/m2",
            "b) 0.2kN/m2",
            "c) 0.75kN/m2",
            "d) 0.8kN/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The live load for roof truss should not be less than 0.4kN/m2. For roof slopes ≤ 10o and access provided, the live load to be taken is 1.5kN/m2 of plan area. For roof slopes > 10o and access is not provided , the live load to be taken is 0.75kN/m2 of plan area."
    }
]